<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/14.pdf</file>
	<title>Physical Studies on Calcium Phosphate and Barium Citrate Used as Clotting-Factor Adsorbents</title>
	<date>Unknown</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/14.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>Susan Deacon</author>
		<author>Roy Howell</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>the pH range 2-6. From pH6 to 10.2 the mobilities of the protein-coated high-density particles accelerated to a level 35 % greater, at pH8.2, than the low-density particles.</abstract>
	<methods/>
	<full_text>Inorganic precipitates, containing Ca2+ or BaZ+ cations, have been used extensively in purification procedures for removing the vitamin K-dependent clotting factors from serum or plasma. The prothrombin group, which consists of factors 11, VII, IX and X, contains the modified amino acid y-carboxyglutamic acid which is responsible for the high cation-binding capacity of these proteins (Stenflo et al., 1974).

We have examined the crystalline structure and charge of these inorganic compounds more closely, by scanning electron microscopy and particle electrophoresis, in an attempt to relate physical properties and chemical composition to their properties as clotting-factor adsorbents. The present investigation on the physical properties of calciumphosphate and bariumcitrate is similar to our previous study of BaS04asaclottingfactor adsorbent (Howell &amp; Deacon, 1975). The electrophoretic mobility of particles of various adsorbents was measured at 25°C in 0.02~-barbitone buffer over the pH range 2-1 1 by the procedure of Bangham et al. (1958).

Despite differences in morphology, various grades of BaSO,, in the former study, gave similar pH-mobility curves, since the internal composition of the crystal remains relatively constant. Incontrast, the present study showed a considerable shift in theshape of the pH-mobility curves from one adsorbent to another. This suggests that a change in the anionic component exerts more influence on particle charge than either of the cation components.

The origin of surface charge is complex and still rather obscure, but the sparingly soluble salts of calcium and barium can be separated into two groups according to the presence, or absence, of a charge reversal point in the pH-mobility curve. The charge characteristics for calcium phosphate gel (obtained from British Drug Houses, Poole, Dorsct, U.K.) and hydroxyapatite (Tiselius et al., 1956) (Fig. 1) are similar to those for various grades of BaSO, (Howell &amp; Deacon, 1975). Apart from minor variations, the bimodal curve is composed of regions of positive and negative mobility on either side of a charge-reversal region. Factors contributing to this characteristic shape are adsorption of protons and free cations from the medium on the crystal lattice creating a positive potential and, as the pH increases, complexing of organic ions from the buffer causing a negative charge. The chemical composition of calcium phosphate is variable and in addition to the tricalcium orthophosphate form Ca3(P04)2, substitution of water and hydroxyl ions in the crystal lattice may result in the formation of brushite, CaHPO,, 2 H 2 0 or hydroxyapatite, Ca5(P04)30H. Similarities between the curves in Fig. 1 suggest that the 'gel' form contains a considerable amount of hydroxyapatite, although vast differences in morphologywere seen byscanningelectron microscopy (Deacon &amp; Howell, 1976). Micrographs of hydroxyapatite showed small well-defined crystal agglomerations in contrast with the irregular and totally amorphous particles seen for samples of calcium phosphate gel, specified for enzyme adsorption. The gel was freeze-dried to retain as much as possible of the hydrated structure for scanning electron microscopy, but the porous nature necessary for the separation of proteins was indiscernible, even at high magnifications. Both adsorbents take up serum proteins in relatively large amounts (Howell &amp; Deacon, 1976), but, in contrast with high-density BaS04, neither has been found to induce factor X activation (Howell &amp;Dupe, 1972).

The charge characteristics of a sparingly soluble salt can be altered when an ion is preferentially adsorbed on the surface (Reyerson et al., 1947;Morimoto, 1964). In this respect some ions have a more pronounced effect than others and these are known as potential-determining ions. Morimoto (1964) and Reyerson et al. (1947) found that citrate ions altered the surface potential of BaS0, to a high negative value, which they attributed to the formation of a barium citrate complex on the surface. It has also been reported (Morimoto, 1964;Tokiwa &amp; Imamura, 1969) that the negative mobility of colloidal particles was unexpectedly high when phosphate ions were adsorbed from solution. These results reflect our observations on particles composed entirely of barium citrate or calcium orthophosphate which possess either a zero or negative potential over the pH range 3-1 1 (Fig. 2). These monophasic curves are typical of a surface in which the potential-determing group is either a carboxyl or phosphate ion (Goddard, 1970), and the indications are that the negatively charged tervalent citrate or phosphate ions suppress the positive potential of the bivalent cation in a crystal lattice. This suppression may prevent cation chelation by y-carboxyglutamic acid residues, a theory supported by the finding that the vitamin K-dependent clotting factors show very little affinity for calcium orthophosphate or commercial barium citrate (Howell &amp; Deacon, 1976). Scanning-electron-microscopic studies on calcium orthophosphate showed irregular flaky amorphous plaques with crystalline edges visible at higher magnifications, and little or no activation has been reported for this adsorbent. The finding that commercial barium citrate is composed of large non-porous crystals, reminiscent of high-density BaSO,, was a surprising anomaly, since it has not been reported to induce activation of factor X. A possible explanation may be that since barium citrate is precipitated in situ during the purification procedures (Radcliffe &amp; Nernerson, 1 9 7 3 , incorporation of clotting factors into the crystal lattice (Tishkoff et al., 1968) protects the protein from activation.</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Nature</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Professor</author>
				<author>James</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1958</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Thromb. Haemosfas</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Deacon</author>
				<author>R Howell</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1976</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title/>
			<authors>
				<author>G Goddard</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1970</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Thromb. Diarh. Haemorrh</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Howell</author>
				<author>S Deacon</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1975</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochem. SOC. Trans</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Howell</author>
				<author>S Deacon</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1976</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Thromb. Diarh. Haernorrh. 2</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Howell</author>
				<author>R Dupe</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1972</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Bull. Chem. SOC. Jpn</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Morimoto</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1964</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Biol. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Radcliffe</author>
				<author>Y Nernerson</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1975</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Phys. Colloid Chern</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Reyerson</author>
				<author>I Kolthoff</author>
				<author>K Coad</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1947</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
</document>
