<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/4. lecture Continuous functions.pdf</file>
	<title>4. lecture Continuous functions</title>
	<date>Unknown</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/4. lecture Continuous functions.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors/>
	<abstract/>
	<methods/>
	<full_text>Prof. Inese Bula
University of Latvia
Faculty of Physics, Mathematics and Optometry
Lecture Notes
«Matemātiskā analīze I»
CALCULUS I
Doc. Līga Zariņa
University of Latvia
Faculty of Computing

Dr. Līga Zariņa
Researcher
University of Latvia
Laboratory for Perceptual and Cognitive Systems
at the Faculty of Computing
Raiņa bulv 19, room 418
E-mail: liga.zarina@lu.lv - please, write to arrange consultations if needed
Phone: +371 28622755

LECTURE 4.
CONTINUOUS FUNCTIONS
Basic definitions
Continuity of the elementary functions
Points of discontinuity
Properties of the continuous functions
4. Homework

Basic definitions
In math an science, we use word continuous to describe process that goes on
without abrupt changes.
Our experiece leads us to assume that this is an essential feature of many natural
processes.
DEFINITION 4.1. (1st definition of the continuity, continuity at a point)
Let f(x) be defined on an open interval containing 𝑥 . We say that f(x) is
0
continuous at 𝑥 if
0
lim 𝑓 𝑥 = 𝑓(𝑥 )
0
𝑥→𝑥
0
We mean by this definition to require three things:
1. lim 𝑓 𝑥 exists,
𝑥→𝑥
0
2. 𝑓 𝑥 exists (𝑥 is in the domain of f), and
0 0
3. lim 𝑓 𝑥 = 𝑓(𝑥 )
0
𝑥→𝑥
0
If any one of these three fails, then f(x) is discontinuous at 𝑥 .
0

Basic definitions
∆𝑥 = 𝑥 − 𝑥 – change in x
0
∆𝑦 = 𝑓(𝑥) − (𝑥 ) – change in y (denotation: also ∆𝑓(𝑥 ))
0 0
Note that ∆𝑦 = 𝑓(𝑥) − 𝑓(𝑥 ) = 𝑓(𝑥 + ∆𝑥) − 𝑓(𝑥 ).
0 0 0
Thus, ∆𝑦 can be seen also as function of argument ∆𝑥.

Basic definitions
DEFINITION 4.2. (2nd definition of the continuity)
We say that f(x) is continuous at 𝑥 if
0
lim ∆𝑦 = 0
∆𝑥→0
DEFINITION 4.3. We say that function u(x) is infinitely-small function as x
approaches x if
0
lim 𝑢(𝑥) = 0
𝑥→𝑥
0
The second definition of the continuity shows that ∆𝑦(or ∆𝑓(𝑥 )) is infinitely-
0
small function as ∆𝑥 approaches 0. In such case, we can say that for infinitely-
small change in argument ∆𝑥 at 𝑥 corresponds infinitely-small change in
0
function ∆𝑓(𝑥 ).
0

Basic definitions
DEFINITION 4.4. We say that function f(x) is left continuous at 𝑥 if
0
lim 𝑓(𝑥) = 𝑓(𝑥 ). We say that function f(x) is right continuous at 𝑥 if
0 0
𝑥→𝑥 −
0
lim 𝑓(𝑥) = 𝑓(𝑥 ).
0
𝑥→𝑥 +
0
DEFINITION 4.5. (3rd definition of the continuity)
We say that function f(x) is continuous at 𝑥 if function is left continuous at 𝑥
0 0
and right continous at 𝑥 .
0
4.1., 4.2. and 4.5. definitions are equivalent.
We call function f(x) continuous in a set X (on an open interval), if f(x) is
continuous in each point of the set X (of that interval). It is continuous on the
closed interval [a,b] if it is continuous on (a,b), right continuous at a, and left
continuous at b.

Continuity of the elementary functions
From main limit theorem we get a such theorem.
Theorem 4.6. (Continuity under function operations)
If functions f(x) and g(x) are continuous at 𝑥 , then so are kf(x), f(x)+g(x), f(x)-
0
𝑛
g(x), f(x)*g(x), f(x)/g(x) (provided that 𝑔(𝑥 ) ≠ 0), and 𝑓(𝑥)(provided that
0
𝑓(𝑥 &gt; 0 if n is even).
0
Examples
1.
𝑓 𝑥 = 𝑐, 𝑐 − 𝑐𝑜𝑛𝑠𝑡, for each 𝑥 the lim 𝑓(𝑥) = 𝑐. That means that the
0
𝑥→𝑥
0
constant function is continous at every real number.
2.
𝑓 𝑥 = 𝑥, for each 𝑥 ∈ ℝ the lim 𝑓(𝑥) = 𝑥 . That means that the function
0 0
𝑥→𝑥
0
𝑓 𝑥 = 𝑥 is continous at every real number.

Continuity of the elementary functions
Since any rational function is obtained by adding, multiplying and dividing
continuous functions f(x)=c and g(x)=x, then the rational function is continuous
at any point in their domain.
The sine, cosine, and 2 𝑥functions are continuous at every real number 𝑥 .
0
In general, a larger result is valid.
Theorem 4.7.
Any elementary function f(x) is continuous in its domain Dom(f).

Continuity of the elementary functions
Example
Function 𝑦 = |𝑥| is continuous at every real number, even if it is not elementary
function.
𝑥, 𝑥 ≥ 0
𝑥 =
−𝑥, 𝑥 &lt; 0
For 𝑥 &lt; 0, 𝑦 = −𝑥, a polynomial; for 𝑥 &gt; 0, 𝑦 = 𝑥, another polynomial.
Both are continuous in their domains.
lim (−𝑥) = 0 , lim 𝑥 = 0 , 𝑡𝑕𝑎𝑡 𝑖𝑠 lim |𝑥| = 0
𝑥→0− 𝑥→0+ 𝑥→0
Therefore, |x| is continuous at 0.
We can see that |x| is continuous at every real number.

Continuity of the elementary functions
Theorem 4.8. (Composite limit theorem)
If g(y) is continuous at a point 𝑦 and lim 𝑓 𝑥 = 𝑦 , then
0 0
𝑥→𝑥
0
lim 𝑔 ∘ 𝑓 𝑥 = 𝑔( lim 𝑓 𝑥 )
𝑥→𝑥 𝑥→𝑥
0 0
Result
If g(y) is continuous at a point 𝑦 , but f(x) is continuous at a point 𝑥 and
0 0
𝑓 𝑥 = 𝑦 , then composition of the functions 𝑔 ∘ 𝑓 𝑥 is continuous at 𝑥 .
0 0 0
Thus, we can also conclude: if g(y) is continuous at every real number, but f(x)
is continuous in a set X, then 𝑔 ∘ 𝑓 𝑥 is continuous in the set X.
Example
𝑕 𝑥 = |𝑥 2 − 3𝑥 + 8| is continuous at every 𝑥 ∈ ℝ, because 𝑓 𝑥 =
𝑥 𝑎𝑛𝑑 𝑔 𝑥 = 𝑥 2 − 3𝑥 + 8 are continuous functions. Thus their composition
𝑕 𝑥 = 𝑓 𝑔 𝑥 = (𝑓 ∘ 𝑔)(𝑥) is continuous.

Points of discontinuity
We will consider classification of such points 𝑥 for which the deleted
0
neighbourhood 𝔄(𝑥 , 𝛿 ) includes infinite amount of points from function f(x)
0 0
domain Dom(f). (𝔄(𝑥 , 𝛿 ) ⊆ 𝐷𝑜𝑚(𝑓))
0 0
DEFINITION 4.9. The point 𝑥 is a point of discontinuity if 𝑥 ∉ 𝐷𝑜𝑚(𝑓) or
0 0
the function is not continuous at this point.
If at the point of discontinuity 𝑥 exist one-sided limits, then such a point is
0
called discontinuity of the first kind (or jump discontinuity, step discontinuity).
At this situation the difference lim 𝑓(𝑥) − lim 𝑓(𝑥) is called a jump at 𝑥 .
0
𝑥→𝑥 + 𝑥→𝑥 −
0 0
If the jump is 0, then the point of discontinuity 𝑥 is called removable point of
0
discontinuity. Otherwise the point of discontinuity is called nonremovable.
If a point of discontinuity 𝑥 is not a discontinuity of the first kind, then it is
0
called discontinuity of the second kind (or essential discontinuity, infinite
discontinuity).

Points of discontinuity
Examples
Please, indicate the points of discontinuity!
2
2𝑥 − 1, 𝑥 ≤ 0
1
𝑦 = , 𝑦 = 𝑠𝑔𝑛 𝑥 (signum from x), and 𝑦 =
𝑐𝑜𝑠𝑥, 𝑥 &gt; 0 𝑥
1. discontinuity of the first kind with a jump 2, at 0 the function is continuous
from left-hand side
2. At 0 the function does not have one sided limits
3. discontinuity of the second kind

Points of discontinuity
Examples
Integer function 𝑥 is right continuous at every real number, even if at 𝑥 ∈ ℤ it
0
has discontinuity of the first kind (tha jump is 1).
For function
1, 𝑥 ≠ 0
𝑦 = the point 0 is a removable
−1, 𝑥 = 0
point of discontinuity, as well as for function
2
𝑥 −8
𝑦 = the point 2 is a removable
𝑥−2
point of discontinuity, even if the function is not
Defined at this point.
In turn, for Dirichlet Function all points are
discontinuity of the second kind, even if domain
of the function include every real number.

Properties of the continuous functions
DEFINITION 4.10. Lets say that 𝑥 ∈ 𝐷𝑜𝑚(𝑓) and 𝑆 ⊆ 𝐷𝑜𝑚(𝑓).
0
f(c) is called the greatest or maximum value (element) of function f in a set S if
𝑓 𝑐 ≥ 𝑓 𝑥 for each 𝑥 ∈ 𝑆.
f(c) is called the least or minimum value (element) of function f in a set S if
𝑓 𝑐 ≤ 𝑓 𝑥 for each 𝑥 ∈ 𝑆.
The maximal and minimal values of the function f in a set S are called extrema.
Often the existence of maximum and minimum for function is dependant from
the set S.
1
For example, for function 𝑓 𝑥 = in a set 𝑆 = (0; +∞) do not have
𝑥
extremum. However, if 𝑆 = 𝑎; 𝑏 , 𝑎 &gt; 0, then f(a) is maximum, but f(b) is
minimum of the function f. In turn, if 𝑆 = (𝑎; 𝑏), then again the function f does
not have extremum.

Properties of the continuous functions
The existence of extremum is dependant from the type of the function.
If we consider discontinuous function
2
2𝑥 − 1. , 𝑥 ≤ 0
𝑦 =
𝑐𝑜𝑠𝑥, 𝑥 &gt; 0
1
then in a set 𝑆 = − ; 4 the function does not have maximum, but it has
2
minumum 𝑦 0 = 𝑦 𝜋 = −1.
DEFINITION 4.11. Function f(x) is called bounded in a set 𝑋 ⊆ 𝐷𝑜𝑚(𝑓), if
∃𝑀 &gt; 0∀𝑥 ∈ 𝐷𝑜𝑚 𝑓 𝑓 𝑥 &lt; 𝑀.
Theorem 4.12. (Weierstrass theorem)
In a closd interval [a;b] every continuous function is bounded. In this interval
the function reaches its maximum and minimum.

Properties of the continuous functions
Theorem 4.13. (Cauchy)
If a function is continuous in a closd interval [a;b], at one endpoint its value is
positive, but in other – negative, then at least at one point inside the interval its
value is 0.
This theorem has simple geometris interpretation: if the values of the endpoints
of the continuous function are with opposite signs, then at least at one point the
graph crosses the Ox axis within the interval. At this point the value of the
function is 0.
In general, such a result is valid.
Theorem 4.14. (Intermediate value theorem, Cauchy)
Let f be a function defined on [a;b] and let W be a number between f(a) and f(b).
If f is continuous on [a;b], then there is at least one number 𝑥 between a and b
0
such that 𝑓(𝑥 ) = 𝑊.
0

HOMEWORK 4
7. Please, indicate at what points are the functions discontinuous and
according which type. Please substantiate and sketch the graphs.
1
, 𝑥 &lt; 0
𝑥−1
a) 𝑦 =
2
(𝑥 + 1) , 0 ≤ 𝑥 &lt; 2
2
𝑥 − 3, 𝑥 &gt; 2
1
− , 𝑥 &lt; 0
b) 𝑦 = 𝑥
2
5𝑥 − 𝑥 , 0 ≤ 𝑥
|𝑥|
8. Please, indicate if function 𝑔 𝑥 = is continuous at the given
𝑥−1,5
intervals [a;b]; if it is not – please, indicate at what points it is discontinuous
and according which type.
a) 𝑎; 𝑏 = [−1; −0,5], b) a; b = [1; 1,8], c) a; b = [2; 4] .
Reading: D. Varberg, E. J. Purcell, S. E. Rigdon Calculus. 9th Edition,
Prentice-Hall, Inc.m, 2014, p.82 – 92.
Chapter 1. Section 1.6.</full_text>
	<references/>
</document>
