<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/8. lecture Function analysis II.pdf</file>
	<title>8. lecture Function analysis II</title>
	<date>Unknown</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/8. lecture Function analysis II.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors/>
	<abstract/>
	<methods/>
	<full_text>Prof. Inese Bula
University of Latvia
Faculty of Physics, Mathematics and Optometry
Lecture Notes
«Matemātiskā analīze I»
CALCULUS I
Doc. Līga Zariņa
University of Latvia
Faculty of Computing

Dr. Līga Zariņa
Researcher
University of Latvia
Laboratory for Perceptual and Cognitive Systems
at the Faculty of Computing
Raiņa bulv 19, room 418
E-mail: liga.zarina@lu.lv - please, write to arrange consultations if needed
Phone: +371 28622755

LECTURE 8.
FUNCTION ANALYSIS II
Concavity
Local Extrema
8. Homework

Concavity
If the tangent line turns steadly in the counterclockwise direction, we say that the
graph is concave up; if the tangent turns in the clockwise direction, the graph is
concave down.
DEFINITION 8.1.
Let f be differentiable on an open interval I. We say that f (as well as its graph) is
concave up (convex) on I if f’ is increasing on I, and we say that f is concave
down on I if f’ is decreasing on I.
Concave up – the graph is under the tangent line in the considered interval
Concave down – the graph is over the tangent line in the considered interval

Concavity
DEFINITION 8.2.
Let f be continuous at c. We call (c, f(c)) an inflection point on the graph of f if f is
concave up on one side of c and concave down on the other side.

Concavity
Let f be differentiable on an open interval I
Concave up – for any two points of the interval the graph that connects these two
points is over chord that connect these points
Concave down – for any two points of the interval the graph that connects these
two points is under chord that connect these points

Concavity
THEOREM 8.3.
(Concavity theorem)
Let f be twice differentiable on an open interval I.
1) If f’’(x) &lt; 0 for all x in I, then f is concave up on I.
2) If f’’(x) &gt; 0 for all x in I, then f is concave down on I.
Points where f’’(x) = 0 or where f’’(x) does not exist are the candidates for
points of inflection. The conclusion is made according the change of signs of
the f’’(x).

Concavity
Example
1
𝑦 = 3𝑥2 −
𝑥2
𝑥4 − 1
𝑦′′ = 6
𝑥4
Critical points are -1, 0 and 1.
Detect the signs of y’’.
Function is
concave down on (-∞;-1) and (1; +∞)
concave up on (-1;0) and (0;1)
The points of inflection are (-1, 2) and (1, 2).
The point 0 does not belong to Dom(y) and also the change of signd does not indicate 0 as
point of inflection.

Concavity
Example
𝑦 = (𝑥 + 2)3 𝑥
Please find the points of inflection!
4(𝑥 − 1)
𝑦′′ =
3
9 𝑥5
Critical points are 0 and 1.
Detect the signs of y’’.
Both critica points (0, 0) and (0, 3) are points of inflection.
The point 0 belongs to Dom(y), but at this point does not exist y’’.
Function is
concave down on (-∞;-1) and (1; +∞)
concave up on (0;1)

Concavity
Exercises
Please find the points of inflection and concavity intervals!
𝑥2
𝑎) 𝑦 =
(𝑥 − 1)2
𝑏) 𝑦 = ln(𝑥2 + 2𝑥 − 3)

Local Extrema
The maximum and minimum value on a given interval are reffered as global
extreme values (global maximum value and global minimum value).
DEFINITION 8.6. (Monotonicity theorem)
Let S, the domain of f, contain the point c. We say that
1) f(c) is a local maximum value of f if there ia an interval (a, b) containing c
such that f(c) is the maximum value of f on (a, b) ∩ S.
2) f(c) is a local minimum value of f if there ia an interval (a, b) containing c
such that f(c) is the minimum value of f on (a, b) ∩ S.
3) f(c) is a local extreme value of f if it is either a local minimum or a local
maximum value.
Any global extreme value is also a local extreme value.

Local Extrema
Where do local extreme values occur?
The candidates for points where local extreme may occure are critical points:
• End points
• Stationary points (the derivative = 0)
• Singular points (the derivative does not exist)
We are not claiming that there must be a local extremum at every critical point.
Example
𝑦 = 𝑥 3 , 𝑦 ′ = 3𝑥 2, the only critical point is 0, but here the function does not
reach local minimum or local maximum value.
However, if the derivative is positive on one side of the critical point and
negative on the other (and if the function is continuous), then we have alocal
extremum.

Local Extrema
THEOREM 8.7.
(First derivative test)
Let f be continuous on an open interval (a, b) that contains a critical point c.
1) If f’(x) &gt; 0 for all x in (a, c) and f’(x) &lt; 0 for all x in (c, b), then f(c) is a
local maximum value of f.
2) If f’(x) &lt; 0 for all x in (a, c) and f’(x) &gt; 0 for all x in (c, b), then f(c) is a
local minimum value of f.
3) If f’(x) has the same sign on both sides of c, then f(c) is not a local extreme
value of f.

Local Extrema
Proof of 1).
□
Since f’(x) &gt; 0 for all x in (a, c), f is increasing on (a, c] by the Monotonicity
theorem.
And again, since f’(x) &lt; 0 for all x in (a, c), f is decreasing on [c, b) by the
Monotonicity theorem.
Thus, f(x) &lt; f(c) for all x in (a, b), except of course at x = c.
We conclude that f(c) is a local maximum.
■

Local Extrema
Exercise
4𝑥 + 5
𝑓 𝑥 =
1 − 𝑥2
Critical points are -2, -1/2, -1 and 1.
At -1 and 1 there is no extrema values, because the derivative values do not
change signs. Also these values do not belong to Dom(f(x)).
According the change of signs at the point -2 the function has local maximum
value 1 and at the -1/2 the function has local minimum value 4.
We see that these are local extrema values, because the maximum value is
smaller then minimum value.

Local Extrema
Exercise
3
𝑥 + 4
𝑓 𝑥 =
𝑥2
Please find the extrema values!
3
𝑥 − 8
′
𝑦 =
𝑥3
Critical points are 0 and 2.
Hav to detect signd for first derivative.
At 0 the function is not defined, thus it cannot have extrema value there, even if
the derivative changes the sign.
The point (2, 3) in accordance with the change of signs is a local minimum
point.
It is local, because, for example) f(-2) = -1 &lt; 3.t

Concavity
Exercises
Please find the extreme values! Please detect if any of them is the global extreme value!
𝑙𝑛𝑥
𝑎) 𝑦 =
𝑥
𝑥𝑛
𝑏) 𝑦 = , 𝑛 = 1, 2, … ,
1 + 𝑥2

HOMEWORK 8
𝑥
15. Where is 𝑦 = concave up and where it is concave down? Please,
(𝑥−2)2
detect th points of inflection.
Answer:
point of inflection (-4; -1/9)
oncave down on (-4;2) and (2; +∞)
concave up on (- ∞;-4)
16. The the number a in the sum with the square of the number b gives 48.
Please, find such a and b, so that their multiplication is greatest.
Answer: a=32, b=4
Reading: D. Varberg, E. J. Purcell, S. E. Rigdon Calculus. 9th Edition,
Prentice-Hall, Inc.m, 2014, p. 155– 166.
Chapter 3. Sections 3.2., 3.3.</full_text>
	<references/>
</document>
