<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/A novel amorphous calcium phosphate polymer ceramic for bone repair I. Synthesis and characterization.pdf</file>
	<title>A Novel Amorphous Calcium Phosphate Polymer Ceramic for Bone Repair: I. Synthesis and Characterization</title>
	<date>2001</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/A novel amorphous calcium phosphate polymer ceramic for bone repair I. Synthesis and characterization.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>Archel Ambrosio</author>
		<author>Janmeet Sahota</author>
		<author>Yusuf Khan</author>
		<author>Cato Laurencin</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>Traditional materials for bone repair or replacements such as autografts and allografts have a limited supply and other complications. Thus, alternative materials need to be explored. Three-dimensional, porous composites prepared from bioresorbable polymers and hydroxyapatite or other calcium phosphate ceramics are promising materials for the repair or replacement of diseased or damaged bone. However, in many cases the ceramic component of these composites is crystalline in nature, while bone apatite is made of a poorly crystalline, carbonated phosphate system. In this study, we synthesized a noncrystalline, carbonated calcium phosphate ceramic by carrying out the reaction within bioresorbable PLAGA microspheres using a modified emulsion/solvent evaporation technique, making each individual microsphere a composite. Sintering the composite microspheres together yielded a bioresorbable, porous, 3-dimensional scaffold that may be ideal for tissue ingrowth, making this composite scaffold potentially suitable for bone repair applications.</abstract>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>MATERIALS AND METHODS</heading>
			<text>PLAGA (50:50) with a molecular weight of 50,000 was obtained from American Cyanamid. Calcium nitrate tetrahydrate, ammonium hydrogen phosphate, and concentrated ammonium hydroxide were obtained from Aldrich and used as received. Commercial hydroxyapatite used for comparison was obtained from Howmedica. Methylene chloride was purchased from Fisher Scientific and used as received.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Preparation of Composite Microspheres</heading>
			<text>PLAGA (1.50 g, 0.0115 mol) was dissolved in 9 mL of methylene chloride. Calcium nitrate tetrahydrate (3.54 g, 0.0150 mol) was dissolved in 1.5 mL of water previously adjusted to pH 10 with ammonium hydroxide. In a separate vial, ammonium hydrogen phosphate (0.99 g, 0.0075 mol) was dissolved in 2.25 mL of pH 10 water. The polymer solution and the calcium nitrate solution were kept at Ϫ70 °C prior to use, while the phosphate solution was maintained at room temperature. The cooled nitrate solution was added quickly to the cooled polymer solution followed immediately by the addition of the phosphate solution, and vortex-mixed at high speed for 20 s to create an emulsion. The emulsion was then poured in a slow steady stream into 600 mL of a 1% polyvinyl alcohol (PVA) solution (pH 10) containing 30 g of calcium nitrate tetrahydrate, which was being stirred at a speed of 250 rpm during the addition and was raised to 500 rpm after the addition. The reaction was allowed to proceed for 30 h, during which ammonium hydroxide was added at regular intervals in order to maintain a pH of 10. Methylene chloride was allowed to evaporate slowly during the reaction period. After 30 h, the microspheres (hollow) that floated to the top of the reaction mixture were removed using a pipette. The microparticles that settled to the bottom of the reaction vessel were collected by suction filtration and washed several times with pH 10 water. The residue was air-dried for 24 h.

The air-dried residue was added to a separatory funnel containing 100 mL of a 50:50 mixture of water and hexane. The whole mixture was shaken and allowed to stand for a few minutes. Most of the unencapsulated calcium phosphate particles settled into the lower aqueous layer, while most of the microspheres stayed in the upper organic layer. The aqueous layer was removed, more water was added, and the separation process was repeated. This step was repeated one more time and the microspheres in the organic layer were collected by vacuum filtration, air-dried, and then lyophilized for 24 h.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Characterization of Synthesized Calcium Phosphate</heading>
			<text>The calcium phosphate that was synthesized within the microspheres was analyzed for calcium and phosphorus. Elemental analysis was obtained from Quantitative Technologies, Inc. (Whitehouse, NJ). IR analysis was carried out using a Nicolet Magna IR 560 (Madison, WI). Powder X-ray diffraction was performed using a Siemens D500 diffractometer using a Ni-filtered CuK radiation with a 2 range from 2-60°.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Preparation and Characterization of 3-Dimensional Scaffold</heading>
			<text>The composite microspheres (100 -250 in diameter) were placed in a 5-mm stainless steel cylindrical mold and pressed lightly with a correspondingly sized piston. The whole assembly was placed in an oven at 150 °C for 1 h in order to sinter the microspheres. A cross-section of the resulting 3-dimensional scaffold was viewed by scanning electron microscopy (SEM). Samples were gold-coated using a Denton Desk 1 sputter coater in an argon-purged chamber evacuated to 500 mTorr. The images were viewed using an Amray 1830 D4 scanning electron microscope (20 kV) with a tungsten gun and a diffusion pump. The porosity and pore-size distribution of the scaffold was determined using a Micromeritics Autopore III Mercury Intrusion Porosimeter (Norcross, GA) by infusing mercury into the samples with a pressure of 40 psi. Pore size and porosity were determined as a function of pressure and corresponding mercury intrusion volume. As the mercury is forced into the pores of the sample, both the pressure necessary to move the mercury and the volume of mercury moved are recorded. From this data, both porosity and pore size are computed.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Preparation of Composite Microspheres</heading>
			<text>The bioresorbable composite microspheres, which consisted of a calcium phosphate ceramic within PLAGA micro-spheres, had slightly irregular shapes as shown by the scanning electron micrograph of the microspheres (see Fig. 1).

The percent ceramic content of the microspheres was found to be 28.4 Ϯ 5.9%.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Characterization of Synthesized Calcium Phosphate</heading>
			<text>Elemental analysis was performed on the synthesized calcium phosphate to determine its Ca/P molar ratio. Table I shows the % Ca, % P, and Ca/P ratio of the synthesized ceramic together with the calculated values for hydroxyapatite and tetracalcium phosphate. The Ca/P ratio for the synthesized calcium phosphate was found to be 2.02, which is similar to that of tetracalcium phosphate. IR analysis of the synthesized ceramic showed peaks around 1400 -1700 cm Ϫ1 , which are absent in the IR spectra of the commercial hydroxyapatite (Fig. 2), suggesting the presence of carbonate ions in the ceramic. XRD analysis of the ceramic demonstrated the amorphous nature of this calcium phosphate (see Fig. 3) as depicted by the XRD spectra of the synthesized calcium phosphate, which shows no distinguishing features, while the XRD pattern for commercial hydroxyapatite shows welldefined features, indicating its crystallinity.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Preparation and Characterization of 3-Dimensional Scaffold</heading>
			<text>The composite microspheres were sintered together to form a porous 3-dimensional scaffold. Image analysis of a cross-section of this scaffold by scanning electron microscopy showed fused microspheres and deep pores (Fig. 4). The surface of the microspheres was also rougher than that of the unsintered microspheres (Fig. 1). In addition, some of the microspheres were split open, thus exposing more surface area and increasing porosity. Mercury intrusion porosimetry of the scaffold demonstrated a pore-size distribution centered around 100 m (Fig. 5). Porosity calculations indicated a porosity of approximately 75%.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Preparation of Composite Microspheres</heading>
			<text>The reaction between calcium nitrate tetrahydrate and ammonium hydrogen phosphate in basic aqueous solution has been shown to produce an amorphous calcium phosphate, which becomes crystalline over time. 22 In our study, this reaction was carried out within microspheres made from a bioresorbable polymer, PLAGA. The microspheres were prepared using a water-in-oil emulsion containing PLAGA, calcium nitrate tetrahydrate, and ammonium hydrogen phosphate was prepared by adding a basic aqueous solution of the nitrate and phosphate components to a solution of PLAGA in methylene chloride followed by rapid mixing. The different components of this emulsion were cooled prior to mixing in order to prevent the premature reaction of calcium nitrate with the phosphate reagent, and thus avoid precipitation of a calcium phosphate compound at this stage of the process. Once the emulsion was made, it was added to a solution of PVA containing an excess of calcium nitrate tetrahydrate, which was being stirred with a mechanical stirrer. Excess calcium nitrate was added to minimize the diffusion of calcium ions from inside the microspheres to the surrounding solution, thereby increasing the chances of obtaining a calcium phosphate with a high Ca/P molar ratio similar to that of bone apatite, which has a Ca/P ratio of approximately 1.6. 15 The resulting microparticles were collected after a 30-h reaction period.

The microparticles that were collected consisted of the composite microspheres as well as unencapsulated calcium phosphate particles. To separate the microspheres from the unencapsulated ceramic particles, the microparticle mixture was added to a hexane-water mixture, which was then shaken and allowed to stand. This separation method is based on the preference of the unencapsulated calcium phosphate particles for the aqueous layer and the preference of the microspheres for the organic layer due to the presence of the more hydrophobic PLAGA in the microspheres. The hexane layer was then collected and the microspheres isolated by filtration.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Characterization of Synthesized Calcium Phosphate</heading>
			<text>Elemental analysis of the synthesized calcium phosphate indicated a Ca/P molar ratio similar to that of tetracalcium phosphate (Table I). Tetracalcium phosphate was one of the products expected, the other being hydroxyapatite. At pH 10, which was the pH of the reaction mixture, both of these compounds are the least soluble of the various calcium phosphates and are, therefore, more likely to form and precipitate at this pH. 23 While the Ca/P ratio closely matches that of tetracalcium phosphate, the % Ca and % P values did not. It is possible that during the synthesis of the calcium phosphate, carbonate ions may have been incorporated into its structure, thus altering the chemical composition of the ceramic. Incorporation of the carbonate ions occurred, because there may have been dissolved carbonates in the reaction mixture, especially since it was exposed to air and stirred continuously at high speed. Infrared analysis supports this possibility.

Figure 2 shows the IR spectra of the synthesized material as well as that of a commercially available hydroxyapatite. As seen in this figure, the IR spectra for both compounds are very similar except that the spectra of the synthesized calcium phosphate had peaks around 1400 -1700 cm Ϫ1 indicating the presence of carbonate. These peaks are similar to the ones observed for a carbonated apatite that was obtained after implanting brushite for 2 weeks in the femoral metaphysis of a rabbit. 24 Bone apatite has been reported to contain substantial amounts of carbonate. 7 Thus, the synthesized calcium phosphate, being carbonated, more closely resembles the composition of bone apatite than does tetracalcium phosphate or hydroxyapatite.

To determine the crystallinity of the ceramic that was synthesized, X-ray powder diffraction was performed. Figure 3 shows the diffraction spectra for the synthesized material and a commercial hydroxyapatite. As illustrated in this figure, the hydroxyapatite is highly crystalline while the synthesized calcium phosphate material appears noncrystalline. The noncrystalline pattern is similar to those seen in other amorphous calcium phosphate XRD spectra. 22 This noncrystalline pattern suggests that, by restricting the synthesis of the calcium phosphate to the small space within the microsphere's interior, crystalline formation was prevented as determined by XRD analysis. As mentioned earlier, bone apatite is a poorly crystalline calcium phosphate ceramic. In addition, amorphous or poorly crystalline calcium phosphates are more resorbable than their crystalline counterparts. Thus, the results indicate that we have synthesized a calcium phosphate ceramic whose chemical composition and low crystallinity may make it suitable as a material for bone repair. However, while the synthesized ceramic has some interesting properties, by itself it may not be structurally suitable for certain orthopedic applications due to its brittleness. Thus, by combining it with a polymeric material, the brittleness of the ceramic is offset.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Preparation and Characterization of 3-Dimensional Scaffold</heading>
			<text>The composite microspheres were sintered at 150 °C for 1 h in order to fuse the microspheres together. Fusion of the microspheres was possible, because the sintering temperature was above the melting temperature of the polymeric component of the microspheres, PLAGA. The resulting 3-dimensional scaffold was porous and did not crumble upon handling unlike some sintered, porous, calcium phosphate ceramics. The scanning electron micrograph of a cross-section of the scaffold illustrates the porosity of the scaffold (see Fig. 4). In addition, some of the microspheres split open probably due to the slight pressure provided by the piston of the cylindrical mold assembly. As a result, the porosity of the scaffold was increased further, which also increased the surface area for cell attachment. Furthermore, the sintering process transformed the surface of the microspheres into a rougher one, characterized by the preponderance of micronsized pores. Decades ago, the minimum pore size for effective bone ingrowth into a porous scaffold was established to be approximately 100 . [25][26][27] Mercury intrusion porosimetry on the scaffold indicates that a majority of the pores have diameters of at least 100 , thus meeting the minimum requirement for bone ingrowth (Fig. 5). The porosimetry results also showed that the scaffold had a porosity of approximately 75%.</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>With U.S. demographics shifting towards an older population and with more people living more active lifestyles, the number of orthopedic injuries and disorders is expected to rise significantly. In the U.S. alone, there were more than 6 million fractures each year from 1992-1994. 1 In 1995, there were 216,000 total knee replacements, 134,000 total hip replacements, and close to 100,000 bone grafting procedures. In all, musculoskeletal conditions cost the U.S. $214.9 billion in 1995. Traditionally, orthopedic surgeons have used autografts and allografts to repair fractures and other bone defects. However, because of limitations such as donor-site morbidity, risk of disease-transfer, potential immunogenicity, and insufficient supply, increasingly more investigators are looking for alternative bone repair materials. Some of the materials that have been and continue to be extensively investigated are hydroxyapatite and the range of materials within the calcium phosphate family. [2][3][4][5][6] This is only to be expected, because the main mineral component of bone is a complex inorganic calcium phosphate system called apatite. 7 Additionally, calcium phosphate ceramics are reported to be osteoconductive and to directly bond to bone 8,9 and have been considered precursors to bone apatite formation in vivo. 2 Thus, the good bone biocompatibility of these materials makes them suitable for the repair or replacement of damaged or diseased bone. However, their brittleness limits their widespread use in orthopedics especially in load-bearing applications. One solution has been to prepare composites of these ceramics with bioresorbable polymeric materials such as collagen and polymers of lactic acid and glycolic acid. 10 -14 In general, these composites are made porous in order to create a 3-dimensional scaffold that would allow the ingrowth of new bone and the eventual replacement of the scaffold with new skeletal tissue. 12,13 In many of these studies, the ceramics used are usually calcium phosphate compounds with moderate to high crystallinity. [10][11][12][13][14] Yet it is widely known that bone apatite is poorly crystalline and nonstoichiometric due to the presence of other ions such as magnesium and carbonate ions. 7,15 In addition, crystalline forms of hydroxyapatite have been shown to resorb at a slower rate than that of new bone formation. In fact, the rate of new bone formation coincides more closely with the resorption rate of poorly crystalline or amorphous calcium phosphate ceramics. 16 -18 In effect, the replacement of a poorly crystalline or amorphous calcium phosphate ceramic by new bone occurs more or less concurrently as the ceramic is resorbed. Also, the degradation of an amorphous calcium phosphate forms alkali products that would serve to buffer the acidic degradation products of either lactic or glycolic acid in a composite of the two materials.

Thus, in this study, the goal was to prepare a bioresorbable composite consisting of poly(lactide-co-glycolide), PLAGA, and a noncrystalline calcium phosphate ceramic. To accomplish this, the synthesis of the calcium phosphate was carried out within the PLAGA microspheres. The rationale was that, by confining the reaction within the microspheres, the formation of a crystalline calcium phosphate material would be prevented or at least minimized. In addition, because each microsphere is itself a composite, sintering the microspheres together would yield a porous, 3-dimensional scaffold with uniform composition all throughout the scaffold.

PLAGA (50:50) with a molecular weight of 50,000 was obtained from American Cyanamid. Calcium nitrate tetrahydrate, ammonium hydrogen phosphate, and concentrated ammonium hydroxide were obtained from Aldrich and used as received. Commercial hydroxyapatite used for comparison was obtained from Howmedica. Methylene chloride was purchased from Fisher Scientific and used as received.

PLAGA (1.50 g, 0.0115 mol) was dissolved in 9 mL of methylene chloride. Calcium nitrate tetrahydrate (3.54 g, 0.0150 mol) was dissolved in 1.5 mL of water previously adjusted to pH 10 with ammonium hydroxide. In a separate vial, ammonium hydrogen phosphate (0.99 g, 0.0075 mol) was dissolved in 2.25 mL of pH 10 water. The polymer solution and the calcium nitrate solution were kept at Ϫ70 °C prior to use, while the phosphate solution was maintained at room temperature. The cooled nitrate solution was added quickly to the cooled polymer solution followed immediately by the addition of the phosphate solution, and vortex-mixed at high speed for 20 s to create an emulsion. The emulsion was then poured in a slow steady stream into 600 mL of a 1% polyvinyl alcohol (PVA) solution (pH 10) containing 30 g of calcium nitrate tetrahydrate, which was being stirred at a speed of 250 rpm during the addition and was raised to 500 rpm after the addition. The reaction was allowed to proceed for 30 h, during which ammonium hydroxide was added at regular intervals in order to maintain a pH of 10. Methylene chloride was allowed to evaporate slowly during the reaction period. After 30 h, the microspheres (hollow) that floated to the top of the reaction mixture were removed using a pipette. The microparticles that settled to the bottom of the reaction vessel were collected by suction filtration and washed several times with pH 10 water. The residue was air-dried for 24 h.

The air-dried residue was added to a separatory funnel containing 100 mL of a 50:50 mixture of water and hexane. The whole mixture was shaken and allowed to stand for a few minutes. Most of the unencapsulated calcium phosphate particles settled into the lower aqueous layer, while most of the microspheres stayed in the upper organic layer. The aqueous layer was removed, more water was added, and the separation process was repeated. This step was repeated one more time and the microspheres in the organic layer were collected by vacuum filtration, air-dried, and then lyophilized for 24 h.

A known weight of microspheres was placed in methylene chloride to dissolve away the PLAGA component. The mixture was filtered and the residue was placed in methylene chloride to remove more PLAGA. This extraction step was repeated one more time. The residue was collected, lyophilized, and weighed. This experiment was carried out in triplicate.

The calcium phosphate that was synthesized within the microspheres was analyzed for calcium and phosphorus. Elemental analysis was obtained from Quantitative Technologies, Inc. (Whitehouse, NJ). IR analysis was carried out using a Nicolet Magna IR 560 (Madison, WI). Powder X-ray diffraction was performed using a Siemens D500 diffractometer using a Ni-filtered CuK radiation with a 2 range from 2-60°.

The composite microspheres (100 -250 in diameter) were placed in a 5-mm stainless steel cylindrical mold and pressed lightly with a correspondingly sized piston. The whole assembly was placed in an oven at 150 °C for 1 h in order to sinter the microspheres. A cross-section of the resulting 3-dimensional scaffold was viewed by scanning electron microscopy (SEM). Samples were gold-coated using a Denton Desk 1 sputter coater in an argon-purged chamber evacuated to 500 mTorr. The images were viewed using an Amray 1830 D4 scanning electron microscope (20 kV) with a tungsten gun and a diffusion pump. The porosity and pore-size distribution of the scaffold was determined using a Micromeritics Autopore III Mercury Intrusion Porosimeter (Norcross, GA) by infusing mercury into the samples with a pressure of 40 psi. Pore size and porosity were determined as a function of pressure and corresponding mercury intrusion volume. As the mercury is forced into the pores of the sample, both the pressure necessary to move the mercury and the volume of mercury moved are recorded. From this data, both porosity and pore size are computed.

The bioresorbable composite microspheres, which consisted of a calcium phosphate ceramic within PLAGA micro-spheres, had slightly irregular shapes as shown by the scanning electron micrograph of the microspheres (see Fig. 1).

The percent ceramic content of the microspheres was found to be 28.4 Ϯ 5.9%.

Elemental analysis was performed on the synthesized calcium phosphate to determine its Ca/P molar ratio. Table I shows the % Ca, % P, and Ca/P ratio of the synthesized ceramic together with the calculated values for hydroxyapatite and tetracalcium phosphate. The Ca/P ratio for the synthesized calcium phosphate was found to be 2.02, which is similar to that of tetracalcium phosphate. IR analysis of the synthesized ceramic showed peaks around 1400 -1700 cm Ϫ1 , which are absent in the IR spectra of the commercial hydroxyapatite (Fig. 2), suggesting the presence of carbonate ions in the ceramic. XRD analysis of the ceramic demonstrated the amorphous nature of this calcium phosphate (see Fig. 3) as depicted by the XRD spectra of the synthesized calcium phosphate, which shows no distinguishing features, while the XRD pattern for commercial hydroxyapatite shows welldefined features, indicating its crystallinity.

The composite microspheres were sintered together to form a porous 3-dimensional scaffold. Image analysis of a cross-section of this scaffold by scanning electron microscopy showed fused microspheres and deep pores (Fig. 4). The surface of the microspheres was also rougher than that of the unsintered microspheres (Fig. 1). In addition, some of the microspheres were split open, thus exposing more surface area and increasing porosity. Mercury intrusion porosimetry of the scaffold demonstrated a pore-size distribution centered around 100 m (Fig. 5). Porosity calculations indicated a porosity of approximately 75%.

In recent years, bioresorbable, porous, 3-dimensional scaffolds have been studied as matrices for the regeneration of tissue such as skin, cartilage, and bone. 19 -21 The rationale for this design is that the interconnected pores would allow the ingrowth of new tissue, which eventually replaces the degrading scaffold. In orthopedic applications, the scaffolds are typically made of bioresorbable polymers, ceramics, or composites. In this study, we have designed a bioresorbable 3-dimensional composite scaffold made from composite microspheres of an amorphous calcium phosphate ceramic encapsulated within bioresorbable polymeric microspheres. This was accomplished by using the microspheres as microreactors for the synthesis of the calcium phosphate ceramic.  The rationale is that by carrying out the synthesis within the confined space of the microsphere's interior, crystal growth is impeded due to the constraints imposed by the small internal space of the microsphere. As a result, the formation of crystalline calcium phosphates is prevented or at least minimized. Bone apatite is reported to be poorly crystalline. 7,15 Thus, a calcium phosphate ceramic that more closely mimics the low crystallinity of bone apatite would presumably be a better bone substitute than a highly crystalline calcium phosphate material. In addition, amorphous or poorly crystalline calcium phosphates have a faster resorption rate than their crystalline counterparts, which allows them to be more readily replaced by new bone. 16 -18 Also, the degradation of an amorphous calcium phosphate forms alkali products that would serve to buffer the acidic degradation products of either lactic or glycolic acid in a composite of the two materials. Another rationale for this design is that the poly-  meric component would reduce the brittleness of the ceramic component while serving to bind the microspheres together during the sintering process. Additionally, because each individual microsphere is in itself a composite, the resulting scaffold has uniform composition throughout. Although calcium phosphates have been extensively studied and several different Ca/P ratios have been constructed and characterized, our system is unique in the sense that we have formed a composite scaffold from composite microspheres that encompass two relevant materials for bone graft substitutes and also complement each other as a composite.

The reaction between calcium nitrate tetrahydrate and ammonium hydrogen phosphate in basic aqueous solution has been shown to produce an amorphous calcium phosphate, which becomes crystalline over time. 22 In our study, this reaction was carried out within microspheres made from a bioresorbable polymer, PLAGA. The microspheres were prepared using a water-in-oil emulsion containing PLAGA, calcium nitrate tetrahydrate, and ammonium hydrogen phosphate was prepared by adding a basic aqueous solution of the nitrate and phosphate components to a solution of PLAGA in methylene chloride followed by rapid mixing. The different components of this emulsion were cooled prior to mixing in order to prevent the premature reaction of calcium nitrate with the phosphate reagent, and thus avoid precipitation of a calcium phosphate compound at this stage of the process. Once the emulsion was made, it was added to a solution of PVA containing an excess of calcium nitrate tetrahydrate, which was being stirred with a mechanical stirrer. Excess calcium nitrate was added to minimize the diffusion of calcium ions from inside the microspheres to the surrounding solution, thereby increasing the chances of obtaining a calcium phosphate with a high Ca/P molar ratio similar to that of bone apatite, which has a Ca/P ratio of approximately 1.6. 15 The resulting microparticles were collected after a 30-h reaction period.

The microparticles that were collected consisted of the composite microspheres as well as unencapsulated calcium phosphate particles. To separate the microspheres from the unencapsulated ceramic particles, the microparticle mixture was added to a hexane-water mixture, which was then shaken and allowed to stand. This separation method is based on the preference of the unencapsulated calcium phosphate particles for the aqueous layer and the preference of the microspheres for the organic layer due to the presence of the more hydrophobic PLAGA in the microspheres. The hexane layer was then collected and the microspheres isolated by filtration.

The ceramic content of the microspheres as determined by gravimetric analysis, was approximately 28%. It may be possible to increase the ceramic content of the microspheres up to a certain point, if further improvement in mechanical properties is desired. However, the main goal of this study was to prove the feasibility of synthesizing noncrystalline calcium phosphate within bioresorbable polymeric microspheres to form a composite microsphere with appropriate physico-chemical properties to be used as a bone graft substitute. Thus, optimizing the ceramic content of the composite microspheres will be addressed in future work.

Elemental analysis of the synthesized calcium phosphate indicated a Ca/P molar ratio similar to that of tetracalcium phosphate (Table I). Tetracalcium phosphate was one of the products expected, the other being hydroxyapatite. At pH 10, which was the pH of the reaction mixture, both of these compounds are the least soluble of the various calcium phosphates and are, therefore, more likely to form and precipitate at this pH. 23 While the Ca/P ratio closely matches that of tetracalcium phosphate, the % Ca and % P values did not. It is possible that during the synthesis of the calcium phosphate, carbonate ions may have been incorporated into its structure, thus altering the chemical composition of the ceramic. Incorporation of the carbonate ions occurred, because there may have been dissolved carbonates in the reaction mixture, especially since it was exposed to air and stirred continuously at high speed. Infrared analysis supports this possibility.

Figure 2 shows the IR spectra of the synthesized material as well as that of a commercially available hydroxyapatite. As seen in this figure, the IR spectra for both compounds are very similar except that the spectra of the synthesized calcium phosphate had peaks around 1400 -1700 cm Ϫ1 indicating the presence of carbonate. These peaks are similar to the ones observed for a carbonated apatite that was obtained after implanting brushite for 2 weeks in the femoral metaphysis of a rabbit. 24 Bone apatite has been reported to contain substantial amounts of carbonate. 7 Thus, the synthesized calcium phosphate, being carbonated, more closely resembles the composition of bone apatite than does tetracalcium phosphate or hydroxyapatite.

To determine the crystallinity of the ceramic that was synthesized, X-ray powder diffraction was performed. Figure 3 shows the diffraction spectra for the synthesized material and a commercial hydroxyapatite. As illustrated in this figure, the hydroxyapatite is highly crystalline while the synthesized calcium phosphate material appears noncrystalline. The noncrystalline pattern is similar to those seen in other amorphous calcium phosphate XRD spectra. 22 This noncrystalline pattern suggests that, by restricting the synthesis of the calcium phosphate to the small space within the microsphere's interior, crystalline formation was prevented as determined by XRD analysis. As mentioned earlier, bone apatite is a poorly crystalline calcium phosphate ceramic. In addition, amorphous or poorly crystalline calcium phosphates are more resorbable than their crystalline counterparts. Thus, the results indicate that we have synthesized a calcium phosphate ceramic whose chemical composition and low crystallinity may make it suitable as a material for bone repair. However, while the synthesized ceramic has some interesting properties, by itself it may not be structurally suitable for certain orthopedic applications due to its brittleness. Thus, by combining it with a polymeric material, the brittleness of the ceramic is offset.

The composite microspheres were sintered at 150 °C for 1 h in order to fuse the microspheres together. Fusion of the microspheres was possible, because the sintering temperature was above the melting temperature of the polymeric component of the microspheres, PLAGA. The resulting 3-dimensional scaffold was porous and did not crumble upon handling unlike some sintered, porous, calcium phosphate ceramics. The scanning electron micrograph of a cross-section of the scaffold illustrates the porosity of the scaffold (see Fig. 4). In addition, some of the microspheres split open probably due to the slight pressure provided by the piston of the cylindrical mold assembly. As a result, the porosity of the scaffold was increased further, which also increased the surface area for cell attachment. Furthermore, the sintering process transformed the surface of the microspheres into a rougher one, characterized by the preponderance of micronsized pores. Decades ago, the minimum pore size for effective bone ingrowth into a porous scaffold was established to be approximately 100 . [25][26][27] Mercury intrusion porosimetry on the scaffold indicates that a majority of the pores have diameters of at least 100 , thus meeting the minimum requirement for bone ingrowth (Fig. 5). The porosimetry results also showed that the scaffold had a porosity of approximately 75%.

This study has demonstrated that, by restricting the reaction of a calcium salt with a phosphate compound to the small confine of a microsphere's interior, a noncrystalline, carbonated calcium phosphate ceramic was obtained. The calcium phosphate family of ceramics is said to have excellent bonebonding properties due to its similarity to bone apatite, which is a poorly crystalline, carbonated calcium phosphate ceramic. Additionally, crystalline calcium phosphates are more slowly resorbed than poorly crystalline or amorphous calcium phosphates such as bone apatite. Thus, the calcium phosphate synthesized inside the microspheres exhibits similarities with bone apatite with respect to its chemical composition and low crystallinity. Sintering the composite microspheres together produced a highly porous, 3-dimensional scaffold with a rough surface. In all, the combination of high-porosity and a calcium phosphate component that is noncrystalline and carbonated may make this 3-dimensional composite scaffold suitable for bone repair applications.

Figure 2. IR spectra of (a) synthesized calcium phosphate, and (b) commercial hydroxyapatite. Note the presence of peaks around 1400 -1700 cm Ϫ1 in the synthesized ceramic, indicating carbonation. 297 NOVEL AMORPHOUS CALCIUM PHOSPHATE POLYMER CERAMIC FOR BONE REPAIR 10974636, 2001, 3, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/1097-4636(2001)58:3&lt;295::AID-JBM1020&gt;3.0.CO;2-8 by Riga Technical University, Wiley Online Library on [06/04/2026]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License

10974636, 2001, 3, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/1097-4636(2001)58:3&lt;295::AID-JBM1020&gt;3.0.CO;2-8 by Riga Technical University, Wiley Online Library on [06/04/2026]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Am Acad Orthop Surg</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Praemer</author>
				<author>S Furner</author>
				<author>D Rice</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomed Mater Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Eap Demaeyer</author>
				<author>Rmh Verbeeck</author>
				<author>Cwj Vercruysse</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomed Mater Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Keller</author>
				<author>W Dollase</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Zeng</author>
				<author>K Chittur</author>
				<author>W Lacefield</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomed Mater Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Ma</author>
				<author>R Zhang</author>
				<author>G Xiao</author>
				<author>R Franceschi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2001</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomed Mater Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Durucan</author>
				<author>P Brown</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Acc Chem Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Posner</author>
				<author>F Betts</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1975</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Clin Orthop Rel Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Jarcho</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1981</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Clin Orthop Rel Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Kitsugi</author>
				<author>T Yamamuro</author>
				<author>H Takeuchi</author>
				<author>M Ono</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1988</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomed Mater Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Tenhuisen</author>
				<author>R Martin</author>
				<author>M Klimkiewicz</author>
				<author>P Brown</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1995</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomed Mater Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Yasunaga</author>
				<author>Y Matsusue</author>
				<author>T Furukawa</author>
				<author>Y Shikinami</author>
				<author>M Okuno</author>
				<author>T Nakamura</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomed Mater Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Zhang</author>
				<author>P Ma</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomater Sci Polymer Ed</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Devin</author>
				<author>M Attawia</author>
				<author>C Laurencin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1996</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Boeree</author>
				<author>J Dove</author>
				<author>J Cooper</author>
				<author>J Knowles</author>
				<author>G Hastings</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1993</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Bigi</author>
				<author>E Foresti</author>
				<author>R Gregorini</author>
				<author>A Ripamonti</author>
				<author>N Roveri</author>
				<author>J Shah</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Frayssinet</author>
				<author>J Trouillet</author>
				<author>N Rouquet</author>
				<author>E Azimus</author>
				<author>A Autefage</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1993</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomed Mater Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Cpat Klein</author>
				<author>A Driessen</author>
				<author>K De Groot</author>
				<author>A Van Den Hoof</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1983</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomed Mater Res (Appl Biomater)</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Knaack</author>
				<author>Mep Goad</author>
				<author>M Aiolova</author>
				<author>C Rey</author>
				<author>A Tofighi</author>
				<author>P Chakravarthy</author>
				<author>D Lee</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1998</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Syn-thetic biodegradable polymer scaffolds</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Naughton</author>
				<author>R Bartel</author>
				<author>J Mansbridge</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomed Mater Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Freed</author>
				<author>J Marquis</author>
				<author>A Nohria</author>
				<author>J Emmanual</author>
				<author>A Mikos</author>
				<author>R Langer</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1993</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Annual review of biomedical engineering</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Laurencin</author>
				<author>Ama Ambrosio</author>
				<author>M Borden</author>
				<author>Cooper Jr</author>
				<author>J</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nature</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Eanes</author>
				<author>I Gillessen</author>
				<author>A Posner</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1965</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Mat Res Soc Symp Proc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Chow</author>
				<author>S Takagi</author>
				<author>P Constantino</author>
				<author>C Friedman</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1991</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomed Mater Res (Appl Biomater)</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B Constantz</author>
				<author>B Barr</author>
				<author>I Ison</author>
				<author>M Fulmer</author>
				<author>J Baker</author>
				<author>L Mc-Kinney</author>
				<author>S Goodman</author>
				<author>S Gunasekaren</author>
				<author>D Delaney</author>
				<author>J Ross</author>
				<author>R Poser</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1998</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biomed Mater Res Symp</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Klawitter</author>
				<author>S Hulbert</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1971</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>O Gauthier</author>
				<author>J Bouler</author>
				<author>E Aguado</author>
				<author>P Pilet</author>
				<author>G Daculsi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1998</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Daculsi</author>
				<author>N Passuit</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1990</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
</document>
