<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Adsorption of dextrans onto hydroxyapatite Presence of maxima.pdf</file>
	<title>Adsorption of dextrans onto hydroxyapatite: presence of maxima</title>
	<date>Unknown</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Adsorption of dextrans onto hydroxyapatite Presence of maxima.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>S Spa&amp;o</author>
		<author>K Ananthapadmanabhan</author>
		<author>M Aronson</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>has been widely used as a model substrate ;br studying biological systems involving mineralization and protein adsorpticn.</abstract>
	<methods/>
	<full_text>has been widely used as a model susbtrate for studying biological systems involving mineralization, protein adsorption and biohlm formation. The behavior of hydroxyapatite in these systems can be expected to be influenced markedly by the chemical, electrokinetic and morphological properties of the solid surface [ 1 J. These properties can be especially important in adsorption studies involving proteins, macromolecuIes and surfactant micelies. In poly*mer adsorption systems, for example, certain molecular weight fractions of the polymer may be excluded from a porous substrate. In competitive adsorption studies involving a polymer and an inorganic species, however, the low molecuiar weight species will be able to penetrate into the pores and the polymer may be excluded preferen- tially. Qecognition of these effec:c is extremely important in making a mesningiui interpretation of the experimentai results. in the present study, hydroxyapatite samples from commercial sources were used to determine the appropriate substrate and the methods needed to understand the adsorption behavior of different molecular weight dextrans from aqueous solutions.

samples were purchased from the following three sources: Biorad (Biogel I-ITP), Aldrich, and Albright &amp; Wilson (U.K.). Dextran of average molecular weight 15 000-20 000 was obtained from Polyscience Inc. The dextrans of molecular weights 6000 and 500000 were from Fluka Chemicals. Samples were prcparcd in !hc following mrtnncr. A slurry of the powder in ethanol was ground and ultrasonicatcd until the powder was sl:%cicntly fine. This was necessary to deaggregate tlz big chunks so that the fine structure can be imaged clearly.

A carbon-coated TEM grid was then dipped into the diluted slurry to deposit the hydroxyapatitc powder on the grid surface. The surface was cxamincd in a JEOL IOOC transmission electron microscope using an accelerating voltage of 100 kV. The tcxturc or porosity present in the hydroxyapatite pc:vder was imaged by the &quot;defocus-contrast&quot; technique.

show features which exhibit rcvcrsal of contrast, indicating that the fcaturcs arc indeed phase objjccts such as voids. The contrast arises from the difference in the mean inner potential bctwccn the ports and tnatrix material. By focusing either above or hclow the sample, a phase diff'ercnce can be induced between the clcctron beams. This phase difference manifests itself as either dark or light rings which surround the void. The voids in the Biogel HTP were found !o possess a lameliar morphology aGd tl?cir sizes range from 150 to 1000 A.

The adsorption isotherms of different molecular weight dextrans on Biogel HTP are shown in Fig. 1. it can bc seen that for dextran-6K, i.e. the dcxtran of mo!eczlar weight 6000, adsorption increases with increasing concentration and attains a plateau value above an initial polymer concentration of about 12 mg ml-' hydroxyapatite.

Interestingly, both the dext;an-15K and dextran-500K exhibit an adsorption maximum in their isotherms. Furthermore, these resuits clearly show that adsorption is lower for the higher molecular weight polymers. The presence of a maximum as well as lower adsorption at higher molecular weights is contrary to what is expected for polymer adsorption on non-porous solids. However, exclusion of higher molecular weight polymers from micropores can indeed lead to lower adsorption.

The I.resence of micropores was verified by examining the morphology of the particles using SEM (Fig. 2). It is evident that the Biogel HTP sample exhibits a &quot;cake-like&quot; structure with an average particle size of at least IO0 pm. Attempts to break the aggregates by vigorous stirring and even sonication were not successful in the sense that these sonicated particles did not eliminate the adsorption maximum for dextran-500K.

Adsorp!ion results obtained under mild agitation conditions (see Experimental section, Method l), using two other hydroxyapatite samples, are shown  in Figs 3 and 4 and aIso exhibit a maximum for dextran-500K. The maximum adsorption density values for these samples are much higher than those obtained using Gogel HTP. SEM pictures of these samples show that these, unlike the Biogel HTP, are powder-like aggregates (Figs 5 and6). Interestingiy, a thorough dispersion of these particles, obtained by stirring for 16 h, resulted in an isotherm with almost no maximum (Fig. 7).

It is clear from the results obtained that the presence of a maximum is directly related to the cake-like structure of BiogeI HTP. Furthermore. even powder-like samples, if improperly dispersed, can lead to anomalous results.

Intuitively, one would expect exclusion of polymers from pores to result in a lower plateau value than in the case where the pores arc large enough to allow the po!ymers to penetrate so that all the internal area of the aggregate is availabIe for adsorption. The reason for the prsscnce of a maximum in the isotherm is not obvious from the fact that the substrate is porous. The phenomenon can be explained by examining the definition of thermndynamic adsorption in terms of what is actually measured by the solution depletion technique and how much is realiy on the surface. ln classical colloid chemistry, adsorption refers to the Gibbs thermodynamic adsorption which is defined as the surface excess, i.e. the cxccss solute in a unit volume at the interfacial region over that in the same volume in the bulk solution. This can be expressed as

where C, refers to the solute concentration at the surface and Cb is the bulk concentration.

Note that according to the above definition, if for some reason the surface repels or excludes a solute from the interfacial region, a C, which is lower than Ci,, can result and consequently the adsorption can be negative. The negative adsorption will continue to increase with increasing bulk concentration.

Factors which can cause solute exclusion include electrostatic repulsion of similarly charged adsorbate and substrate, size exclusion as well as solvation/desoivation of the adsorbate and the adsorbent [3]. In the case of size exclusion, adsorption can occur only on the external surface of a porous substrate in which case C, will initially increase and ultimately reach a plateau va!ue. The adsorption value will correspondingly increase due to C, up to the plateau concentration but above this concentration the increase in Cb will result in a decrease in adsorptio;l. This is the phenomenon which gives rise !d an adsorption maximum in this case.

The determination of adsorption using the solution depIetion technique involves taking the difference between the concentrations of the solute before and after contact with the solid. This difference is then attributed to surface adsorption. It is then normalized on a &quot;per unit area&quot; or &quot;per gram&quot; basis. Adsorption measured using this technique is, therefore, the thermodynamic or Gibbs adsorption. If, however, the adsorbed amount is measured by directly analyzing the solid, the result obtained will correspond to the actual physical accurtiulation on the solid. The latter is referred to as the Guggenheim adsorption. Normally, the distinction between the two types of adsorption is not made, simply because for most surface-active substances the surface concentration is markedly higher than the bulk concentration and, therefore, the Cb term is negligible compared to C,.

An ideal situation in which polymer molecules adsorb on the external surface, and are excluded completely from pores, can be modeled as follows. The adsorption density, f, on a per gram basis is given by r=

where Ci is the initial concentration and Cr is the If the adsorbent is porous such that all the solute is excluded and the solvent is not. then the actual initial concentration will bc higher than Ci and is given by

where L&lt; is the initial voIumc, Cl is the corrcctcd polymer concentration in solution and 1% is the nvcragc pore volume in miIlilitrcs per gram of the solid.

The calculated apparent adsorption, I-.,. using the uncorrected initia1 concentrations is ii, giving information on the porosity of the solid. K dcpcnds on the propcrtics of the solid and its concentration in soiution.

It is clear from Eqn (7) that the apparent adsorption at conccntrations above the saturation concentration will decrease linearly with increasing bulk conccntralion.

A plot of r2 vs Ci for concentrations well above the maximum for dextran-5OOK on porous Biogel HTP is shown in Fig. 8. The linearity of the plot clearly indicates that the levels chosen are well above the saturation concentration.

The estimated pore volume is 1.4 ml g-' and the value of the saturation adsorption is 32.2 mg g-' (Fig. 8). Using these values andEqns (2) and(3 adsorb more than their lower molecular weight counterparts.

Assuming the pores to be cylindrical, and using the estimated pore volume from the adsorption isotherm and the measured surface area by 'he nitrogen adsorption technique, the pore diameter of the Biogel HTP is estimated to be 800 A. We have attempted to compare the calculated pore diameter with the radius of gyration of the polymer in solution. Assuming the polymer to be linear, for dextran-500K, the radius of gyration (R,) and the hydrodynamic diameter (Dl) of the poiymer can be calculated using the following equations [4,5] R, = 0.23 M'.=O (9)

R, is found to be 162.6 8, and D, is 797.0 A. It is clear that these dimensions are indeed comparable to the estimated pore diameter and, therefore, the polymer molecule can be expected to be excluded from such pores. These results are in agreement with the TEM results which show that the pore-size range is between 150 and 1000 8, (Table 1).

We have also attempted to determine the pore size and pore-size distribution using mercury porosimetry and TEM. The former indicated two groups of pores with average sizes of 8 pm and 200 A. The 8 pm pores may well be a result of the void in the aggregates as seen in SEM. This pore-size range is too big to exclude any of the polymers in this study and would not play any role in influencing the adsorption behavior of the polymers. TEM gave pore sizes ranging from 150 to 1000 A. It is mozt reasonable that dextran-500K with a calculated diameter of about 800 8, would be totally excluded from all the micropores. The dextran-15-20K with a calculated diameter of 138-I 59 A would be partially excluded, especially from the pores of 200 _A, realrlting in an adsorption maximum (Fig. 1). Dextran-6K with a calculated diameter of x90 A could gain access to all the pores and this is in agreement with the observation that the corresponding isotherm does not exhibit a maximum.

It is interesting that the results obtained from mercury gorosimetry and TEM are indeed in accordance with the pore-size estimates from the adsorption data and the dimensions of the polymer molecule in solution. Note, however, that the pore volume estimated from mercury porosimetry data is about 40% of the value obtained from polymer adsorption results. The reason for such a big difference is not clear at present. Partial breakdown of some of the internal structure under high pressure during mercury porosimetry can possibly account for some of the observed difference.

Under gentle mixing of the solid with a polymer solution, adsorption isotherms as a function of polymer concentrations exhibited a maximum for each hydroxyapatitr; sample far dextran-5!IOK. The presence of maxima is indicative of some form of polymer exclusion and preferential adsorption of the solvent. SEM of two hydroxyapatite samples indicated a powder-like structure whereas the third sample showed a cake-like morphology.

The first two samples could be broken down by intense mixing, as seen by photomicrographs, and prodsced a norma'l adsorption isotherm after this treatment.

The cake-like sample did no: break down even after sonicstion as judged by th:: amount of polymer adsorbed before and after sonication.

The calculated pore diameter from the adsorption isotherm of an excluded polymer agreed well with the experimentally determined results using mercury porosimetry and TEM. It is clear that the adsorption maximum is due to the exclusion of the high molecular weight polymer from the micropores.

It is evident from this study that thorough investigation of the morphological properties of the adsorbent is necessary in generating meaningful and reproducible adsorption data.

Ol66-6622/92,'$05.00 @I3 1992 -Elscvier Science Publishers B.V. All rights reserved.</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Adsorption on and Surface Chemistry of Hydroxyapati!e</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Misra</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1984</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Methods in Biochemical Analysis</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Win&amp;r</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1955</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colioids Surfaces</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Ananthapadmanabhan</author>
				<author>P Somasundaran</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1983</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Modern Sizc-Exclusion Liquid Chromatography</title>
			<authors/>
			<date>1979</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Polymer Handbook</title>
			<authors/>
			<date/>
		</reference>
	</references>
</document>
