<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Adsorption of bovine serum albumin onto octacalcium phosphate and its hydrolyzates.pdf</file>
	<title>ADSORPTION OF BOVINE SERUM ALBUMIN ONTO OCTACALCIUM PHOSPHATE AND ITS HYDROLYZATES</title>
	<date>Unknown</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Adsorption of bovine serum albumin onto octacalcium phosphate and its hydrolyzates.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>H Suzuki</author>
		<author>Yagi Shita</author>
		<author>M Yamazaki</author>
		<author>T Aoba</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>Octacalcium phosphate (OCP) has been advocated to be a precursor of biomineral s. Tn thi s repo rt , we aimed at investigating OCP hydro lysis and the interacti on of OCP and its hydrolyzates (apatitic products) with bovine serum albumin (BSA). A batch of syntheti c OCP was allowed to hydrolyze either (a) in deioni zed water at 70 °C or (b) in Tris buffer (pH 7.4) containing 2 ppm fluoride at 37°C. OCP hydrolysis was completed within reasonable experimental periods: afte r 48 hours at 70°C and after 10 days at 37 °C in the presence of flu oride. The adsorption isotherms of BSA ont o the o ri ginal OCP and its various hydrolyzates were determined at pH 7. 4 and 37 °C . The BSA adsorption on to all the adsorbents was desc ribed by a Langmuri an mode l. Remarkable findings were that: (1) when the maximum number of BSA adsorption sites was expressed on basis of unit surface area (N , mols/m 2 ), the greatest values of N was obtained for the original OCP ; (2) th e N va lues became smaller with the advance of OCP-apatite conversion in both hydrolysis systems; (3) the affinity values ( K , ml/,umol) were relatively constant for the OCP anti the non-fluoridated hydrolyzates, while the K values increased markedly after hydrolys is of OCP in the presence of flu o ride. The results of th e present work support the hypothesis that the process o f precurso r precipitation and its subsequent hydrolysis tak ing place in forming hard tissues may be modulated thro ugh the matrix protein-crystals interaction. It seems li kely that flu oride ions has a dual role, i.e., acceleration of OCP hydrolysis and, once incorporated into the crystals, enhancement of the protein-mineral interaction .</abstract>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>Materials and Methods</heading>
			<text>Preparation of OCP and its hydrolyzates Reagent grade chemicals were used in the current work. A batch of OCP was prepared by direct precipitation at pH 5 to 6 and 60 ( ± 2) oc according to the method of LeGeros (1985). The precipitates were washed several times with deionized water and then lyophilized. The recovered solid was passed through a USA standard testing sieve (270-mesh, 53 Jlffi pore size). In a series of preliminary experiments, we examined effects of various factors on the kinetics of OCP hydrolysis. The factors tested were solid/solution ratios in equilibration media, temperature (37, 60, 70, and 80°C) and pH (6.0, 7.4, and 8.0) , fluoride concentrations in the range of 0 and 10 ppm F as NaF, and equilibration periods covering from 1 hour through 10 days . The nature of solid products was characterized by X-ray diffraction (XRD) and Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR) as described below. As a consequence of the results obtained in those preliminary trials and with the purpose to secure both fluoridated and nonfluoridated OCP hydrolyzates, OCP hydrolysis was investigated in two solutions: (A) deionized water at 70°C in the absence of fluoride and (B) in 150 mM Tris buffer at pH 7.4 and 37°C in the presence of 2 ppm fluoride. The details of the procedure used for the hydrolysis were as follows:

(A) One gram of OCP powder was suspended in 10 ml of the solution, sonicated for 1 minute, and then introduced into a reaction plastic vessel containing 200 ml of deionized water. The reaction vessel was tightly sealed with a rubber stopper and settled in the water bath that was maintained at 70°C. The resulting slurry was continuously agitated with a magnetic stirrer. Samples were withdrawn periodically from the agitated slurry and centrifuged at 12,000 g. The supernatant was then carefully removed from the tube for analyses (Ca, P, and pH), while the pellet was freeze-dried and subjected to FTIR analysis. At this hi gh temperature, the OCP hydrolysis was insured to complete within 48 hours. Thus, aliquots, roughly corresponding to one third of the slurry, were taken at short intervals, namely 6, 24 and 48 hours. The suspension recovered was separated by centrifugation. The supernatant was collected and then analyzed with respect to concentrations of the lattice ions (Ca2+, phosphate, H+, and F). The solid obtained as pellet was lyophilized and then passed through the sieve.

(B) One gram of the same batch of OCP was incubated in 1 liter of 150 mM Tris buffer (pH 7 .4), which contained 2 ppm F, as well as 4 mM azide for bacteriostat. Equilibration and sample collection were carried out in the same manner as described above. At 3rC, OCP hydrolysis proceeded at much slower rates and completed after 10 days incubation. Thus, fractions of the slurry were withdrawn to recover the solids at 1, 3, and 10 days during the equilibration.

In addition to those OCP and hydrol yzates , hydroxyapatite (HAp) synthesized at 80°C was used as adsorbent in the required adsorption experiments. The crystals exhibi ted long, blade-like appearance. The details of preparation and characterization of that batch of HAp were reported previously (Shimoda et al., 1990).</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Adsorption experiment</heading>
			<text>The adsorbate used was BSA {molecular weight (M.W.): 66 kD; Sigma Chern. Co., St. Louis, MO), which was dissolved in 150 mM Tris buffer at pH 7.4. The general experimental procedures to o btain the adsorption isotherms of BSA onto the various adsorbents were those used previously (Aoba and Moreno, 1985). Each of the adsorbents having different specific surface areas (see Table 1) was accurately weighed to provide the total surface area of 0.12 m 2 /g . The weighed crystals were added to 1.5 ml of the experimental solution in polystyrene tubes. Controls without either adsorbent or adsorbate were included in all experiments. Equilibration was conducted by end-over-end rotation at 37°C. In the first series of experiments, the time sequence of BSA adsorpti on onto either OCP or HAp crystals was examined by preparing a series of the adsorbate-adsorbent mixtures. After equil ibrati on, at specified periods ranging from 15 minutes to 24 hours, each suspension was centrifuged and, thereafter, the supernatant was carefully recovered. BSA concentrations in both the original experimental solution and the supernatant were determined by protein assay (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). The amount of BSA adsorbed was obtained by the difference between the analytical values of BSA concentrations before and after equilibration. Part of the recovered supernatant was also used for determination of calcium and total phosphate concentrations, and pH values. In the second series of adsorption experiments, we examined effects of calcium and phosphate concentrations in solution on the BSA adsorption onto OCP and HAp. In those cases, all equilibrations were carried out at a fixed equilibration time (2 hours, see Results) otherwise in the same way as described above. In the last series of adsorption experiments, BSA adsorption onto all the adsorbents was examined in a wide range of the equilibrium concentrations so that the adsorption isotherms Table 1. Chemical composition and specific surface area (SSA) of OCP, its hydrolyzates, and non-stoichiometric hydroxyapatite. were constructed at 3rC. To this end, the total surface areas of the adsorbents used were varied from 0.06 to 0.18 m 2 . Initial concentrations of BSA were in the range of 0.15 through 1.5 mg/ml. In order to minimize dissolution or alteration of the adsorbent crystals during equilibration, the initial adsorbate solution contained 0.5 mM calcium and 0.5 mM phosphate.

X-ray diffraction, Fourier transfom1 infrared spectroscopy, and scanning electron microscopy (SEM)

All adsorbent samples before and after equilibration with BSA were examined by FTIR and, if samples were enough for analysis, by XRD, too . FTIR spectra were obtained by means of a diffuse-reflectance attachment in a Perkin-Elmer 1600 FTIR (Perkin-Elmer, Norwalk, CT). Usually, 64 spectral scans were conducted over the range of 4500 to 450 cm-1 with 2 cm-1 resolution . X-ray diffraction patterns of those samples were recorded with a D/Max X-ray powder diffractometer (Rigaku USA, Peabody, MA) equipped with a rotating anode and a graphite monochrometer. In order to detect the characteristic (100) reflection of OCP at 28 = 4. 75 degrees, a step-scanning was done at 0.02 degrees interval in the range of 3.5 and 60 degrees. The original batch of OCP and its hydrolyzates were examined in a Hitachi S-4000 SEM (Tokyo, Japan) operating at an accelerating voltage of 2.5 kV. Before observation, powder samples were placed with the aid of a paste on aluminum stubs and then coated with a thin layer (approx. 4 nm) of platinum.

Chemical analysis and determination of specific surface area (SSA)  (Vogel, 1961), respectively. Fluoride concentration of the recovered supernatant was directly determined with an ionselective electrode (Orion #10003, Cambridge, MA) .

The fluoride content of the solid samples was determined according to the microdiffusion procedure with hexamethyldisiloxane (Whitford and Reynolds, 1979;Aoba et al., 1989). Special attention was given to the acid phosphate of the solid samples because even a subtle decrease in the acid phosphate most likely reflects the conversion from OCP to apatite. In practice, the acid phosphate was determined by the procedure reported by Gee and Deitz (1953) after pyrolysis of the solid at 600°C for 24 hours; a full consideration about the pyrolysis conditions and analytical procedures was given elsewhere (Shimoda et al., 1991). Specific surface areas of the original OCP and its hydrolyzates were determined by nitrogen adsorption.</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>Min eralizati on events taking place in bone and tooth are in essence organized untler contro ls by the tissuespeci fie cell s and the sec reted matrix proteins. However, much still remains to be learned about the mechanism by which the proliferation and growth of biorninera l progress in a concerted manner in ex tracellular spaces. Recent in vivo anti in vitro work provided evitlence that the morpholog ic and structural features of bio mineral, such as enamel crystals, are most satisfactorily ex plained by the epitax ial overgrowth of apatite on the &lt; 100 &gt; direc tion o f octacalcium phosphate (OCP, (Ca 8 H 2 (P0 4 ) 6 •5H 2 0) (Nelson and Barry , 1989;Iijima et al . , 1992a;Miake er al ., 1993). The OCP is not the most stab le phase, but can hydrolyze to basic calcium phospha te under physiological conditi ons. It is also becoming clear that the majo r incorporat ion o f impurities (e.g., ca rbonate ions) into biomineral takes place during the hydrolysis process and that the substituted impurities in turn affect the chemi cal and physical properties of the crystals (Chickerur et a! . , 1980;Brown et al., 1987 ;Si ew et al. , 1992). Despite the wealth of information as to effects of various ionic regulators (e.g., ca rbonate, pyrophosphate, citrate, Mi+ , F.) on OCP hydrolys is (LeGeros er al., 1984 , 19 89;Bigi et al., 198 8;Iijima et al. , !992b;Tung et al., 1992) , there is a paucity o f information as to whether OCP may interact selecti vely with macromolecul es and whether the precursor hydrolysis may weaken or strengthen the matrix protein-mineral interaction , thereby modulating the subsequent mineralization process . On the basis of these considerations, we prepared OCP and various batches of fluoridated and non-fluoridated OCP hydrolyzates and, using those crystals as adsorbents, investigated their adso rption properti es with bovine serum albumin (BSA). The rati onale fo r the use of BSA as adsorbate is that (a) the material is well characterized and commercially available and, from a bi ological point of view, (b) serum-deri vetl macro molecul es are involved in most biominerali za ti on processes, of particular interest in reactive bone inducti on with ca lcium phosphate implants. 0. Suzuki , H . Yagashita, M. Yamazaki and T . Aoba Indeed, previous studies indicated that selective adsorption of serum constituents, including albumin, occurred onto OCP shortly after its implantation into the subperiosteal space on mouse calvaria (Suzuki et al., 1993).

Preparation of OCP and its hydrolyzates Reagent grade chemicals were used in the current work. A batch of OCP was prepared by direct precipitation at pH 5 to 6 and 60 ( ± 2) oc according to the method of LeGeros (1985). The precipitates were washed several times with deionized water and then lyophilized. The recovered solid was passed through a USA standard testing sieve (270-mesh, 53 Jlffi pore size). In a series of preliminary experiments, we examined effects of various factors on the kinetics of OCP hydrolysis. The factors tested were solid/solution ratios in equilibration media, temperature (37, 60, 70, and 80°C) and pH (6.0, 7.4, and 8.0) , fluoride concentrations in the range of 0 and 10 ppm F as NaF, and equilibration periods covering from 1 hour through 10 days . The nature of solid products was characterized by X-ray diffraction (XRD) and Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (FTIR) as described below. As a consequence of the results obtained in those preliminary trials and with the purpose to secure both fluoridated and nonfluoridated OCP hydrolyzates, OCP hydrolysis was investigated in two solutions: (A) deionized water at 70°C in the absence of fluoride and (B) in 150 mM Tris buffer at pH 7.4 and 37°C in the presence of 2 ppm fluoride. The details of the procedure used for the hydrolysis were as follows:

(A) One gram of OCP powder was suspended in 10 ml of the solution, sonicated for 1 minute, and then introduced into a reaction plastic vessel containing 200 ml of deionized water. The reaction vessel was tightly sealed with a rubber stopper and settled in the water bath that was maintained at 70°C. The resulting slurry was continuously agitated with a magnetic stirrer. Samples were withdrawn periodically from the agitated slurry and centrifuged at 12,000 g. The supernatant was then carefully removed from the tube for analyses (Ca, P, and pH), while the pellet was freeze-dried and subjected to FTIR analysis. At this hi gh temperature, the OCP hydrolysis was insured to complete within 48 hours. Thus, aliquots, roughly corresponding to one third of the slurry, were taken at short intervals, namely 6, 24 and 48 hours. The suspension recovered was separated by centrifugation. The supernatant was collected and then analyzed with respect to concentrations of the lattice ions (Ca2+, phosphate, H+, and F). The solid obtained as pellet was lyophilized and then passed through the sieve.

(B) One gram of the same batch of OCP was incubated in 1 liter of 150 mM Tris buffer (pH 7 .4), which contained 2 ppm F, as well as 4 mM azide for bacteriostat. Equilibration and sample collection were carried out in the same manner as described above. At 3rC, OCP hydrolysis proceeded at much slower rates and completed after 10 days incubation. Thus, fractions of the slurry were withdrawn to recover the solids at 1, 3, and 10 days during the equilibration.

In addition to those OCP and hydrol yzates , hydroxyapatite (HAp) synthesized at 80°C was used as adsorbent in the required adsorption experiments. The crystals exhibi ted long, blade-like appearance. The details of preparation and characterization of that batch of HAp were reported previously (Shimoda et al., 1990).

The adsorbate used was BSA {molecular weight (M.W.): 66 kD; Sigma Chern. Co., St. Louis, MO), which was dissolved in 150 mM Tris buffer at pH 7.4. The general experimental procedures to o btain the adsorption isotherms of BSA onto the various adsorbents were those used previously (Aoba and Moreno, 1985). Each of the adsorbents having different specific surface areas (see Table 1) was accurately weighed to provide the total surface area of 0.12 m 2 /g . The weighed crystals were added to 1.5 ml of the experimental solution in polystyrene tubes. Controls without either adsorbent or adsorbate were included in all experiments. Equilibration was conducted by end-over-end rotation at 37°C. In the first series of experiments, the time sequence of BSA adsorpti on onto either OCP or HAp crystals was examined by preparing a series of the adsorbate-adsorbent mixtures. After equil ibrati on, at specified periods ranging from 15 minutes to 24 hours, each suspension was centrifuged and, thereafter, the supernatant was carefully recovered. BSA concentrations in both the original experimental solution and the supernatant were determined by protein assay (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). The amount of BSA adsorbed was obtained by the difference between the analytical values of BSA concentrations before and after equilibration. Part of the recovered supernatant was also used for determination of calcium and total phosphate concentrations, and pH values. In the second series of adsorption experiments, we examined effects of calcium and phosphate concentrations in solution on the BSA adsorption onto OCP and HAp. In those cases, all equilibrations were carried out at a fixed equilibration time (2 hours, see Results) otherwise in the same way as described above. In the last series of adsorption experiments, BSA adsorption onto all the adsorbents was examined in a wide range of the equilibrium concentrations so that the adsorption isotherms Table 1. Chemical composition and specific surface area (SSA) of OCP, its hydrolyzates, and non-stoichiometric hydroxyapatite. were constructed at 3rC. To this end, the total surface areas of the adsorbents used were varied from 0.06 to 0.18 m 2 . Initial concentrations of BSA were in the range of 0.15 through 1.5 mg/ml. In order to minimize dissolution or alteration of the adsorbent crystals during equilibration, the initial adsorbate solution contained 0.5 mM calcium and 0.5 mM phosphate.

X-ray diffraction, Fourier transfom1 infrared spectroscopy, and scanning electron microscopy (SEM)

All adsorbent samples before and after equilibration with BSA were examined by FTIR and, if samples were enough for analysis, by XRD, too . FTIR spectra were obtained by means of a diffuse-reflectance attachment in a Perkin-Elmer 1600 FTIR (Perkin-Elmer, Norwalk, CT). Usually, 64 spectral scans were conducted over the range of 4500 to 450 cm-1 with 2 cm-1 resolution . X-ray diffraction patterns of those samples were recorded with a D/Max X-ray powder diffractometer (Rigaku USA, Peabody, MA) equipped with a rotating anode and a graphite monochrometer. In order to detect the characteristic (100) reflection of OCP at 28 = 4. 75 degrees, a step-scanning was done at 0.02 degrees interval in the range of 3.5 and 60 degrees. The original batch of OCP and its hydrolyzates were examined in a Hitachi S-4000 SEM (Tokyo, Japan) operating at an accelerating voltage of 2.5 kV. Before observation, powder samples were placed with the aid of a paste on aluminum stubs and then coated with a thin layer (approx. 4 nm) of platinum.

Chemical analysis and determination of specific surface area (SSA)  (Vogel, 1961), respectively. Fluoride concentration of the recovered supernatant was directly determined with an ionselective electrode (Orion #10003, Cambridge, MA) .

The fluoride content of the solid samples was determined according to the microdiffusion procedure with hexamethyldisiloxane (Whitford and Reynolds, 1979;Aoba et al., 1989). Special attention was given to the acid phosphate of the solid samples because even a subtle decrease in the acid phosphate most likely reflects the conversion from OCP to apatite. In practice, the acid phosphate was determined by the procedure reported by Gee and Deitz (1953) after pyrolysis of the solid at 600°C for 24 hours; a full consideration about the pyrolysis conditions and analytical procedures was given elsewhere (Shimoda et al., 1991). Specific surface areas of the original OCP and its hydrolyzates were determined by nitrogen adsorption.

Figure 1 shows X-ray diffraction patterns of the original OCP and its hydrolysis products obtained at 70°C. All reflections observed for the synthesized OCP including the characteristic (100) reflection (Fig. lA) corresponded well to those expected from the OCP structure (Mathew et al., 1988). OCP-apatite conversion progressed steadily as a function of the incubation time. In Figure 1, the patterns B and C showed that samples removed near the middle of hydrolysis process (6 and 24 hours) were comprised of both OCP and apatite. The (100) reflection of OCP disappeared completely and only apatitic reflections were obtained from the 0. Suzuki, H. Yagashita, M. Yamazaki and T. Aoba resulting product after 48 hours hydrolysis (Fig . 1D); the conversion into moderately well crystallized apatite crystals was indicated by their well resolved reflections.

As can be seen in Figure 2, the OCP hydrolysis occurred at much slower rates at 37 °C even in the presence of2 ppm F. The (100) OCP reflection disappeared completely after extending the incubation up to 10 days. At 37°C, the resulting apatites yielded broad and overlapped reflections, except for the (002) reflection, indicating their low crystallinity.

Figure 3 shows scanning electron micrographs of the OCP and its hydrolyzates. OCP crystals exhibited platy morphology, several ~m in length; usually those crystals showed smooth surfaces and smooth terminal s (Fig. 3A) . The hydrolyzates obtained at 70°C still retained the original platy mo-rphology (Figs. 3B through 3D). The hydrolyzates obtained at 3rC in the presence of fluoride displayed wide variations in morphology and particle size (Figs. 3E through 3G): some crystals retained the original platy morphology, while others were small in particle size, thin-blade in appearance , having pointed terminals. The latter suggested de novo precipitation of apatite crystals on the platy templets, mostly due to acceleration of the kinetic rates by fluoride ions.

Table 1 shows the chemical composition and SSA of the OCP and its hydrolyzates. The composition of the OCP batch was Ca-deficient, having the Ca/P molar ratio of 1.26. The acid phosphate (38% of the total P) was slightly higher than that expected for the OCP stoichiometry, although analyses by XRD and FTIR ruled out contamination of dicalcium phosphate. Regarding the high acid phosphate content, Mathew et al. (1988) recently reported a new formula of OCP, Ca 16 H 4 +x(P0 4 ) 12 (0H)x•(l0-x)H 2 0 . According to this formula, the authors stated that the maximum acid phc.s,. phate assessed by pyrolysis can correspond to about 40 % of the total phosphorus. At this time, we do not have further information about the stoichiometry and structure of the OCP batch used. The apatite products were nonstoichiometric, exhibiting low Ca/P values (around 1.48). It was also found that: (a) the acid phosphate decreased consistenly with the advance of OCP hydrolysis, (b) nevertheless, the resulting apatite crystals still contained high acid phosphate as observed for enamel crystals at early developmental stages (Shimada et a/., 1991), and (c) the fluoride contents of all hydrolyzed products obtained at 37°C were constant, regardless of the incubation time. The fluoride contents obtained (0.22-0.25% weight) correspond roughly to substitution of fluoride into one tenth of the OH sites on the assumption of its homogeneous distribution in the apatite lattice. Consistent with those results obtained from solid samples, analysis of the experimental solution proved that most of the fluoride in solution was removed, decreasing sharply from the initial2 ppm to barely detectable levels (below 0.01 ppm), within 1 hour upon introduction of the crystals in the solution. The OCP hydrolysis was also accompanied by an increase of the SSA. The finding that the hydrolyzates obtained at 70°C had lower values of SSA than the hydrolysis products at 3rC is also consistent with their differences in morphology and crystallinity obtained by SEM and XRD. As shown in Table 1, the HAp exhibited non-stoichiometric composition, containing 10.6% total P as acid phosphate.

Figure 4 illustrates the time course of BSA adsorption onto OCP and HAp. The amount of protein molecules adsorbed onto the solid surface increased rapid! y in the first 15 minutes, thereafter remaining constant mg/ml, the total surface area of the adsorbents = 0.06 m 2 /ml, and the equilibration time = 2 hours. Note that, excep t for a marked decrease of adsorption in the presence of the highest concentration of phosphate, BSA adsorpt ion levels were relatively constant, regardless of wide variations of solute concentrations in the experimental solutions. over the range of time studied. In those experiments, no calci urn and phosphate were added to the original adsorbate solution. At the end of equilibration using OCP as adsorbent, some of the lattice ions were released from the adsorbent crystals; theCa and P0 4 concentrations increased up to 0.5 mM and 0.7 mM, respectively, which were explained by dissolution, at maximum 5%, of the total OCP crystals used. In the equilibration systems using HAp, both Ca and P0 4 concentrations were much lower, close to 0.1 mM or below. Since the buffer solution at the high concentration was used for equilibration , changes in pH values were only marginal, if any.

Figure 5 illustrates the effects of calcium and phosphate concentrations in solution on BSA adsorption onto OCP and HAp. Fairly constant adsorption of BSA onto OCP was obtained over the range of Ca and P0 4 concentrations tested, whereas the addition of the highest P0 4 concentration gave rise to a marked decrease of the protein adsorption onto both OCP and HAp. At present, we do not have an unequivocal explanation for the observed effect of phosphate ions, although one may argue that high concentrations of negatively charged (mostly divalent) ions may cause electrostatic modification of apatite surfaces or changes of protein conformation in solution . Nevertheless, it is noteworthy that the addition 4.0 . . -----------------,   C, mglmL Figure 6. Adsorption isotherms of BSA onto synthetic OCP and its hydrolyzed products at 37°C. Equilibration was carried out in 150 mM tris buffer containing 0.5 mM Ca and 0.5 mM P0 4 . Adsorbents used were: (A) OCP, (B) intermediate products comprising OCP and apatite, which were obtained after 1-day equilibration in the presence of 2 ppm F, and (C) apatite crystals converted from OCP after 10-day equilibration in the presence of 2 ppm.  Wavenumber (em•')

Figure 7. FTIR absorption spectra of synthetic OCP taken (A) before and (B) after equilibration with 1.5 mg BSA/ml for 2 hours. The spectrum shown in (C) was obtained by subtraction procedure, (B) -(A). Note that there occurred no appreciable changes in OCP spectral feature after equilibration with BSA. Two prominent absorption bands stemming from the adsorbed BSA were discerned at 1655 and 1538 cm-1 • Figure 6 gives the adsorption isotherms of BSA onto the OCP and its fluoridated hydrolyzates (obtained after 1 and 10 days hydrolysis), which were determined in the presence of0.5 mM Ca and 0.5 mM P0 4 at pH 7.4 and 37°C. In all cases, the experimental data yielded typical Langmurian isotherms (Moreno et al. , 1978) which were characterized by an initial increase in adsorption with the equilibrium concentration of BSA, followed by a plateau indicating a proximity to adsorption saturation. On the basis of this adsorption model, the adsorption parameters were determined according to the equation:

where Q is the amount of BSA adsorbed onto the solid, C is the BSA concentration in equilibration, N is the maximum number of adsorption sites per unit of surface area, and the parameter K reflects the affinity that BSA molecules have for the adsorption sites. Table 2 shows 0 . Suzuki , H. Yagashita , M . Yamazaki and T. Aoba the values of N and K, which were calculated by nonlinear least squares regression of the experimental data. In most cases, the correlation coefficients of regressions (r) were 0 .98. Remarkable findings were that (1) theN values became smaller for the hydrolyzed products than that obtained for the OCP, (2) the fluoridated hydrolyzates exhibited slightly lower values of N as co mpared with the non-fluoridated products, and (3) the K values for the non-fluoridated products decreased consistently with the progress of OCP-apatite conversion, while the fluoridated apatites had significantly higher affinity for BSA. At present, no plausible explanation is available as to why the N values should decrease with the progressive conversion of OCP to apatite, although the obtained difference in the adsorption sites surely reflects the distinct structures between OCP and apatite cry stals.

Since the crystal structure of metastable OCP and its intermediate hydrolyzed products could be altered during the protein equilibration, special care was given to characterize the nature and co mposition of the adsorbents recovered after the equilibration. Figure 7 shows an example of such attempts by FT1R. FTIR spectrum of the original OCP (Fig. 7 A) corresponded well to that reported by others (Fowler et al., 1966). The spectrum of the OCP recovered after equilibration with the initial concentration of 1.5 mg BSA /ml (Fig. 7B), was identical to that of the original crystals, except for the appearance:: of amide bands in the wave-number range o f I ,400 and 1,700 cm• 1 , which stemmed from the adsorbed BSA molecules. Similar analyses by FTIR, as well as XRD , also confirmed that no apparent structural changes were discerned for all hydrolyzates before and after the equilibration with BSA (data not included) .

The present studies provide further evidence that the synthesized OCP crystals can be converted into apatite crystals within reasonably short periods. The temperature markedly affected the hydrolysis kinetics and the crystallinity of the apatite crystals formed . Another factor of probable biological importance is the fluorid e ion concentration in solution: (a) The well-grown OCP crystals remained stable at 37 °C and pH 7.4 over 10 days even in agitated solutions containing low concentrations of F. such as 0.2 ppm or below (data not included); it is of interest that the precipitating OCP crystals were hydrolyzed concurrently even at such low fluoride concentrations, advancing a solid-solution transformation (Mura-Galelli et al., 1992). (b) Higher concentrations of fluoride in the range of l and I 0 ppm were required to complete the hydrolysis of the synthesized OCP within 10 days at the physiological temperature. The resulting fluoridated apatite crystal s were Ca-defi-cient, exhibiting platy or thin-blade appeara1ce. The general feature of their XRD patterns and th: values of SSA (50-60 m 2 I g) are simi Jar to those o\tai_ned for young enamel mineral at early developmettal stages (Aoba et al., 1987; Aoba and Moreno, 1990 .   52   All the results of the present adsorptionstudies, in agreement with the prev ious reports (Monno et al. , 1977 ;Hlady and Fliredi-Milhofer, 1978), irdicate that BSA behaves as a relatively strong adsorbateonto calcium phosphate crystals. Most interestingly, he adsorption behavior of BSA onto OCP and the hydrdys is products was similar to that onto HAp: all the ads&lt;rption isotherms were described well by the Langmuiradsorption model; the adsorption parameters obtained f1r the OCP crystals were in the same range as those mtained for synthetic HAp, regardless of the difference irtheir crystal structures. The foregoing finding s pro\\de the rationale that serum albumin is a strong inhilitor of the crystal growth of calcium phosphates in virro (Robinson et al., 1992), although its biological signiicance still remains open . Previously, E idelman et al. 1987) suggested that serum constituents with molectlar weight above 50 kD may facilitate hydrolysis of OC to an apatitic product. Our current work ascertain:d that the OCP hydrolysis was retarded markedly by pr:adsorption with BSA or bone matrix proteins even in scl ution containing 10 ppm flu oride (data not included) .

An expected , but still interesting findit g was that the enhancement of the adso1-ption bond ont fluoridated hydrolyzates took place without affecting tht parameter N. Similar enhanci ng effects of fluoride on the adsorption of salivary or enamel proteins have bem reported previously using a seri es of flu oridated apaites having various magnitudes of lluoride substitution , Moreno et al., 1978;Tanabe et al., 1988). The obsevation that the adsorption affinity was maximized for thecompletely hydrolyzed crystal s, leads to the proposition hat fluoride ions modulate the protein adsorption unique'y onto apatite surfaces, most probably by lowering sur&quot;ace energy and thereby facilitating water desorption equisite for protein adsorption (Tanabe er al., 1988) . The above proposition was partially supported by the _. inding that fluoride ions in solubl e state even at concent•ation of 10 ppm did not yield di stinctive effects on the ESA adsorption onto OCP or apatite c rystals (data not n cluded).

The current work using BSA as adsorb&lt;te provided so me insight into protein-OCP (or its hydn,Jyzates) interaction . It is obviously of interest to ea rn about whether tooth or bone-specitic proteins, e.g ., non-collagenous proteins in enamel, dentin , and bone, may exhibit strong adsorption onto OCP as well as apatite surfaces. Preliminary evidence was obtained in adsorption studies using enamel matrix protei ns, in w1ich the secreted amelogenins adsorb selectively onto OCP as well as onto hydroxyapa tite (Aoba et al., 1987). As reported by others (Doi et al., 1993;Fiiredi-Milhofer et al., 1994), dentin and boone matrix proteins appear to interact with OCP, affecting the precipitation process. Taken together, it is reasonable to assume that early extracellular events in tooth and bone formation involves the interaction between matrix proteins and OCP precursor, which in tum may affect the precursor hydrolysis, consequently, the mineralization process. In that whole process, fluoride ions seem to have a dual role, i.e., acceleration of OCP hydrolysis and, once incorporated into the crystals, enhancement of the protein-mineral interaction.

Discussion with Reviewers R.Z. LeGeros: What is the pH of the deionized water at 70°? (A) and (B) solutions differ in different aspects; (a) presence ofF; (b) composition: deionized water vs . Tri s buffer; (c) temperature, 70°C vs. 37°C; (d) pH:? vs. 7 .4. There appears to be no variable in common between solutions A and B. How can one compare these variables? Authors: We did not measure the pH value at 70°C. The experimental solutions, having no variables in common , were selected to secure two types of OCP hydrolyzates, with and without fluoride substitutions. As the reviewer knows (and we described in the text), the hydrolysi s rate of OCP in the absence of fluoride at 37°C is quite slow. With thi s restriction , we forced to conduct one hydrolysis experiment at the high temperature. At 3rC, we chose other conditions to simulate the physiological medi a.

Reviewer III: In the introduction, the statement &quot;serum-derived macro mol ecul es are involved in most biomineralization processes&quot; is not accurate. Usually, the active organic matter is sy nthesized by specialized cell s, e.g., osteoblasts, ameloblasts, etc. Authors : It was establi shed that serum derived proteins, e.g . , a2-l-IS-g lycoprotei ns, are involved with tissue-specifi c matrix proteins. Thus we do not agree with the reviewer's commen t.

of 0.5 mM of both calcium and phosphate ions to the</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Aoba</author>
				<author>J Collins</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1989</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif. Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Aoba</author>
				<author>M Fukae</author>
				<author>T Tanabe</author>
				<author>M Shimizu</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1987</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Aoba</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1985</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif. Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Aoba</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1990</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Inorg. Biochem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Bigi</author>
				<author>M Gazzano</author>
				<author>A Ripamonti</author>
				<author>N Roveri</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1988</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adv. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Brown</author>
				<author>N Eidelman</author>
				<author>B Tomzaic</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1987</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif. Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Chickerur</author>
				<author>M Tung</author>
				<author>W Brown</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1980</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif. Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Doi</author>
				<author>T Horiguchi</author>
				<author>S Kim</author>
				<author>Y Moriwaki</author>
				<author>N Wakamatsu</author>
				<author>M Adachi</author>
				<author>H Shigeta</author>
				<author>S Sasaki</author>
				<author>H Shimokawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1993</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif. Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Eidelman</author>
				<author>L Chow</author>
				<author>W Brown</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1987</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Arch. Oral Bioi</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B Fowler</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>W Brown</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1966</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Connect. Tissue Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Fiiredi-Milhofer</author>
				<author>J Moradian-Oldak</author>
				<author>S Weiner</author>
				<author>A Veis</author>
				<author>K Mintz</author>
				<author>L Addadi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1994</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Anal. Chern</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Gee</author>
				<author>V Deitz</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1953</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Coli. Int. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>V Hlady</author>
				<author>H Fiiredi-Milhofer</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1978</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Crystal Growth</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Iijima</author>
				<author>H Tohda</author>
				<author>Y Moriwaki</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif. Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Iijima</author>
				<author>H Tohda</author>
				<author>H Suzuki</author>
				<author>T Yanagisawa</author>
				<author>Y Moriwaki</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif. Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Legeros</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1985</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Scanning Electron Microscopy</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Legeros</author>
				<author>R Kijkowska</author>
				<author>J Legeros</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1984</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Scanning Microsc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Legeros</author>
				<author>G Daculsi</author>
				<author>I Orly</author>
				<author>T Abergas</author>
				<author>W Torres</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1989</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Crystal structure of octacalcium bis(hydrogenp h o s ph ate) tetra b i s(p hospha t e) pen tahyd rate, Ca 8 (HP0 4 h(P</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Mathew</author>
				<author>W Brown</author>
				<author>L Schroeder</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1988</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Crystallographic Spectroscopic Res</title>
			<authors/>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif. Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Miake</author>
				<author>S Shimoda</author>
				<author>M Fukae</author>
				<author>T Aoba</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1993</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Caries Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>M Kresak</author>
				<author>R Zahradnik</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Arch. Oral Bioi</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>M Kresak</author>
				<author>D Hay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1978</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Cells and Materials</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Mura-Galelli</author>
				<author>H Narusawa</author>
				<author>T Shimada</author>
				<author>Iijima Sur&lt;i</author>
				<author>H Yagashita</author>
				<author>M Yamazaki</author>
				<author>T Aoba</author>
				<author>M Aoba</author>
				<author>T</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Anat. Rec</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Dga Nel Son</author>
				<author>J Barry</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1989</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Robinson</author>
				<author>J Kirkham</author>
				<author>S Brooke</author>
				<author>R Shore</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Shimada</author>
				<author>T Aoba</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Shimada</author>
				<author>T Aoba</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>Y Iiake</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1990</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif. Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Siew</author>
				<author>S Gruninger</author>
				<author>C Chow</author>
				<author>W Brown</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Bone and Iineral</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Suzuki 0</author>
				<author>M Nakamura</author>
				<author>Y Miyasaa</author>
				<author>M Kagayama</author>
				<author>M Sakurai</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1993</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Tanabe</author>
				<author>T Aoba</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1988</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs . Oral</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Tung</author>
				<author>B Tomazic</author>
				<author>W Brown</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Quantitative Inrgani c Analysis</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Vogel</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1961</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J . Dent. Re</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Whitford</author>
				<author>K Reynolds</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
	</references>
</document>
