<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Adsorption of bovine serum albumin and lysozyme on hydrophobic calcium hydroxyapatites.pdf</file>
	<title>Unknown</title>
	<date>Unknown</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Adsorption of bovine serum albumin and lysozyme on hydrophobic calcium hydroxyapatites.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors/>
	<abstract>The adsorption of bovine serum albumin (BSA) and lysozyme (LSZ) to oleyl phosphate(OP)-grafted calcium hydroxyapatite (OP-CaHAP) with different degrees of hydrophobicity, ranging the number of surface oleyl group per unit nm 2 (n O ) from 0 to 2.60, was investigated. The pronounced effects of the hydrophobic moiety of adsorbent on protein adsorption were observed. The saturated amount of adsorbed BSA (n s ) was increased up to n O ‫؍‬ 0.6 by an enlargement of hydrophobic interaction between hydrophobic CaHAP particle and proteins. However, n s decreased at n O &gt; 1.3 by increasing the electrostatic repulsive force between negatively charged BSA and OP-CaHAP particles. On the other hand, the n s value of LSZ was continuously increased up to n O ‫؍‬ 2.0 and saturated by increasing either the hydrophobic interaction or the electrostatic attraction of positively charged LSZ and negatively charged OP-grafted CaHAPs. The BSA adsorption experiment revealed that the effect of positively charged adsorption sites on the exposed ac or bc crystal faces (C-sites) of the CaHAPs is screened by the OP-groups grafted on their particle surfaces.</abstract>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>MATERIALS AND METHODS</heading>
			<text>Eight kinds of colloidal CaHAPs with different numbers of surface oleyl groups were used (Table 1). These particles were produced in our previous study (12), and were synthesized from a coprecipitation reaction of Ca(OH) 2 and H 3 PO 4 with different amounts of disodium oleyl phosphate (DSOP) in water-ethanol mixtures. A solution containing 0.04 mol of Ca(OH) 2 was prepared in a 5.0-dm 3 screw-capped Nalgene polypropylene bottle by dissolving, with stirring, 3 g of Ca(OH) 2 in 2.0 dm 3 of deionized and distilled water free from CO 2 under an N 2 atmosphere. To the Ca(OH) 2 solution a waterethanol solution of DSOP and 2.4 ϫ 10 Ϫ2 mol of H 3 PO 4 was added immediately at room temperature. The details of the preparation and properties of OP-grafted CaHAP particles were reported in our previous paper (12). Some properties of the OP-grafted CaHAP particles are listed in Table 1. It should be mentioned that the number of oleyl groups per nm 2 of particle surface (n O ) is widely varied from 0 to 2.60. After OP grafting, the CaHAP particles are hydrophobic, rather than hydrophilic, in nature and tend to disperse in a cyclohexane phase rather than a water phase at n O Ն 2.0. BSA and LSZ, supplied by Sigma Co., were used as proteins. The isoelectric points of BSA and LSZ are 4.7 and 11.1, respectively.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Adsorption Experiment</heading>
			<text>The conventional adsorption experiment was carried out in 10-cm 3 Nalgene polypropylene centrifugation tubes in which varying concentrations of protein solutions in a 1 ϫ 10 Ϫ4 mol dm Ϫ3 KCl solution of pH 6.0 were added to disperse the OP-grafted CaHAPs (150 mg) as described elsewhere (6). The initial concentrations of BSA and LSZ were 0 -10 and 0 -2 mg cm Ϫ3 , respectively. The polypropylene centrifugation tubes were gently rotated at 15°C for 48 h in a thermostat. The concentration of proteins in the supernatant after centrifugation was determined by a microbiuret method using an ultraviolet absorption band at 310 nm. The electrophoretic mobility (em) of the protein-covered OP-grafted CaHAP particles was measured by using an electrophoresis apparatus as reported before (6).</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>Protein adsorption onto various surfaces in aqueous systems has been studied over the past few decades by many researchers because of its significance in various fields such as dentistry, food science, and medicine. Nowadays, calcium hydroxyapatite [Ca 10 (PO 4 ) 6 (OH) 2 , denoted CaHAP] receives much attention in these fields because this material is a major inorganic component of biological hard tissues and possesses a high affinity for biomolecules (1)(2)(3)(4)(5). From this practical significance, we have investigated the protein adsorption behavior not only onto CaHAP but also onto various kinds of synthetic hydroxyapatites (HAPs), such as CaHAP, strontium HAP (SrHAP), calcium strontium HAP (CaSrHAP), and carbonate-containing CaHAP (CAP) (6 -12). We established in these studies that the saturated amount of adsorbed bovine serum albumin (BSA), n s , depends on the molar ratio of cation (Ca, Sr, and/or Ca ϩ Sr) to phosphorus in the HAPs. Furthermore, the significance of positively charged adsorption sites on the exposed ac or bc crystal faces (called C-sites) for determining the n s of BSA has been addressed in our previous communications (8,9). On the other hand, we recently found that the n s values of lysozyme (LSZ) on CaHAP, SrHAP, and CaSrHAP particles are appreciably smaller than those of BSA and n s depends on neither the cation/P molar ratio nor the number of C-sites of the particles (11). In addition to the adsorption behavior of proteins onto these hydrophilic CaHAP surfaces, the effects of the hydrophobic moiety of CaHAP on the protein adsorption behavior have attracted a great deal of attention. Actually, in protein adsorption studies adsorbent surface properties such as hydrophobicity and electric charge density as well as environmental conditions such as pH, temperature, and ionic strength are often taken as experimental variables. At present, it is widely accepted that the protein adsorption is enhanced by increasing hydrophobicity of the adsorbent surface because many proteins possess hydrophobic parts on their surfaces (13). The higher affinity of proteins for hydrophobic surfaces than hydrophilic surfaces has been reported for adsorption of BSA and LSZ onto polystyrene latex and hematite (14), human serum albumin onto silicon wafers (15), BSA onto silica gel (16), human fibrinogen onto polyethylene foil and glass plate (17), and BSA onto glass plate (18).

To our knowledge, however, no study has been done for the adsorption of proteins onto hydrophobic CaHAP particles. If we can control the hydrophobicity of the CaHAP particle surface, corresponding to the regulation of the protein adsorption affinity of CaHAP, it will become an important technique for applying CaHAP to the purification, identification, fixation, and separation of proteins. Recently, we could control the hydrophobicity of the CaHAP particle surface by grafting various numbers of oleyl phosphate (OP) from 0 to 2.60 groups per nm 2 (n O ) onto the particle surface (12). This OP-grafted CaHAP particle seems to be adequate for understanding the role of the hydrophobic moiety of the CaHAP surface in the protein adsorption behavior.

Eight kinds of colloidal CaHAPs with different numbers of surface oleyl groups were used (Table 1). These particles were produced in our previous study (12), and were synthesized from a coprecipitation reaction of Ca(OH) 2 and H 3 PO 4 with different amounts of disodium oleyl phosphate (DSOP) in water-ethanol mixtures. A solution containing 0.04 mol of Ca(OH) 2 was prepared in a 5.0-dm 3 screw-capped Nalgene polypropylene bottle by dissolving, with stirring, 3 g of Ca(OH) 2 in 2.0 dm 3 of deionized and distilled water free from CO 2 under an N 2 atmosphere. To the Ca(OH) 2 solution a waterethanol solution of DSOP and 2.4 ϫ 10 Ϫ2 mol of H 3 PO 4 was added immediately at room temperature. The details of the preparation and properties of OP-grafted CaHAP particles were reported in our previous paper (12). Some properties of the OP-grafted CaHAP particles are listed in Table 1. It should be mentioned that the number of oleyl groups per nm 2 of particle surface (n O ) is widely varied from 0 to 2.60. After OP grafting, the CaHAP particles are hydrophobic, rather than hydrophilic, in nature and tend to disperse in a cyclohexane phase rather than a water phase at n O Ն 2.0. BSA and LSZ, supplied by Sigma Co., were used as proteins. The isoelectric points of BSA and LSZ are 4.7 and 11.1, respectively.

The conventional adsorption experiment was carried out in 10-cm 3 Nalgene polypropylene centrifugation tubes in which varying concentrations of protein solutions in a 1 ϫ 10 Ϫ4 mol dm Ϫ3 KCl solution of pH 6.0 were added to disperse the OP-grafted CaHAPs (150 mg) as described elsewhere (6). The initial concentrations of BSA and LSZ were 0 -10 and 0 -2 mg cm Ϫ3 , respectively. The polypropylene centrifugation tubes were gently rotated at 15°C for 48 h in a thermostat. The concentration of proteins in the supernatant after centrifugation was determined by a microbiuret method using an ultraviolet absorption band at 310 nm. The electrophoretic mobility (em) of the protein-covered OP-grafted CaHAP particles was measured by using an electrophoresis apparatus as reported before (6).

The change of em of OP-grafted CaHAP particles with pH is displayed in Fig. 1. All the particles show negative em, with the absolute value of em increasing with increasing solution pH, as observed for metal oxides, proving that OH Ϫ and H ϩ ions are potential-determining ions and that the surface P-OH groups (confirmed by FT-IR measurements ( 12)) act as surface charge sites. Since the oleyl group has a long alkyl chain, it is expected that the absolute value of em is decreased with grafting OP groups on the particle surface by shifting of the slipping plane. However, the negative em values increase with increase in n O . This increase of the negative em values by OP grafting on the CaHAP particles would be due to the -electrons in the C|C bonds of the oleyl groups, which act as Lewis acid sites (19).

Figure 2 displays isotherms for adsorption of BSA onto OP-grafted CaHAP particles and their mobilities. The isotherms for adsorption of BSA onto these particles are of the pseudo-Langmuir type, as we have already reported (6 -12). However, the affinity of BSA for adsorption onto OP-grafted CaHAP particles strongly depends on n O . The isotherms for adsorption of BSA onto the OP-grafted CaHAP particles steeply increased in the lower concentration region and the plateau amounts of adsorbed BSA (n s ), corresponding to the saturated amounts of adsorbed BSA, increase up to n O ϭ 0.6. On the other hand, both the initial slope and n s value diminish at n O Ն 1.3. All of the em values of the OP-grafted CaHAP particles shifted strongly to the negative side as the amount of adsorbed BSA increased, and finally they were saturated. This negative shift of em values corresponds to the adsorption isotherms of negatively charged BSA. The isotherms for adsorption of LSZ onto OP-grafted CaHAP particles and their mobilities are shown in Fig. 3. Unlike the BSA system, both the initial slope of the isotherms and the n s values of the OP-grafted CaHAP particles increase with increase in n O . In this system, the negative em values were reversed to positive ones by adsorption of positively charged LSZ, which corresponds to the adsorption isotherms of LSZ as well as the BSA system shown in Fig. 2.

To evaluate the effect of hydrophobicity of CaHAP particles, we plotted n s  In the case of BSA, the hydrophobic interaction between the hydrophobic parts of the proteins and the oleyl groups on the CaHAP may enhance the accumulation of proteins on the particle surface to increase n s . However, since the negative charge of OP-grafted CaHAP particles is increased with increase in n O as was shown in Fig. 1, repulsion forces between negatively charged BSA molecules and OP-grafted CaHAP particles would be increased with increase in n O . Therefore, n s decreased at n O Ն 1.3. On the contrary, LSZ molecules are positively charged at pH 6. Therefore, besides the increase in the hydrophobic interaction, an enhancement of the electrostatic attractive force between LSZ and OP-grafted CaHAP particles with increase in n O appears to play a role in raising the n s .

We have found previously the significance of positively charged adsorption sites (C-sites) on the exposed ac or bc crystal faces for determining the n s of BSA (8 -10). Table 1 shows that the long-axis length of OP-grafted CaHAP particles increases from 36 to 115 nm with increase in n O . We already reported that the large rodlike CaHAP particle is advantageous for the adsorption of negatively charged BSA, because the larger particles exhibit a greater fraction of C-sites on predominant crystal faces (ac or bc). To gain information on the effects of C-sites of the OP-grafted CaHAP particles on the BSA adsorption, we plotted n s values of BSA as a function of the long-axis length of OP-grafted CaHAP particles (Fig. 5). Unfortunately, no clear relationship can be found in the figure. This result substantiated that OP groups grafted on the surfaces of CaHAP particles screen the C-sites.

c d Data from CHN elemental analysis.</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Arch. Biochem. Biophys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Tiselius</author>
				<author>H Hjerten</author>
				<author>O Levin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1956</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Hjerten</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1959</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochem. Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Kawasaki</author>
				<author>M Niikura</author>
				<author>S Takahashi</author>
				<author>W Kobayashi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1986</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Eur. J. Biochem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Kawasaki</author>
				<author>K Ikeda</author>
				<author>S Takahashi</author>
				<author>Y Kuboki</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1986</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Eur. J. Biochem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Kawasaki</author>
				<author>W Kobayashi</author>
				<author>K Ikeda</author>
				<author>S Takahashi</author>
				<author>H Honma</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1986</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids Surf</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Kandori</author>
				<author>S Sawai</author>
				<author>Y Yamamoto</author>
				<author>H Saito</author>
				<author>T Ishikawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids Surf. A</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Kandori</author>
				<author>Y Yamamoto</author>
				<author>H Saito</author>
				<author>T Ishikawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1993</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids Surf. A</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Kandori</author>
				<author>M Saito</author>
				<author>H Saito</author>
				<author>A Yasukawa</author>
				<author>T Ishikawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1995</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Kandori</author>
				<author>M Saito</author>
				<author>T Takebe</author>
				<author>A Yasukawa</author>
				<author>T Ishikawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1995</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids Surf. B</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Kandori</author>
				<author>T Shimizu</author>
				<author>A Yasukawa</author>
				<author>T Ishikawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1995</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Kandori</author>
				<author>N Horigami</author>
				<author>H Kobayashi</author>
				<author>A Yasukawa</author>
				<author>T Ishikawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids Surf. B</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Kandori</author>
				<author>A Fujiwara</author>
				<author>A Yasukawa</author>
				<author>T Ishikawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>The Hydrophobic Effect</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Tanford</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1980</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids Surf</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Arai</author>
				<author>W Norde</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1990</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adhesion and Adsorption of Polymers</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Grant</author>
				<author>R Dehl</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1979</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Macritchie</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1972</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Biomed. Mater. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Brynda</author>
				<author>N Cepalova</author>
				<author>M Stol</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1984</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Pharm. Bull</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Mizutani</author>
				<author>A Asaoka</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1984</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Organic Chemistry</title>
			<authors/>
			<date>1970</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title/>
			<authors>
				<author>Kazuhiko Kandori</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>School of Chemistry Osaka University of Education Asahigaoka</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Megumi Mukai</author>
				<author>Aya Fujiwara</author>
				<author>Akemi Yasukawa</author>
				<author>Tatsuo Ishikawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title/>
			<authors>
				<author>Kashiwara-Shi</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
	</references>
</document>
