<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Adsorption mechanism of polylysine on hydroxyapatite and its effect on dissolution properties of hydroxyapatite.pdf</file>
	<title>ADSORPTION MECHANISM OF POLYLYSINE ON HYDROXYAPATITE AND ITS EFFECT ON DISSOLUTION PROPERTIES OF HYDROXYAPATITE</title>
	<date>Unknown</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Adsorption mechanism of polylysine on hydroxyapatite and its effect on dissolution properties of hydroxyapatite.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>Hideji Tanaka</author>
		<author>Youko Nuno</author>
		<author>Shigeru Shimomura</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>amounts of poly-L-lysine @Lys) and bromide ion on hydroxyapatite (HAP) from aqueous solutions of poly-L-lysine hydrobromide, and amounts of calcium and phosphate ions liberated concurrently from HAp during the adsorption of pLys were determined at 25&quot;. The pLys was adsorbed on HAp by the mechanism of ion-exchange between its amino groups and calcium ions of HAp. The released amount of calcium ion increased, therefore, with the adsorbed amount of pLys. On the other hand, the released amount of phosphate ion first decreased and then increased after attaining a minimum with the equilibrium concentration of pLys. The analysis using an equilibrium dialysis method revealed that the released phosphate ions were mainly in the bound state to the ammo groups of pLys remaining in the solution, and that the concentrations of calcium and phosphate ions free from both HAp and pLys were restricted by each other under the law of the solubility product of HAp. The first decrease in the released amount of phosphate ion was concluded to be attributed primarily to the increase in the released amount of calcium ion because pLys remaining in the solution was little in this region. When sodium hydroxide was added to the solution, the adsorbed amount of pLys increased and then slightly decreased with the equilibrium pH of the solution due to the increase or decrease of the electrostatic attractive force between the adsorbate and the adsorbent. However, conformational change in pLys around pH 10 seemed to have little effect on the adsorption.</abstract>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>Procedure</heading>
			<text>The adsorption experiment was carried out by suspending HAp (1 g) to aqueous solutions of pLysHBr (5Oml) at 25&quot; for 5 days. After filtration with a Millipore filter with a pore size of 0,l pm, the filtrates were analysed.

The dialysis experiment was carried out as follows: HAp (0.6 g) was suspended in pLysHBr solutions (30ml). A dialysis bag (Visking Company, type 36/32) containing water (20 ml) was immersed in each suspension. After 5 days, the dialysis bags were taken out and the concentrations of the ions in the inner solutions were determined. The suspensions remaining in the vessels were filtered through the Mil~pore filters, and the filtrates were analysed.

The concentration of pLys was determined by fluorometry at 475 nm with excitation at 335 nm, using o-phthalaldehyde and %-mercap-toethanol according to the method of Roth.&quot;

The reaction was performed at pH 9.0 by using sodium dihydrogen phosphate-potassium hydroxide buffer. Hereafter, the concentration of pLys is given in terms of molar&amp;y of the lysine residue of pLys. The concentration of bromide ion was determined by spectrophotometry at 458 nm, using mercuric thiocyanate and ferric nitrate.16*17

The concentrations of calcium and phosphate species in solution were determined by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrometry (ICP-AES) at 393.4 and 214.9 nm, respectively. Working standards were prepared from 1,000 mg/l. standards (Kant0 Chemical Co,) by mixing and diluting them with 1% nitric acid. It was confirmed that pLys up to 5mM does not interfere with the determination. For the determination of phosphate in the solutions inside the dialysis bags, where the phosphate level was very low (around O.Olti) and pLys was absent, spectrometry at 720nm using ammonium molyhdate and stannous chloridei was adopted instead of ICP-AES.

Circular dichroism (CD) spectra of the pLys solutions in the range of 200-250 nm were measured at various pH values on the spectropolarimeter. Solutions of pLys in the three forms (i.e., random coil, a-helix and p-sheet) were prepared according to the method of Greenfield et al.zo~2'</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>(HAP), a basic calcium phosphate which has the chemical formula Ca,0(P04)6(OH)2, is the most stable phase of calcium phosphates under ordinary conditions.',' This has been widely used for chromatographic separations of proteins, nucleic acids, enzymes, and so on, since Tiselius et al. introduced it as a packing material for liquid chromatography in 1950'~.~ Today, many commercial HAp-columns for high performance liquid chromatography are on the market.

In the studies on HApcolumn chromatography, the factors governing interactions between proteins and HAp have been investigated, and some mechanisms, such as specific or nonspecific complex formation between functional groups of protein and calcium or phosphate ions of HAp and as ion-exchange between the groups and the ions, were proposed.4-7 However, detailed mechanism of the adsorption is still unknown because complexity of confor-*Author for correspondence. mation and diversity of side chains of proteins make the elucidation of the mechanism difficult.

On the other hand, HAp is known to dissolve slightly in aqueous media. This behaviour is complicated and, in spite of many studies,&quot;i2 not elucidated entirely, mainly because HAp exists in the form of very small crystallites and its physicochemical properties depend on the surface state.i3 The dissolution properties of HAp seem important in connection with the durability of HAp-columns.

Poly-L-lysine (pLys) is a typical homopolypeptide, the molecular structure of which has been studied extensively. In the present study, the interactions between pLys and HAp are investigated by using an equilibrium dialysis technique. The adsorbed amount of pLys on HAp and the amounts of calcium and phosphate ions liberated from HAp are determined, and the results are discussed taking into account ion-exchange between calcium ions of HAp and amino groups of adsorbed pLys, binding of phosphate ions to the groups of pLys in solution, and the solubility product of HAp.

Hydroxyapatite was synthesized according to the method of Avnimelech et ali4 The calcium~phospho~s ratio was 10.3816, and the point of zero charge (PZC) determined by pH titration was 6.70. The specific surface area determined by the BET procedure at 77 K with nitrogen gas as an adsorbate was 29.Om'jg. Poly-L-lysine hy~obro~de ~LysHBr) was purchased from Sigma Chemical Co., and its viscosity average molecular weight assessed by the supplier was 21,500. The standardization of a stock solution of the pLysHBr was performed by the colloidal titration methodi for amino group of pLys, using a standard solution of potassium polyvinyl sulphate (Wako Pure Chemical Industries, Ltd.) with Toluidine Blue indicator, and by the mercuric thiocyanate methodt6g&quot; for bromide ion. Water was demineralized with a Milli-QSP water purification system (Mi~i~re Co.).

A Nippon Jarrel-Ash ICAP-750N multichannel inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrometer was used, The nebulizer used was a conventional cross-flow type and argon gas flow-rates were 0.5 (carrier), 0.6 (auxiliary) and 16 (coolant) 1 l./min. A Hitachi 330 spectrophotometer, Hitachi 650 spectrofluorometer, Jasco J-600 spectropolarimeter and Horiba F-l 1 pH meter were also used for the analyses described below.

The adsorption experiment was carried out by suspending HAp (1 g) to aqueous solutions of pLysHBr (5Oml) at 25&quot; for 5 days. After filtration with a Millipore filter with a pore size of 0,l pm, the filtrates were analysed.

The dialysis experiment was carried out as follows: HAp (0.6 g) was suspended in pLysHBr solutions (30ml). A dialysis bag (Visking Company, type 36/32) containing water (20 ml) was immersed in each suspension. After 5 days, the dialysis bags were taken out and the concentrations of the ions in the inner solutions were determined. The suspensions remaining in the vessels were filtered through the Mil~pore filters, and the filtrates were analysed.

The concentration of pLys was determined by fluorometry at 475 nm with excitation at 335 nm, using o-phthalaldehyde and %-mercap-toethanol according to the method of Roth.&quot;

The reaction was performed at pH 9.0 by using sodium dihydrogen phosphate-potassium hydroxide buffer. Hereafter, the concentration of pLys is given in terms of molar&amp;y of the lysine residue of pLys. The concentration of bromide ion was determined by spectrophotometry at 458 nm, using mercuric thiocyanate and ferric nitrate.16*17

The concentrations of calcium and phosphate species in solution were determined by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrometry (ICP-AES) at 393.4 and 214.9 nm, respectively. Working standards were prepared from 1,000 mg/l. standards (Kant0 Chemical Co,) by mixing and diluting them with 1% nitric acid. It was confirmed that pLys up to 5mM does not interfere with the determination. For the determination of phosphate in the solutions inside the dialysis bags, where the phosphate level was very low (around O.Olti) and pLys was absent, spectrometry at 720nm using ammonium molyhdate and stannous chloridei was adopted instead of ICP-AES.

Circular dichroism (CD) spectra of the pLys solutions in the range of 200-250 nm were measured at various pH values on the spectropolarimeter. Solutions of pLys in the three forms (i.e., random coil, a-helix and p-sheet) were prepared according to the method of Greenfield et al.zo~2'

The adsorbed amounts of pLys and bromide ion (Ply and X,,) on HAp from aqueous solutions of pLysHBr are shown in Fig. 1 as a function of the equilibrium concentration of pLys (C,,,,), where both amounts increased with c p~ys9 and JGL, was larger than Xa,.

It was found that calcium and phosphate ions were released from HAp incon~ently (nonconstant in the ~lc~~~phospho~s ratio) during the adsorption of pLys on HAp. The equilibrium concentrations of calcium and phosphate ions in the solutions were plotted against C,,, in Fig. 2(a). The equilibrium con~nt~tion of calcium ion (C,) increased and that of phosphate ion (Cn) decreased with c pLY,. However, the latter increased after attaining a minimum when C,,, became high. equilibrium pH of the solutions and CPLYS, where the pH had the similar tendency to C,.

From the outer suspension in contact with the dialysis bag containing water, some of the bromide ions (added as pLysHBr) and some of the calcium and phosphate ions (released from HAp) migrated into the inside of the bag to reach membrane equilibrium. The equilibrium values of the dialysis experiment are listed in Table I; initial concentration of pLys was 2.31 (A) or 3.08 mM (B). The concentrations of anionic species in the outer solution were  higher than those in the inner solution, whereas the concentration of calcium ion in the outer solution were lower than that in the inner solution. Equilibrium pH of the outer solution was higher than that of the inner solution. In aqueous solution of calcium phosphates, the chemical species of Ca2+, PO:-, HPa-, H,PO;, H3P04, CaHPO, and CaH,PO,+ are formed through protonation of phosphate ion and through complex formation between calcium and phosphate ions.23 Moreover, in the presence of pLys, a part of anionic species of phosphate is considered to be bound to amino groups of pLys. The concentration of calcium species determined by the ICP-AES is, therefore, the sum of the concentrations of Ca2+, CaHPO, and CaH,PO: ; the concentration of phosphate species determined simultaneously is the sum of the concentrations of PO:-, HPO:-, H,PO;, H3P04, CaHPO,, CaH,PO: and phosphate which is bound to pLys in solution.

The concentrations and activities of chemical species in the solutions inside the dialysis bags can be calculated from the data shown in Table 1 using the first, second and third dissociation constants of phosphoric acid (K,, K2 and 4, respectively) and the formation constants of CaHPO, and CaH,PO:

(K, and KY, respectively).24 The obtained values were listed in the middle part of Table 2, where brackets and parentheses mean concentration and activity, respectively. The numerical values used were as follows: K, 7.08 x 10-3, K2 6.31 x lo-*, K3 4.17 x 10-'3,25 K, 244 and KY 8.20.24 The activity coefficient for each ion (y) was calculated through the Debye-Hiickel equation;

where z is the valency of the ion, Z is the ionic strength of the medium, A and B are constants  trations of calcium and phosphate ions in the inner solutions were limited by each other under the law of the &amp; of HAp. When membrane equilibrium is attained, the Kw of HAp are equal on both sides of the membrane, under the assumption that the standard chemical potential of HAp on both sides of the membrane are the same. Therefore, even in the outer solutions containing pLys, the activities of calcium and phosphate ions were mutually restricted under the law of the Kw of HAp. It was concluded that the released phosphate ions in the outer solution exist mainly in the bound state to the amino groups of pLys in the solution. On the other hand, adsorbed pLys expels calcium ion from HAp through the ionexchange between positively charged amino groups of pLys and calcium ions of HAp to keep electroneutrality of the surface phase. The concomitant increase of C, and C, shown in Fig. 2(A) were attributed to these facts. The tendency of CR to decrease with an increase in C, was observed only in the region of low CpLys, where the amount of phosphate ions which were bound to pLys in the solution phase was little.

Taking the Donnan's membrane equilibrium into account, the concentrations of anions, i.e., phosphate and bromide ions, free from both pLys and HAp in the outer solution ([Pi]; and [Br-1:) can be evaluated from the following equations;

where the subscript &quot;f&quot; means &quot;free&quot;, and the superscripts &quot;i&quot; and &quot;0&quot; mean &quot;inside&quot; and &quot;outside&quot;, respectively. It was assumed that the activity coefficients for uni-and bivalent ions and the concentrations of neutral species, i.e., H3P04 and CaHPO,, were equal on both sides of the dialysis membrane, and that the cationic species did not interact with pLys. Accordingly, the concentrations of phosphate and bromide ions which were bound to pLys in the outer solution are obtained; The calculated values were listed in the bottom part of Table 2. It shows that phosphate ions in the outer solution exist mostly in the bound state as presumed above. When the solution pH becomes higher than the PZC of HAp (6.7), the electrostatic attraction between the cationic pLys and the negatively charged HAp surface increases. Thus, x,,, increased with the pH. However, when the pH further increases, pLys comes to lose its positive charges and the conformational change between random coil (at lower pH) and a-helix (at higher pH) occurs in pLys. The dotted line in Fig. 3(A) shows the helix content, estimated from the CD-spectra of the pLys solutions according to the procedure of Greenfield et al.*' It shows that the helix content increased sharply in the range of pH 9-l 1. However, no pronounced change in XpLYs was observed in this region. It was concluded, therefore, that the conformational change of pLys in this region does not give a significant effect on the adsorption of pLys.

In general, as for the adsorption of highly solvated polymers on an impenetrable surface, a fraction of the molecules is actually attached to the sorbent surface, and the remainder dangles in solution.29 Therefore, the following model explaining the phenomena found in the present study was considered as shown in Fig. 4. A fraction of adsorbed pLys which was actually attached to HAp (c) released calcium ions from HAp (d) by the mechanism of ion-exchange. Co-adsorbed bromide ions were captured by the amino groups of the remaining fraction of adsorbed pLys (b), because the affinity of bromide ion to HAp is very low.'O In addition to the ion-exchange mechanism, calcium ions were released from HAp through the dissolution of HAp (e). On the other hand, phosphate ions were released only through the dissolution (e). Most of these phosphate ions protonated (g) and/or were bound to pLys in the solution phase (i). Some released phosphate ions formed complexes with calcium ions (h). The dissolution of HAp and the protonation of phosphate ions (g) increased the concentration of hydroxide ion in solution (e) and (f). The similar tendency between the shape of curves of C, and (pH) in   -were limited by each other under the restriction of the K, of HAp (enclosed with the dotted line). Therefore, the release of phosphate ions through the dissolution of HAp (e) was suppressed by the excess release of calcium ions through the ionexchange (d) when the equilibrium concentration of pLys in solution was low. These facts were responsible for the marked incongruent dissolution properties of HAp in the presence of PLYs* It is known that the constituent ions of HAp having the same sign of electric charge as that of the adsorbed polymeric ions are released from HAp during their adsorption.3'g32 On the other hand, little attention is paid to the behaviour of the constituent ions having a counter-charge to the adsorbate. One of the exceptions is a report of Juriaanse et ~1.~~ They found that not only calcium ions but also phosphate ions were released from HAp in the presence of pLys and poly+ornithine; not only phosphate ions but also calcium ions were released in the presence of poly+asparaginate. Although they did not refer to it, initial decrease in the released amount of the counter-charge ions, such as that shown in Fig. 2(a), was seen in their reported data. These facts suggest that the dissolution tendency of HAp found in the present study is not specific for the case of adsorption of pLys but is common to those of other cationic peptides, and that the behaviour of phosphate and calcium ions changed place with each other according to the sign of the electric charge of the adsorbed polymeric ions. The results obtained in the present study are, therefore, important as a basis for understanding the interaction between charged polymers and HAp.</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Phys. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Feenstra</author>
				<author>P De Bruyn</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1979</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Van Kemenade</author>
				<author>P De Bruyn</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1987</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Arch. Biochem. Biophys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Tiselius</author>
				<author>S Hjertim</author>
				<author>Levitt</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1956</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Anal. Biochem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Gorbunoff</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1986</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title/>
			<authors>
				<author>I&amp;m</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1986</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Chromatographic Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Makino</author>
				<author>B Kim</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Phys. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Levinskas</author>
				<author>W Neuman</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1955</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Rootare</author>
				<author>V Deitz</author>
				<author>F Carpenter</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1964</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title/>
			<authors>
				<author>V Deitz</author>
				<author>H Rootare</author>
				<author>F Carpenter</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1964</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Smith</author>
				<author>A Posner</author>
				<author>J Quirk</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1974</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Cal&amp; Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Kaufman</author>
				<author>I Kleinberg</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1979</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Chander</author>
				<author>D Fuerstenau</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1979</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Res. Nat. Eur. Stand., Sect. A</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Avnimelech</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>W Brown</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1973</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Koroido Tekitei-hou (Colloidal Titration Method)</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Senju</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1976</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nippon Kagaku Zasshi</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Tomonari</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1952</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Anal. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Roth</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1973</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title/>
			<authors>
				<author>A Gee</author>
				<author>L Domingues</author>
				<author>V Deitz</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1954</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochemistry</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Greenfield</author>
				<author>B Davidson</author>
				<author>G Fasman</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title/>
			<authors>
				<author>N Greenfield</author>
				<author>G Fasman</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1969</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Pharm. Bull</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Tanaka</author>
				<author>K Miyajima</author>
				<author>M Nakagaki</author>
				<author>S Shimabayashi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1989</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Phys. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Chugtai</author>
				<author>R Marshall</author>
				<author>G Nancollas</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1968</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Res. Nat. Eur. Stand., Sect A</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>T Gregory</author>
				<author>W Brown</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1968</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Electrolyte Solutions</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Robinson</author>
				<author>R Stokes</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1968</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Am. Chem. Sot</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Kielland</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1937</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adsorption on and Surface Chemistry of Hydroxyapatite</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Chander</author>
				<author>D Fuerstenau</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1984</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>AL. Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Norde</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1986</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Pharm. Bull</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Shimabayashi</author>
				<author>H Tanaka</author>
				<author>M Nakagaki</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1987</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Garbacia-Ramos</author>
				<author>P Carmona</author>
				<author>A Hidalgo</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1981</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adsorption on and Surface Chemistry of Hydroxyapatite</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Rawls</author>
				<author>I Cabasso</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1984</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Juriaanse</author>
				<author>J Arends</author>
				<author>J Bosch</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1980</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
</document>
