<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Adsorptive Properties of Cu(II) on CaHPO4·2H2O and MgHPO4·3H2O Powders in Aqueous Solutions.pdf</file>
	<title>Ca艶) 2CuHPO4十Cu諸+十2Cr-→Cu3(PO4)2十2H幸 十2Cr(2)</title>
	<date>Unknown</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Adsorptive Properties of Cu(II) on CaHPO4·2H2O and MgHPO4·3H2O Powders in Aqueous Solutions.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors/>
	<abstract/>
	<methods/>
	<full_text>1) T. Maki, M. Ohkubo, Bull. Inst. Chem. Res., Kyoto Univ., 51, 278 (1973) .

2)遠 山 一 郎,中 村 富 三,小 松 宏 二s水 処 理 嫁 術,14,11 〈1973&gt; ;15, 29(1974&gt;.

的 研 究 は ア パ タ イ ト(Calo(Pq)6×2,X;F,CI,OH)を

3) D. Grisafe, F. Hummel, Amer. Mineral., 55, 1131 (1970). 4) T.Shigematsu, 0.Fujino, M.Matsui, Bull. Inst. Chem.

Res., Kyoto Univ., 50, 645(1972). 8) V. Wazer, &quot;Phosphorus &amp; its Compounds&quot;, Vol.1 (Chemistry), Interscience (1958)D. 510. 9) R. Legeros, J. Legeros, I. Cryst. Growth, 13/14 , 470 (1972). •=CompactscomposedofCaHPO4・2H20 ×=X'enotlite(Firedat600℃)1) ○:Ion-exchangeresin(AmberliteIR-120) •:CaHPOぺ2H皇0,0:MgHPO4・3H20,

andarnounts◎fpowdersamples.

P◎wdersampleswereimmersedin100ml◎fcopper 〈皿)chloridesoluti◎Rsc◎ntaining2500PPmofCu

(皿)f◎r48hrs.

•:CaHPO4・2H20,0:MgHPOs・3H20,    ピ ー クはCuHPO4・H20(こ のd値 はA.S.T.M.カ ー ド12-520

ExchangeandSolventExtraction',,VoL5,J.Marinsky &amp;Y,MarcusEditors,Dekker(1973

(2)+(5)  Nucl. Chem., 35, 1327(1973) . 16) G. Alberti, U. Costantino, S. Allulli, M. Massucci, ibid., 35, 1339Massucci, ibid., 35, (1973) ) . Powders of commercially available calcium hydrogenphosphate dihydra.te (CaHPQ4.2 H20) or magnesium hydrogenphosphate trihydrate (MgHPO4'3 H20) (composed of particles ranging 1-100 ,u in diameter) were immersed in copper (II ) sulfate or copper ( IC) chloride solutions con taining 100-2500 ppm of Cu (II) for 0-48 hrs at room temperature and adsorption ability and mechanism of Cu (II ) were investigated by measuring amounts of Cu ( II ) , Ca ( II) or Mg ( if) and P (V) in the residual solutions and by analysing X-ray diffraction patterns of the powders before and after adsorption. The results were as follows :

1) Although the powders dissolved a little into solution, the adsorption progressed with processes, in which the powders changed to Cu ( ) containing insoluble phosphates in the • solution of pH range 3 . 0-7. 0.

2) When they were immersed in the solutions containing 1500 or 2500 ppm of Cu ( II ) , their uptakes of Cu (Tr) were fairly larger than those of other phosphates and commercial adsorbents, and their values both amounted to about 7. 0 meq Cu/g.

3) The adsorption mechanism of the powders immersed into the copper ( 10 chloride solutions was explained with following formulas.</full_text>
	<references/>
</document>
