<document>
  <file>./pdf-files/Advanced Therapeutics - 2025 - Choe - Hydroxyapatite Binding Peptide Lipid Nanoparticles for Biomimetic mRNA Delivery to.pdf</file>
  <title>Hydroxyapatite Binding Peptide Lipid Nanoparticles for Biomimetic mRNA Delivery to Bone</title>
  <date>2025-04-17</date>
  <authors>
    <author>Joshua Choe</author>
    <author>Jena Moseman</author>
    <author>Jamie Jones</author>
    <author>Jacobus Burger</author>
    <author>Ashley Weichmann</author>
    <author>Douglas Mcneel</author>
    <author>William Murphy</author>
  </authors>
  <abstract>Development of strategies for non-viral gene delivery targeted to bone can be used for bone pathologies. Applications include rheumatologic disease, metastatic disease to the bone, pathologies with deficits in hematopoiesis, osteomyelitis, and regenerative medicine. However, specific delivery to tissues like bone is challenging. Here mRNA LNPs (lipid nanoparticles) decorated with a biomimetic hydroxyapatite-binding peptide (HABP-LNP) are described, which show improved binding to bone minerals compared to sham peptide conjugated mRNA LNPs (Sham-LNP). The HABP-LNPs also increase transfection when associated with bone mineral. Furthermore, HABP mRNA LNPs improve intraosseous transfection and reduce hepatic uptake in vivo. The continued development of these mRNA LNPs can result in non-viral therapies for bone pathologies.</abstract>
  <methods>
    <method>Experimental Section: Lipid Nanoparticle (LNP) Preparation: Figure 6 is a schematic outlining LNP preparation. Lipids were dissolved in ethanol and stored in glass vials at -20 °C. Lipid nanoparticles were prepared by mixing a molar ratio of 50:38.5:10:1.5 of ionizable lipid:cholesterol:1,2-DSPC:PEG lipid at 5 mm in ethanol. Lipid nanoparticles were formed by rapidly mixing the lipid-ethanol formulation, as described above, with mRNA in citric acid buffer (100 mm, pH 4) at a ratio of 1:3 by volume. LNPs were dialyzed (10K MWCO, Pur-A-Lyzer Midi, Sigma-Aldrich, Burlington, Massachusetts, USA) for 2 h into PBS prior to further use. To visualize mineral binding or quantify LNP binding 0.1% by molar weight of lipid label (DiO: 3,3′-Dioctadecyloxacarbocyanine Perchlorate, DiD: 1,1′-Dioctadecyl-3,3,3′,3′-Tetramethylindodicarbocyanine, 4-Chlorobenzenesulfonate Salt, DIR: 1,1′dioctadecyl-3,3,3′,3′-tetramethylindotricarbocyanine iodide, Thermofisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) were added prior to mixing (Figure 6). DIR was used as near-infrared lipid lael for in vivo studies.

For peptide conjugation, LNPs were synthesized as described above with 0.15-1.2% of the total lipid consisting of DSPE-PEG-Maleimide. DSPE-PEG-2000-Maleimide served as a substitute for DMG-PEG-2000. For peptide conjugation by thiol Michael addition, HABP or sham peptide were incubated with LNPs at 10-times molar excess of peptide: DSPE-PEG-Maleimide overnight at 4 °C. Peptide functionalized LNPs were then washed to remove residual peptide and LNPs were concentrated two times using ultracentrifugation (Amicon Ultra 10KDA MWCO, Sigma Aldrich, Burlington, Massachusetts, USA). pK a Determination: Lipid nanoparticle pK a was determined by 6-(p-Toluidino)-2-naphthalenesulfonic acid (TNS) assay as previously described. [55] The base buffer consisted of 20 mm sodium phosphate, 25 mm citrate, 20 mm ammonium acetate, and 150 mm NaCl. Buffers were adjusted with 0.1N of NaOH or HCl from pH 4-10. 100 μl of buffer at each pH was added to a black 96 well plate and TNS (6 μm final) and LNPs (25 μm final) were added to the plate. Fluorescence measurements were obtained using a plate reader at 325/435 nm excitation/emission. These fluorescence measurements were normalized to the minimum value and fit to give a titration curve. pK a was evaluated by determining the pH representing 50% of the maximum fluorescence. Statistical differences between curves were determined using Student's t-test in Prism software.

Encapsulation Efficiency: mRNA encapsulation efficiency was determined by incubating mRNA LNPs with a nucleic acid-binding fluorophore (Ribogreen Reagent, Thermofisher Scientific, Waltham, Massachusetts, USA). mRNA encapsulation efficiency was determined by comparing the input mRNA mass of mRNA LNPs against the measured concentration of free mRNA as determined with a standard curve of free mRNA.

Dynamic Light Scattering and Zeta Potential: The size and charge of mRNA LNPs were determined using dynamic light scattering and zeta potential analysis using a Zetasizer (Malvern Panalytical, Malvern, UK). mRNA LNPs were prepared at a concentration of 0.1 mg mL -1 by mass of total lipid in PBS.

Cell Culture and Transfection: hMSCs (Passage 3-6, Lonza, Basel, CH) were grown in 10% FBS/1% penicillin/streptomycin alpha minimum essential medium (Corning, NY, USA). Media was changed every three days and cells were grown to 80-90% confluence prior to transfection. To determine the expression of firefly luciferase mRNA, cells were lysed after 24 h transfection. Cells were washed with PBS prior to the addition of Cell Culture Lysis Reagent (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). 20 μL of lysates were mixed with 100 μL of stock luciferase assay buffer (50 mm Tris, 10 mm MgSO 4 , 6 mm cysteine, 0.02 mm sodium pyrophosphate, 1 mM EDTA, and 2g L -1 BSA). Working buffer was made prior to the assay by mixing the buffer with 0.15 mg mL -1 D-Luciferin and 1 mm ATP. Samples were read on a plate reader (Synergy HTX, Biotek, Winooski, VT, USA).

Mineral Binding Experiments: To assess binding and transfection of mRNA LNPs in the presence of mineral, Sham-LNP or HABP-LNPs were mixed with HAp micro powder (size 3-5 μm, Plasma Biotal, Buxton, UK) at a ratio of 25 μg HAp: μg of mRNA for 30 min unless otherwise specified. For quantification of binding DiO labeled mRNA LNPs were incubated with HAp as described above. At each time point, the mixture was centrifuged for 30s at 2000 g and the supernatant was taken off. Binding percentages were determined by comparing the fluorescence of binding supernatant to unbound control mRNA LNPs in a black multi-well plate using a plate reader (Synergy HTX, Biotek, Winooski, VT, USA). To determine binding to bone, DiD-peptide LNPs (5 μg) were incubated with cancellous cortical chips (4-6 mm, Regeneration Technologies inc., Alachua, FL, USA) for 1 h and then imaged. All imaging was performed using a fluorescent microscope with FITC,Cy5 filter cubes (Nikon Ti-Eclipse, Nikon, Toyko, Japan). The optimal formulation of HABP-LNPs incorporated 0.3% DSPE-PEG-Maleimide and was used unless otherwise specified in screening studies.

In Vivo Experiments: DiR labeled mRNA LNPs were prepared as described above. C57BL/6 mice were obtained from Jackson Laboratory (Bar Harbor, ME, USA). Mice were housed and monitored in the Wisconsin Institute for Medical Research vivarium and experiments were conducted under a University of Wisconsin-Madison Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) approved protocol. Animals were injected with control, HABP-or Sham-LNPs at 0.5 mg kg -1 mRNA with 3:1 eGFP: Firefly Luciferase mRNA. 24 h after transfection mice were injected with 150 mg kg -1 of D-Luciferin and imaged after 15 min. Mice were then sacrificed, blood was collected, and organs were harvested and imaged for fluorescence and luminescence. Organs were kept moist in PBS in multi-well plates. Serum was isolated from blood and liver function tests (LFTs) were performed. These included the liver enzymes aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT), alkaline phosphatase (ALP), total bilirubin, albumin, and total protein. LFTs were measured using a veterinary hematology analyzer (Vetscan VS2, Zoetis Diagnostics, Parsippany, NJ, USA).

Histology and Immunofluorescence: Livers and femora were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde. Mouse femurs were decalcified with 20% EDTA for 48 h, washed, and placed in 70% EtOH prior to paraffin embedding and sectioning. Livers and femora were stained using hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E). Immunofluorescence was performed using anti-GFP primary antibody (1:500, Ab290, Abcam, Cambridge, UK) and Alexafluor 488 goat anti-rabbit secondary antibody (1:500, A11034, Invitrogen, Waltham, MA, USA). Embedding, sectioning, and staining were performed by the Translational Research Initiatives in Pathology laboratory at the University of Wisconsin-Madison.

Statistical Analysis and Data Availability: All statistical analyses were conducted using PRISM software (v.10, GraphPad, Boston, MA, USA). Reported data in figures are mean ± standard deviation (SD) unless otherwise specified. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to compare differences between three or more groups with post-hoc testing done by Tukey's Honest Significant Difference test to determine differences between individual groups. Annotations for figures were as follows **** p &lt; 0.0001, *** p &lt; 0.001, ** p &lt; 0.01 * p &lt; 0.05; n.s: no significance, unless otherwise specified. N = 3 replicates were performed for each experiment unless otherwise stated. The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.</method>
  </methods>
  <full_text>Messenger RNA (mRNA) lipid nanoparticles (LNP) are widely used for vaccination against COVID-19 via local intramuscular injection. However, tissue-specific targeting is still a challenge, DOI: 10.1002/adtp.202400505 as most nanoparticles traffic to the liver. [1] Next generation LNPs have incorporated charged lipids to promote improved extra-hepatic trafficking to the lungs or spleen. [2][3][4][5] However, tissue-specific targeting of peripheral tissues, including bone, requires new approaches to allow for LNPs to bypass major organs in circulation, including the liver, lung, heart, spleen, and kidneys.

Bone is a vital organ of the body that provides structural support, protects central organs, facilitates movement, acts as a reservoir for minerals, and is the origin of hematopoietic cells. [6] Unlike most organs, bone is widespread throughout the body, and bone-related diseases including osteoporosis, osteoarthritis, and metastatic bone disease often occur in multiple skeletal sites. [7] Therapeutic strategies developed to target bone diseases include bisphosphonates, tetracyclines, and mineral binding peptides. [8][9][10][11][12][13] Tetracycline use has been limited by disruptions of the gut microbiome, poor stability, and side effects including hyperpigmentation and aberrant skeletal development. [14] Recently, bisphosphonate-conjugated mRNA LNPs have been shown to improve mRNA delivery to bone. [15] Bisphosphonates include functional groups that inhibit osteoclast activity to prevent bone resorption. [16] However, bisphosphonates can cause severe side effects, including osteonecrosis of the jaw, atypical femoral fractures, and musculoskeletal pain. [12,13,17,18] In addition, bisphosphonates are only liberated from bone after the bone is resorbed, meaning bisphosphonates can be retained for several years in vivo. [19] Mineral binding peptides have been derived from natural proteins or discovered by synthetic means, including phage display. Peptides derived from non-collagenous bone proteins include statherin, [20,21] osteopontin, [22] osteonectin, [23] and osteocalcin, [24] among others. However, many of these proteins play an important biological role in cell adhesion, and cell signaling, or influence the growth of hydroxyapatite crystals. [20][21][22]25,26] Similarly, synthetic peptides are often highly analogous to natural peptides and may have similar biological effects. [27] Some synthetic acidic oligopeptides, consisting of repeating Asp or Glu residues, bind calcium-based surfaces but lack specificity for the bone mineral hydroxyapatite. [28] On the other hand, osteocalcin, one of the primary non-collagenous bone matrix proteins, has limited biological activity and binds bone minerals with high affinity. [24]  Osteocalcin contains three 𝛾-carboxyglutamic acid residues that form an alpha helix in the N-terminal region when it is adsorbed to the bone mineral hydroxyapatite (HAp). [24] Unlike bisphosphonates, osteocalcin's N-terminus does not regulate cell signaling during bone formation or resorption. [29][30][31][32][33] Instead, osteocalcin is important in the alignment of bone mineral crystals. [29][30][31][32][33] Therefore, osteocalcin's high affinity for bone, without a known mechanism of action for off-target effects, makes it an attractive biomimetic inspiration to develop targeting ligands for therapeutic delivery.

Conjugation of targeting peptides to mRNA LNPs can improve tissue-specific delivery in vivo. For example, click chemistry has been recently used to create a modular, peptide-conjugated mRNA LNP to target photoreceptors of the retina. [34] Similarly, here we hypothesized that conjugation of an osteocalcin-inspired hydroxyapatite binding peptide (HABP) to a mRNA LNP may improve tissue-specific targeting to bone.

Here we describe a modular, HAp peptide conjugated LNP that improved mRNA delivery to bone in vitro and in vivo. Functionalization of lipid nanoparticles with a HABP improved binding to HAp particles and cancellous cortical bone chips in vitro. HABP-LNPs that were bound to HAp particles improved the transfection of human mesenchymal stromal cells (hMSC) in vitro. Systemically infused HABP-LNPs in vivo demonstrated improved transfection in the femur and enhanced escape from the liver when compared to LNPs decorated with sham peptides.

HABP-LNPs bind to HA particles and cancellous cortical chips in vitro in a peptide sequence-dependent manner. DiD labeled HABP-LNPs were visualized via fluorescence microscopy and localized to HAp particles. Conversely, Sham-LNPs were rarely detected in association with HAp (Figure 1A,B). Increased binding time resulted in improved binding of HABP-LNPs prepared with 0.3% DSPE-PEG-Maleimide. The binding of the HABP-LNPs to HAp increased to 62.90 ± 2.29% over 120 min while only 18.18 ± 2.75% of Sham-LNPs were bound to HAp (Figure 1C). Similar to HAp binding, HABP-LNPs are also bound to explanted bone mineral in vitro. DiD labeled HABP-LNPs were detected on the surface of cancellous cortical chips in vitro as assessed by fluorescence microscopy, while Sham-LNPs were not apparent on the bone chips (Figure 1D,E).

HABP-LNPs promoted transfection when bound to HAp particles. LNP formulations incorporating varying amounts of DSPE-PEG-Maleimide (0-1.2%) were conjugated with peptide and evaluated. LNPs were then incubated with HAp particles, resus- pended to remove free LNPs, and added to human mesenchymal stromal cells (hMSCs; Figure 2A). HABP-LNPs combined with HAp improved transfection significantly when compared to either free HABP-LNPs, free Sham-LNPs, or Sham-LNPs combined with HAp (Figure 2C). The most effective formulation of HABP-LNPs combined with HAp included 0.3% DSPE-PEG-Maleimide and resulted in significantly higher transfection when compared to all other groups (Figure 2C). hMSCs exposed to comparable Sham-LNPs with 0.3% DSPE-PEG-Maleimide expressed minimal transgene when delivered without HAp particles or combined with HAp particles (Figure 2C). hMSCs demonstrated reduced metabolic activity when exposed to HABP-LNPs combined with HAp microparticles compared to Sham-LNPs but did not show significantly reduced metabolic activity compared to HABP-LNPs alone (Figure 2D). Increased binding time resulted in increased transfection with HABP-LNPs. HABP-LNPs combined with HAp particles significantly increased transfection by over 45-fold after 120 min binding, while Sham-LNPs with HAp only increased by 1.3-fold over the same period (Figure 2E). LNPs without peptide functionalization did not transfect cells appreciably following binding to HAp, as expected (Figure 2B).

Increasing the amount of DSPE-PEG-Maleimide lipid changed the pK a and size of mRNA LNPs. HABP-LNPs formed with 0.3% DSPE-PEG-Maleimide had a significantly higher pK a of 6.16 when compared to the 5.06 pKa of Sham-LNPs (p = 0.010). LNPs with no peptide had a pKa of 5.89, which was not significantly different from the HABP-LNP pKa (p = 0.3; Figure 3A and Table 1). HABP-LNPs tended to have higher pK a than Sham-LNPs for compositions created with between 0-0.9% DSPE-PEG-Maleimide (Figure 3A and Table 1).

HABP-LNPs tended to be more negatively charged than Sham-LNPs (Figure 1B). For example, HABP-LNPs formed with 0.3% DSPE-PEG-Maleimide had significantly less charge (-7.10 ± 0.50, p &lt; 0.001) than the comparable Sham-LNPs (-4.00 ± 0.80; Figure 3B). LNPs without peptide were smaller (148.0 ± 17.1 nm) and less negatively charged (-2.90 ± 4.10 mV) than all peptidefunctionalized LNPs (Figure 3B,C). Increasing the percentage of DSPE-PEG-Maleimide in the LNP formulation tended to increase the size of LNPs (Figure 1C). HABP-LNPs formed with 0.3% DSPE-PEG-Maleimide were significantly smaller (134.50 ± 0.96 nm, p &lt; 0.001) than the comparable Sham-LNPs (195.50 ± 4.00 nm; Figure 3C).

There were no significant differences in mRNA encapsulation efficiency between Sham-LNPs and HABP-LNPs at DSPE-Peg-Maleimide of 0.15-0.9%, and efficiencies were in the 97-99% range (Figure 3D). For example, the 0.3% DSPE-PEG-Maleimide compositions encapsulated mRNA at 99.82 ± 0.14% for Sham-LNPs and 99.52 ± 0.97% for HABP-LNPs (Figure 3D). However, there were significant decreases in encapsulation efficiency at the 1.2% level of DSPE-PEG-Maleimide inclusion for both the Sham-LNPs (90.70% ± 0.51%) and HABP-LNPs (87.40% ± 1.50%, p &lt; 0.0001; Figure 3D).

HABP-LNPs improved liver escape compared to Sham-LNPs after systemic delivery via mouse tail vein injection (Figure 4). This set of experiments used IVIS to evaluate the ex vivo luminescence of firefly luciferase mRNA (to track in vivo transfection) and epifluorescence of the DiR labeled LNPs (to track in vivo LNP localization). Sham-LNPs had significantly more luminescence (3-fold; p = 0.039) and fluorescence (1.6-fold; p = 0.030) in the liver compared to the HABP-LNPs (Figure 4B,C). There were no significant differences in splenic transfection between HABP-LNPs, Sham-LNPs, or LNPs without peptide (Figure 4B,C). There also were no differences in LNP localization measured via epifluorescence between HABP-LNPs, Sham-or LNPs without peptide (Figure 4B,D).

Intraosseous transfection was promoted by HABP-LNPs after systemic delivery via tail vein injection (Figure 5A). Quantifica-tion of immunohistochemical staining for eGFP demonstrated significantly more mean fluorescence intensity (MFI) in the femoral head for HABP-LNPs (Figure 5B, p &lt; 0.01) compared to Sham-LNPs and LNPs without peptide. Similarly, there was significantly higher transfection of eGFP mRNA detected in the femoral shaft for HABP-LNPs (Figure 5B and p = 0.016) compared to Sham-LNPs and LNPs without peptide.

Targeted delivery of non-viral gene therapies to bone is attractive for the potential to treat systemic bone diseases and for regenerative medicine. However, the moieties used in bone targeting strategies to date were often associated with significant side effects. [12,13,17,18] We hypothesized that conjugation of an osteocalcin-inspired HABP to mRNA LNPs would enhance delivery to the bone. Previous work has developed a modular, mineral-binding peptide based on the N-terminal alpha-helix of osteocalcin. [35][36][37] These peptides have been shown to bind to HAp and bone surfaces with high affinity. [35][36][37][38] Together, these approaches form the basis for a modular, bone-targeting mRNA LNP for delivery in systemic circulation. In the current study, Table 1. pK a Measurements of mRNA LNPs. pK a was evaluated by determining the pH representing 50% of the maximum fluorescence using a 6-(p-Toluidino)-2-naphthalenesulfonic acid (TNS) assay. pK a was evaluated for sham peptide and hydroxyapatite binding peptide (HABP) conjugated mRNA LNPs. pK a for control LNP without peptide was 5.89 95% confidence interval (CI) [4.97,6.40]. n = 3 replicates.  a HABP-LNP improved delivery to and transfection of mouse femora after systemic delivery via an intravenous tail vein injection. Additionally, HABP-LNPs reduced mRNA expression in the liver when compared to sham peptide LNPs. Interestingly, the choice of bone targeting ligand may impact the site of localization of the targeting moieties in the bone. Bisphosphonate conjugated mRNA LNPs have been shown to most efficiently transfect the endosteal surface of the bone. [15] However, here with HABP-conjugated LNPs we observed more diffuse eGFP expression throughout the bone matrix, beyond the endosteal surface. Higher affinity bisphosphonates, like the alendronate used to target LNPs, have been shown to have reduced penetration into bone and localize more strongly to resorbing bone surfaces when compared to lower affinity bisphosphonates. [15,39] The high-affinity bisphosphonates alendronate (K d 72 μm) has 120-fold less affinity for bone matrix than osteocalcin (K d 0.6 μm). [40,41] Surprisingly, while the HABP used in the present study has a higher affinity for bone, transfection was seen throughout the mouse femora. [35] Differences in localization may be due, in part, to the conjugation strategy. Previously reported bisphosphonate ligands were linked to the ionizable lipid component of the LNP. [15] This is in contrast to the present approach that conjugated the HABP to a DSPE-PEG lipid (Figure 6). Desorption of PEG has been shown to be important for cellular uptake. [42][43][44] We speculate that anchoring of HABP-LNPs to bone may allow for localized desorption of PEG. This may allow the LNPs to distribute throughout bone, rather than just on the endosteal surface.

HABP-LNPs did not appreciably increase liver function tests (LFTs) compared to control LNPs without peptide and were within reference values for LFTs (Figure S1, Supporting Information). [45] Bisphosphonate conjugated LNPs did not show elevations in the liver enzymes AST and ALT compared to unconjugated controls. [15] Despite similar short-term hepatotoxicity profiles in vivo, the present approach is not burdened with the well-characterized side effects associated with bisphosphonate ligands. Limitations of bisphosphonate ligands include: retention time, toxicity profile, and other systemic effects. Bisphosphonates have been shown to deplete macrophages, reduce hematopoietic stem cell number, and inhibit myeloid differentia-tion of bone marrow cells. [46][47][48][49][50] Bisphosphonates are retained in bone for years and can cause severe clinical side effects such as osteonecrosis of the jaw, nephrotoxicity, hypocalcemia, and ocular dysfunction. [12] Conversely, the HABP used in the present study is a peptide inspired by the N-terminal alpha helix in the bone matrix protein osteocalcin. Osteocalcin can be degraded by osteoclasts and released into the blood, and has a short half-life of 6-8 min, with clearance by the kidneys and liver. [51][52][53] The peptide used in the present study comprises a fragment of osteocalcin, with no expected mechanism of action for direct effects on cell signaling.

HABP-LNPs showed decreased liver uptake compared to Sham-LNPs (Figure 4). Similarly, bone targeting LNPs developed previously using a bisphosphonate-conjugated lipid had less up- take in the liver and more in the spleen. [15] HABP-LNPs were smaller, had a higher pK a , and were more negatively charged than Sham-LNPs (Figure 3). Small, 70-80 nm, LNPs with a pK a between 6-7 have been shown to best transfect the liver. [54][55][56][57] Conversely, we saw that larger Sham-LNPs, 200 nm in size, with a pK a ≈5 best transfected the liver (Figure 3, Table 1). Previously, it has been shown that the tropism of more negatively charged LNPs shifts from the liver to the spleen. [5] Therefore, the relative negative surface charge might best explain the reduced liver tropism of HABP-LNPs compared to Sham-LNPs.Organ-specific uptake of charged LNPs has been associated with the protein corona that forms around the LNP. [58] Ionizable LNPs that are neutrally charged at physiologic pH can adsorb apolipoprotein E (ApoE), which is ubiquitous in blood, leading to LNP uptake by the liver. [58] However, charged LNPs do not adsorb ApoE, but can adsorb other key targeting molecules. For example, positively charged LNPs have been shown to adsorb vitronectin, and negatively charged LNPs adsorbed 𝛽2-GPI from mouse sera in vitro. [57,58] The authors of this work speculate that passive uptake of serum proteins promotes organ-specific uptake. [57,58] Conversely, one major advantage of the present approach is the use of a pre-defined osteocalcin derived peptide with a high affinity for bone. [24] Still, the uptake of HABP-LNPs in the liver and spleen suggests that non-specific mechanisms, such as serum protein adsorption, are reducing the effective dose of mRNA reaching bone (Figure 4).

HABP-LNPs bound to HAp mineral particles transfected hMSCs at similar transfection levels as soluble LNPs without peptide (Figure 2B). However, free HABP-LNPs without HAp mineral particles showed minimal transfection in vitro (Figure 2C). Similarly, Sham-LNPs did not appreciably transfect hMSCs due to minimal binding to HAp (Figure 2C). HABP-LNPs had over 3-fold improved binding to HAp relative to Sham-LNPs. (Figure 1C). Sham-peptides replaced Gla with Glu residues. Gla in the N-terminus of osteocalcin coordinates binding to hydroxyapatite. [59,60] Substitution of Gla with Glu residues reduces the binding affinity of osteocalcin peptides for hydroxyapatite. [35][36][37] These data suggest that binding to min-eral mediates local transfection by HABP-LNPs (Figure 2C). In contrast, free bisphosphonate LNPs in the absence of minerals demonstrated 2.5-fold higher transfection than unfunctionalized LNPs in vitro. [15] Increased density of HABP on the LNP surface -via increased DSPE-PEG-Maleimide in the LNP formulation -decreased the transfection efficacy of HABP-LNPs (Figure 2C). This is in concordance with Herrera-Barrera et al., who identified that photoreceptor-targeting peptides conjugated to 0.15-0.3% DSPE-PEG-Maleimide LNPs transfected more effectively than LNPs with higher functionalization. [34] Decreasing transfection at increasing LNP surface functionalization may be a result of decreased LNP uptake or decreased endosomal escape. Furthermore, the pK a of the LNP formulation likely influences transfection, as the most effective mRNA LNPs used in previous transfection studies have had a pK a between 6 and 7. [61] Lower pK a has led to aggregation and instability of the LNP, while higher pKa has led to protonated LNPs at physiologic pH leading to cytotoxicity. [61] Among the LNPs tested here, 0.15-0.9% DSPE-PEG-Maleimide formulations decorated with HABP had a pK a between 6 and 7 and over 98% mRNA encapsulation efficiency, while 1.2% HABP-LNPs had a pK a of 4.99 and encapsulated less mRNA cargo. Taken together, the lower pKa and lower mRNA encapsulation efficiency of the most highly functionalized LNPs in the current study may have contributed to the observed reductions in transfection efficacy at 1.2% functionalization (Figure 3A,B).

We have demonstrated that HABP-LNPs delivered in systemic circulation improve transfection in bone. However, further developments of this work will help to improve bone localization. Direct comparison of transfection efficiency, retention time, and distribution of HABP-LNPs in bone compared to bisphosphonate conjugated LNPs will be an important future focus. While in the present study, the HABP was conjugated to DSPE-PEG-Maleimide, the impact of peptide conjugation to different LNP lipid components is currently unknown. Most importantly, future work will focus on developing new LNP formulations and methods to reduce off-target delivery of HABP-LNPs. Longer-term studies will be also required to determine the full safety and efficacy of HABP-LNPs.

Conjugation of an osteocalcin biomimetic HABP to mRNA LNPs enabled binding to HAp and promoted transfection in vitro when bound to HAp particles. Importantly, HABP-LNPs improved transfection within the mouse femora in vivo. HABP-LNPs escaped the liver more readily compared to Sham-LNPs in vivo. Future work will emphasize the refinement of LNP formulations to reduce non-specific uptake in central organs and explore systemic delivery of disease-modifying cargo targeted to the bone. Mineral Binding Peptide Description: To bind to bone mineral a HABP (𝛾EPRR𝛾EVA𝛾EL-GGGS-C) based on the N-terminal alpha-helix of osteocalcin and sham peptide (EPRREVAEL-GGGS-C) with glutamine residues instead of gamma-carboxyglutamic acid were used as previously described. [35][36][37] In order to conjugate the peptides to the lipid nanoparticles, a linker sequence and C-terminal cysteine were added as noted above. Peptides were synthesized from a commercial partner with N-terminal acetylation and C-terminal amidation (Genscript, Piscataway, NJ, USA).

Lipid Nanoparticle (LNP) Preparation: Figure 6 is a schematic outlining LNP preparation. Lipids were dissolved in ethanol and stored in glass vials at -20 °C. Lipid nanoparticles were prepared by mixing a molar ratio of 50:38.5:10:1.5 of ionizable lipid:cholesterol:1,2-DSPC:PEG lipid at 5 mm in ethanol. Lipid nanoparticles were formed by rapidly mixing the lipid-ethanol formulation, as described above, with mRNA in citric acid buffer (100 mm, pH 4) at a ratio of 1:3 by volume. LNPs were dialyzed (10K MWCO, Pur-A-Lyzer Midi, Sigma-Aldrich, Burlington, Massachusetts, USA) for 2 h into PBS prior to further use. To visualize mineral binding or quantify LNP binding 0.1% by molar weight of lipid label (DiO: 3,3′-Dioctadecyloxacarbocyanine Perchlorate, DiD: 1,1′-Dioctadecyl-3,3,3′,3′-Tetramethylindodicarbocyanine, 4-Chlorobenzenesulfonate Salt, DIR: 1,1′dioctadecyl-3,3,3′,3′-tetramethylindotricarbocyanine iodide, Thermofisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) were added prior to mixing (Figure 6). DIR was used as near-infrared lipid lael for in vivo studies.

For peptide conjugation, LNPs were synthesized as described above with 0.15-1.2% of the total lipid consisting of DSPE-PEG-Maleimide. DSPE-PEG-2000-Maleimide served as a substitute for DMG-PEG-2000. For peptide conjugation by thiol Michael addition, HABP or sham peptide were incubated with LNPs at 10-times molar excess of peptide: DSPE-PEG-Maleimide overnight at 4 °C. Peptide functionalized LNPs were then washed to remove residual peptide and LNPs were concentrated two times using ultracentrifugation (Amicon Ultra 10KDA MWCO, Sigma Aldrich, Burlington, Massachusetts, USA). pK a Determination: Lipid nanoparticle pK a was determined by 6-(p-Toluidino)-2-naphthalenesulfonic acid (TNS) assay as previously described. [55] The base buffer consisted of 20 mm sodium phosphate, 25 mm citrate, 20 mm ammonium acetate, and 150 mm NaCl. Buffers were adjusted with 0.1N of NaOH or HCl from pH 4-10. 100 μl of buffer at each pH was added to a black 96 well plate and TNS (6 μm final) and LNPs (25 μm final) were added to the plate. Fluorescence measurements were obtained using a plate reader at 325/435 nm excitation/emission. These fluorescence measurements were normalized to the minimum value and fit to give a titration curve. pK a was evaluated by determining the pH representing 50% of the maximum fluorescence. Statistical differences between curves were determined using Student's t-test in Prism software.

Encapsulation Efficiency: mRNA encapsulation efficiency was determined by incubating mRNA LNPs with a nucleic acid-binding fluorophore (Ribogreen Reagent, Thermofisher Scientific, Waltham, Massachusetts, USA). mRNA encapsulation efficiency was determined by comparing the input mRNA mass of mRNA LNPs against the measured concentration of free mRNA as determined with a standard curve of free mRNA.

Dynamic Light Scattering and Zeta Potential: The size and charge of mRNA LNPs were determined using dynamic light scattering and zeta potential analysis using a Zetasizer (Malvern Panalytical, Malvern, UK). mRNA LNPs were prepared at a concentration of 0.1 mg mL -1 by mass of total lipid in PBS.

Cell Culture and Transfection: hMSCs (Passage 3-6, Lonza, Basel, CH) were grown in 10% FBS/1% penicillin/streptomycin alpha minimum essential medium (Corning, NY, USA). Media was changed every three days and cells were grown to 80-90% confluence prior to transfection. To determine the expression of firefly luciferase mRNA, cells were lysed after 24 h transfection. Cells were washed with PBS prior to the addition of Cell Culture Lysis Reagent (Promega, Madison, WI, USA). 20 μL of lysates were mixed with 100 μL of stock luciferase assay buffer (50 mm Tris, 10 mm MgSO 4 , 6 mm cysteine, 0.02 mm sodium pyrophosphate, 1 mM EDTA, and 2g L -1 BSA). Working buffer was made prior to the assay by mixing the buffer with 0.15 mg mL -1 D-Luciferin and 1 mm ATP. Samples were read on a plate reader (Synergy HTX, Biotek, Winooski, VT, USA).

Mineral Binding Experiments: To assess binding and transfection of mRNA LNPs in the presence of mineral, Sham-LNP or HABP-LNPs were mixed with HAp micro powder (size 3-5 μm, Plasma Biotal, Buxton, UK) at a ratio of 25 μg HAp: μg of mRNA for 30 min unless otherwise specified. For quantification of binding DiO labeled mRNA LNPs were incubated with HAp as described above. At each time point, the mixture was centrifuged for 30s at 2000 g and the supernatant was taken off. Binding percentages were determined by comparing the fluorescence of binding supernatant to unbound control mRNA LNPs in a black multi-well plate using a plate reader (Synergy HTX, Biotek, Winooski, VT, USA). To determine binding to bone, DiD-peptide LNPs (5 μg) were incubated with cancellous cortical chips (4-6 mm, Regeneration Technologies inc., Alachua, FL, USA) for 1 h and then imaged. All imaging was performed using a fluorescent microscope with FITC,Cy5 filter cubes (Nikon Ti-Eclipse, Nikon, Toyko, Japan). The optimal formulation of HABP-LNPs incorporated 0.3% DSPE-PEG-Maleimide and was used unless otherwise specified in screening studies.

In Vivo Experiments: DiR labeled mRNA LNPs were prepared as described above. C57BL/6 mice were obtained from Jackson Laboratory (Bar Harbor, ME, USA). Mice were housed and monitored in the Wisconsin Institute for Medical Research vivarium and experiments were conducted under a University of Wisconsin-Madison Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC) approved protocol. Animals were injected with control, HABP-or Sham-LNPs at 0.5 mg kg -1 mRNA with 3:1 eGFP: Firefly Luciferase mRNA. 24 h after transfection mice were injected with 150 mg kg -1 of D-Luciferin and imaged after 15 min. Mice were then sacrificed, blood was collected, and organs were harvested and imaged for fluorescence and luminescence. Organs were kept moist in PBS in multi-well plates. Serum was isolated from blood and liver function tests (LFTs) were performed. These included the liver enzymes aspartate aminotransferase (AST) and alanine aminotransferase (ALT), alkaline phosphatase (ALP), total bilirubin, albumin, and total protein. LFTs were measured using a veterinary hematology analyzer (Vetscan VS2, Zoetis Diagnostics, Parsippany, NJ, USA).

Histology and Immunofluorescence: Livers and femora were fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde. Mouse femurs were decalcified with 20% EDTA for 48 h, washed, and placed in 70% EtOH prior to paraffin embedding and sectioning. Livers and femora were stained using hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E). Immunofluorescence was performed using anti-GFP primary antibody (1:500, Ab290, Abcam, Cambridge, UK) and Alexafluor 488 goat anti-rabbit secondary antibody (1:500, A11034, Invitrogen, Waltham, MA, USA). Embedding, sectioning, and staining were performed by the Translational Research Initiatives in Pathology laboratory at the University of Wisconsin-Madison.

Statistical Analysis and Data Availability: All statistical analyses were conducted using PRISM software (v.10, GraphPad, Boston, MA, USA). Reported data in figures are mean ± standard deviation (SD) unless otherwise specified. One-way analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to compare differences between three or more groups with post-hoc testing done by Tukey's Honest Significant Difference test to determine differences between individual groups. Annotations for figures were as follows **** p &lt; 0.0001, *** p &lt; 0.001, ** p &lt; 0.01 * p &lt; 0.05; n.s: no significance, unless otherwise specified. N = 3 replicates were performed for each experiment unless otherwise stated. The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable request.

© 2025 The Author(s). Advanced Therapeutics published by Wiley-VCH GmbH

Adv. Therap. 2025, 8, 2400505 2400505 (3 of 10) © 2025 The Author(s). Advanced Therapeutics published by Wiley-VCH GmbH 23663987, 2025, 5, Downloaded from https://advanced.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/adtp.202400505 by Cochrane Latvia, Wiley Online Library on [17/03/2026]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License

© 2025 The Author(s). Advanced Therapeutics published by Wiley-VCH GmbH 23663987, 2025, 5, Downloaded from https://advanced.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/adtp.202400505 by Cochrane Latvia, Wiley Online Library on [17/03/2026]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License

Adv. Therap. 2025, 8, 2400505 2400505 (5 of 10) © 2025 The Author(s). Advanced Therapeutics published by Wiley-VCH GmbH 23663987, 2025, 5, Downloaded from https://advanced.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/adtp.202400505 by Cochrane Latvia, Wiley Online Library on [17/03/2026]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License

Adv. Therap. 2025, 8, 2400505 2400505 (6 of 10) © 2025 The Author(s). Advanced Therapeutics published by Wiley-VCH GmbH 23663987, 2025, 5, Downloaded from https://advanced.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/adtp.202400505 by Cochrane Latvia, Wiley Online Library on [17/03/2026]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License

Adv. Therap. 2025, 8, 2400505 2400505 (10 of 10) © 2025 The Author(s). Advanced Therapeutics published by Wiley-VCH GmbH 23663987, 2025, 5, Downloaded from https://advanced.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/adtp.202400505 by Cochrane Latvia, Wiley Online Library on [17/03/2026]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License</full_text>
  <references>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>Y.-N Zhang</author>
        <author>W Poon</author>
        <author>A Tavares</author>
        <author>I Mcgilvray</author>
        <author>W Chan</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2016</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Lopresti</author>
        <author>M Arral</author>
        <author>N Chaudhary</author>
        <author>K Whitehead</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Dilliard</author>
        <author>Y Sun</author>
        <author>M Brown</author>
        <author>Y.-C Sung</author>
        <author>S Chatterjee</author>
        <author>L Farbiak</author>
        <author>A Vaidya</author>
        <author>X Lian</author>
        <author>X Wang</author>
        <author>A Lemoff</author>
        <author>D Siegwart</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2023</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>T Wei</author>
        <author>Y Sun</author>
        <author>Q Cheng</author>
        <author>S Chatterjee</author>
        <author>Z Traylor</author>
        <author>L Johnson</author>
        <author>M Coquelin</author>
        <author>J Wang</author>
        <author>M Torres</author>
        <author>X Lian</author>
        <author>X Wang</author>
        <author>Y Xiao</author>
        <author>C Hodges</author>
        <author>D Siegwart</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2023</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>Q Cheng</author>
        <author>T Wei</author>
        <author>L Farbiak</author>
        <author>L Johnson</author>
        <author>S Dilliard</author>
        <author>D Siegwart</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Su</author>
        <author>J Yang</author>
        <author>Y Xie</author>
        <author>X Du</author>
        <author>H Chen</author>
        <author>H Zhou</author>
        <author>L Chen</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2019</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>Y Chen</author>
        <author>X Wu</author>
        <author>J Li</author>
        <author>Y Jiang</author>
        <author>K Xu</author>
        <author>J Su</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Newman</author>
        <author>D Benoit</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2016</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>L Macri-Pellizzeri</author>
        <author>N De Melo</author>
        <author>I Ahmed</author>
        <author>D Grant</author>
        <author>B Scammell</author>
        <author>V Sottile</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2018</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Stapleton</author>
        <author>K Sawamoto</author>
        <author>C Alméciga-Díaz</author>
        <author>W Mackenzie</author>
        <author>R Mason</author>
        <author>T Orii</author>
        <author>S Tomatsu</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2017</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>E Prommer</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2009</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>H Fleisch</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1998</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Warner</author>
        <author>J Hathaway-Schrader</author>
        <author>R Lubker</author>
        <author>C Davies</author>
        <author>C Novince</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>L Xue</author>
        <author>N Gong</author>
        <author>S Shepherd</author>
        <author>X Xiong</author>
        <author>X Liao</author>
        <author>X Han</author>
        <author>G Zhao</author>
        <author>C Song</author>
        <author>X Huang</author>
        <author>H Zhang</author>
        <author>M Padilla</author>
        <author>J Qin</author>
        <author>Y Shi</author>
        <author>M.-G Alameh</author>
        <author>D Pochan</author>
        <author>K Wang</author>
        <author>F Long</author>
        <author>D Weissman</author>
        <author>M Mitchell</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>E Rudge</author>
        <author>A Chan</author>
        <author>F Leeper</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>K Kennel</author>
        <author>M Drake</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2009</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>I Orriss</author>
        <author>T Arnett</author>
        <author>R Russell</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2016</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>J Lin</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1996</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
      <authors>
        <author>J Long</author>
        <author>J Dindot</author>
        <author>H Zebroski</author>
        <author>S Kiihne</author>
        <author>R Clark</author>
        <author>A Campbell</author>
        <author>P Stayton</author>
        <author>G Drobny</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1998</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>P Stayton</author>
        <author>G Drobny</author>
        <author>W Shaw</author>
        <author>J Long</author>
        <author>M Gilbert</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2003</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>B Grohe</author>
        <author>J O'young</author>
        <author>D Ionescu</author>
        <author>G Lajoie</author>
        <author>K Rogers</author>
        <author>M Karttunen</author>
        <author>H Goldberg</author>
        <author>G Hunter</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2007</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>R Fujisawa</author>
        <author>Y Wada</author>
        <author>Y Nodasaka</author>
        <author>Y Kuboki</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1292</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>P Hauschka</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1986</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Delany</author>
        <author>I Kalajzic</author>
        <author>A Bradshaw</author>
        <author>E Sage</author>
        <author>E Canalis</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2003</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>Y Asou</author>
        <author>S Rittling</author>
        <author>H Yoshitake</author>
        <author>K Tsuji</author>
        <author>K Shinomiya</author>
        <author>A Nifuji</author>
        <author>D Denhardt</author>
        <author>M Noda</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2001</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>Y Li</author>
        <author>B Cao</author>
        <author>S Modali</author>
        <author>E Lee</author>
        <author>H Xu</author>
        <author>V Petrenko</author>
        <author>J Gray</author>
        <author>M Yang</author>
        <author>C Mao</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>J Bang</author>
        <author>H Park</author>
        <author>J Yoo</author>
        <author>D Lee</author>
        <author>W Choi</author>
        <author>J Lee</author>
        <author>Y.-R Lee</author>
        <author>C Kim</author>
        <author>H Koo</author>
        <author>S Kim</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Poundarik</author>
        <author>A Boskey</author>
        <author>C Gundberg</author>
        <author>D Vashishth</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2018</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Kavukcuoglu</author>
        <author>P Patterson-Buckendahl</author>
        <author>A Mann</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2009</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Boskey</author>
        <author>S Gadaleta</author>
        <author>C Gundberg</author>
        <author>S Doty</author>
        <author>P Ducy</author>
        <author>G Karsenty</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1998</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>C Diegel</author>
        <author>S Hann</author>
        <author>U Ayturk</author>
        <author>J Hu</author>
        <author>K Lim</author>
        <author>C Droscha</author>
        <author>Z Madaj</author>
        <author>G Foxa</author>
        <author>I Izaguirre</author>
        <author>Vai Vivarium</author>
        <author>Transgenics Core</author>
        <author>N Paracha</author>
        <author>B Pidhaynyy</author>
        <author>T Dowd</author>
        <author>A Robling</author>
        <author>M Warman</author>
        <author>B Williams</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>T Moriishi</author>
        <author>R Ozasa</author>
        <author>T Ishimoto</author>
        <author>T Nakano</author>
        <author>T Hasegawa</author>
        <author>T Miyazaki</author>
        <author>W Liu</author>
        <author>R Fukuyama</author>
        <author>Y Wang</author>
        <author>H Komori</author>
        <author>X Qin</author>
        <author>N Amizuka</author>
        <author>T Komori</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Herrera-Barrera</author>
        <author>R Ryals</author>
        <author>M Gautam</author>
        <author>A Jozic</author>
        <author>M Landry</author>
        <author>T Korzun</author>
        <author>M Gupta</author>
        <author>C Acosta</author>
        <author>J Stoddard</author>
        <author>R Reynaga</author>
        <author>W Tschetter</author>
        <author>N Jacomino</author>
        <author>O Taratula</author>
        <author>C Sun</author>
        <author>A Lauer</author>
        <author>M Neuringer</author>
        <author>G Sahay</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2023</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Brounts</author>
        <author>J Lee</author>
        <author>S Weinberg</author>
        <author>S Lan Levengood</author>
        <author>E Smith</author>
        <author>W Murphy</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2013</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>J Lee</author>
        <author>J Lee</author>
        <author>A Wagoner-Johnson</author>
        <author>W Murphy</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2009</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>J Lee</author>
        <author>J Lee</author>
        <author>W Murphy</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2010</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>J Lee</author>
        <author>X Yu</author>
        <author>A Wagoner Johnson</author>
        <author>W Murphy</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2017</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Roelofs</author>
        <author>C Stewart</author>
        <author>S Sun</author>
        <author>K Bła Żewska</author>
        <author>B Kashemirov</author>
        <author>C Mckenna</author>
        <author>R Russell</author>
        <author>M Rogers</author>
        <author>M Lundy</author>
        <author>F Ebetino</author>
        <author>F Coxon</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2012</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>J Poser</author>
        <author>P Price</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1979</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>C.-T Leu</author>
        <author>E Luegmayr</author>
        <author>L Freedman</author>
        <author>G Rodan</author>
        <author>A Reszka</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2006</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>B Mui</author>
        <author>Y Tam</author>
        <author>M Jayaraman</author>
        <author>S Ansell</author>
        <author>X Du</author>
        <author>Y Tam</author>
        <author>P Lin</author>
        <author>S Chen</author>
        <author>J Narayanannair</author>
        <author>K Rajeev</author>
        <author>M Manoharan</author>
        <author>A Akinc</author>
        <author>M Maier</author>
        <author>P Cullis</author>
        <author>T Madden</author>
        <author>M Hope</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2013</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>H Hatakeyama</author>
        <author>H Akita</author>
        <author>H Harashima</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2011</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>K Remaut</author>
        <author>B Lucas</author>
        <author>K Braeckmans</author>
        <author>J Demeester</author>
        <author>S De Smedt</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2007</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>F Quimby</author>
        <author>R Luong</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2007</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>R Sabatino</author>
        <author>A Antonelli</author>
        <author>S Battistelli</author>
        <author>R Schwendener</author>
        <author>M Magnani</author>
        <author>L Rossi</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2014</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Van Rooijen</author>
        <author>E Van Kesteren-Hendrikx</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2002</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Patntirapong</author>
        <author>M Poolgesorn</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1294</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Fiegl</author>
        <author>M Juergens</author>
        <author>W Hiddemann</author>
        <author>J Braess</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2007</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Lymperi</author>
        <author>A Ersek</author>
        <author>F Ferraro</author>
        <author>F Dazzi</author>
        <author>N Horwood</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2011</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Blumsohn</author>
        <author>R Hannon</author>
        <author>R Eastell</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1995</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>W Farrugia</author>
        <author>R Melick</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1986</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Page</author>
        <author>A Hayman</author>
        <author>L Andersson</author>
        <author>T Chambers</author>
        <author>M Warburton</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1993</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>K Lam</author>
        <author>P Schreiner</author>
        <author>A Leung</author>
        <author>P Stainton</author>
        <author>S Reid</author>
        <author>E Yaworski</author>
        <author>P Lutwyche</author>
        <author>J Heyes</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2023</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Kim</author>
        <author>M Jeong</author>
        <author>S Hur</author>
        <author>Y Cho</author>
        <author>J Park</author>
        <author>H Jung</author>
        <author>Y Seo</author>
        <author>H Woo</author>
        <author>K Nam</author>
        <author>K Lee</author>
        <author>H Lee</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2021</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Jayaraman</author>
        <author>S Ansell</author>
        <author>B Mui</author>
        <author>Y Tam</author>
        <author>J Chen</author>
        <author>X Du</author>
        <author>D Butler</author>
        <author>L Eltepu</author>
        <author>S Matsuda</author>
        <author>J Narayanannair</author>
        <author>K Rajeev</author>
        <author>I Hafez</author>
        <author>A Akinc</author>
        <author>M Maier</author>
        <author>M Tracy</author>
        <author>P Cullis</author>
        <author>T Madden</author>
        <author>M Manoharan</author>
        <author>M Hope</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2012</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Dilliard</author>
        <author>Q Cheng</author>
        <author>D Siegwart</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2021</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Akinc</author>
        <author>W Querbes</author>
        <author>S De</author>
        <author>J Qin</author>
        <author>M Frank-Kamenetsky</author>
        <author>K Jayaprakash</author>
        <author>M Jayaraman</author>
        <author>K Rajeev</author>
        <author>W Cantley</author>
        <author>J Dorkin</author>
        <author>J Butler</author>
        <author>L Qin</author>
        <author>T Racie</author>
        <author>A Sprague</author>
        <author>E Fava</author>
        <author>A Zeigerer</author>
        <author>M Hope</author>
        <author>M Zerial</author>
        <author>D Sah</author>
        <author>K Fitzgerald</author>
        <author>M Tracy</author>
        <author>M Manoharan</author>
        <author>V Koteliansky</author>
        <author>A De Fougerolles</author>
        <author>M Maier</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2010</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>Q Hoang</author>
        <author>F Sicheri</author>
        <author>A Howard</author>
        <author>D Yang</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2003</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>C Frazão</author>
        <author>D Simes</author>
        <author>R Coelho</author>
        <author>D Alves</author>
        <author>M Williamson</author>
        <author>P Price</author>
        <author>M Cancela</author>
        <author>M Carrondo</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2005</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors>
        <author>P Patel</author>
        <author>N Ibrahim</author>
        <author>K Cheng</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2021</date>
    </reference>
  </references>
</document>