<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Calcium phosphate formation in vitro. II. Effects of environment on amorphous-crystalline transformation.pdf</file>
	<title>Calcium Phosphate Formation in Vitro II. Effects of Environment on Amorphous-Crystalline Transformation '</title>
	<date>Unknown</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Calcium phosphate formation in vitro. II. Effects of environment on amorphous-crystalline transformation.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>J Termine</author>
		<author>R Peckauskas</author>
		<author>A Posner</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract/>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>MATERIALS AND METHODS</heading>
			<text>All solution, reaction, and sample-handling procedures used in this study were exactly the same as those already described in the first paper of this series (7). However, when initial Ca X P millimolar products greater than 50 rn&amp; were used, aliquot centrifugation and precipitate recovery procedures described earlier (2) were substituted for those employed at lower levels of initial supersaturation (7). Amorphous-crystalline conversion was assessed by quantitative

x-ray diffraction examination of the lyophilized precipitates (2,9) and by following supernatant calcium concentration (2) using atomic absorption spectrophotometry (7). The chemical composition of the recovered precipitates was determined by methods described previously (7). Macromolecular inhibition of t,he ready sediment,ation of either amorphous or crystalline calcium phosphate precipitates (macromolecule-calcium phosphate flotation) was examined by differential centrifugation procedures (17,18). The weight ratio of macromolecule to calcium phosphate in both the total precipitates and the different centrifugal fractions recoverable from these flotation reactions was determined from percentage moisture and percentage ash data (9). The buffer-organic solvent systems and their associated dielectric constant valnes utilized in this study were taken from previously published, tabulated dat,a (19).

Reagent grade chemicals were used throughout. The commercial sources of the macromolecules used in this study were the same as those listed in the first paper of this series (7). In addition, histone-stripped soluble RNA (yeast) and preparations of L-a-lecithin and L-or-cephalin were obtained from General Biochemicals. The saltsoluble collagen, kindly provided by Dr. 8. Rothbard of the Department of Medicine, Cornell University Medical College, New York, New York, was reconstituted and purified from young rat tail tendon. The protein-polysaccharide preparations used here were the same as those used earlier (7).</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>The amount of time that actually elapsed during the solution mediated transformation of amorphous calcium phosphate into crystalline apatite was short and invariable.

On the other hand, the time required to reach this period of rapid precipitate conversion was strongly dependent upon the exact solution environment. Amorphous calcium phosphate was more stable when formed from solutions high in pH, ionic strength, and viscosity, rich in Ca2&quot; relative to HPOi-, and low in initial supersaturation and temperature. The suspension lifet,ime of amorphous calcium phosphate was also sensitive to changes in dielectric constant. Amorphous calcium phosphate was also more stable in the presence of poly-n-glutamntc, polyacrylate, phosvitin, casein, and large amounts of the protein-polysaccharides, or by the addition of small amounts of Mg2+, PzO:-, CO&quot;,-and F. Macromolecule-calcium phosphate flotation reactions (inhibition of ready sedimentation) were found for the casein, poly-r-glutamate, polyacrylate, and poly-n-lysine molecules as well as for the protein-polysaccharide complex.

Once initial mineral phase separat.ion takes place during solution-mediated calcium phosphate formation, the next major event to occur is the transformation (via dissolution and reprecipitation) of the initial amorphous calcium phosphate precipitate into tiny crystals of apatitic calcium phosphate (l-7). The physicochemical mechanisms which govern this precipitate phase transformation process are such that once initiated it would normally proceed to completion, i.e., until only crystalline apatite is present (24).

Therefore, amorphous calcium phosphate would be expected to have only a finite suspension lifetime, the natural extent of which may be dependent upon the exact experimental conditions used (2)(3)(4).

Bone tissue has always been found to contain substantial amounts of amorphous calcium phosphate as well as crystalline apatite (8)(9)(10)(11)(12). Thus, it is obvious that some factors must exist within living systems which regulate the physicochemical conversion of amorphous calcium phosphate to crystalline apatite. The variabilit,y and/or specificit,y of these factors is evidenced by t.he fact that while approximately 30% of the total mineral found within mature bone and dentine tissue is always amorphous calcium phosphate (g-12)) no amorphous mineral has been found in mature dental enamel (8). Furthermore, only amorphous calcium phosphate has been found within isolated cell mitochondria which have been subjected to energy-dependent calcium loading in the presence of ATP and inorganic phosphate (13)(14)(15). Because of these findings and because both the physical and chemical properties of amorphous calcium phosphate have been found to be considerably different from those of crystalline apatite (2-5, 8, 11, IG), it is reasonable to suppose that within mammalian tissue systems, the amorphous-crystalline mineral phase transformation is subject to some form of biological control.

The result,s presented in this paper form part of an overall reexamination of calcium phosphate formation in vitro in which both cryst,allographic and kinetic considerations were carefully taken into account (7). This paper reports the manner in which t,he amorphous-crystalline precipitate phase transformation reaction is affect'ed by a number of biologically pertinent environmental factors and outlines some kinetic and physical interachions between amorphous calcium phosphate and certain macromolecules.

All solution, reaction, and sample-handling procedures used in this study were exactly the same as those already described in the first paper of this series (7). However, when initial Ca X P millimolar products greater than 50 rn&amp; were used, aliquot centrifugation and precipitate recovery procedures described earlier (2) were substituted for those employed at lower levels of initial supersaturation (7). Amorphous-crystalline conversion was assessed by quantitative

x-ray diffraction examination of the lyophilized precipitates (2,9) and by following supernatant calcium concentration (2) using atomic absorption spectrophotometry (7). The chemical composition of the recovered precipitates was determined by methods described previously (7). Macromolecular inhibition of t,he ready sediment,ation of either amorphous or crystalline calcium phosphate precipitates (macromolecule-calcium phosphate flotation) was examined by differential centrifugation procedures (17,18). The weight ratio of macromolecule to calcium phosphate in both the total precipitates and the different centrifugal fractions recoverable from these flotation reactions was determined from percentage moisture and percentage ash data (9). The buffer-organic solvent systems and their associated dielectric constant valnes utilized in this study were taken from previously published, tabulated dat,a (19).

Reagent grade chemicals were used throughout. The commercial sources of the macromolecules used in this study were the same as those listed in the first paper of this series (7). In addition, histone-stripped soluble RNA (yeast) and preparations of L-a-lecithin and L-or-cephalin were obtained from General Biochemicals. The saltsoluble collagen, kindly provided by Dr. 8. Rothbard of the Department of Medicine, Cornell University Medical College, New York, New York, was reconstituted and purified from young rat tail tendon. The protein-polysaccharide preparations used here were the same as those used earlier (7).

In every reaction examined in this study, the amount of time which elapsed from the very first detection of apatite crystals to the complete disappearance of the initial amorphous calcium phosphat,e precipitate did not vary from a value of 8 f 3 min as long as pH was kept between values of 7.0 and 8.0 and the Ca X P millimolar product used for the initial reactant mixing was kept below a value of 150 m&amp;. However, the amount of time which elapsed from initial solid phase separation to t,he start of this period of relatively rapid amorphous-crystalline conversion, i.e., the amorphous calcium phosphat,e suspension lifetime defined here as t, , was strongly dependent upon the exact experimental conditions used. For example, Table I shows the effect of decreasing initial Ca2+ and HPO?-concentration upon amorphous calcium phosphate suspension lifetime. As can be seen from this table, amorphous calcium phosphate appears to be much more stable if it is formed from solutions at low levels of initial supersaturation than if formed from solutions at relatively high initial supersaturation.

Throughout this study, solution conditions were generally chosen which afforded instantaneous precipitation at room temperature for the sake of experimental convenience. However, each effect reported in this paper was spot-checked by addit.ional experimentation at 37&quot; and at low levels of initial supersaturation in order to see if it was still valid at different operating conditions. Whenever the buffering capacity of the Tris medium was found to be insufficient to maintain pH effectively throughout initial mineral-phase separation, a higher initial pH was always used at the time the reagents were mixed. Once amorphous calcium phosphate precipitation took place, the resultant pH value remained unchanged thereafter. Therefore, the pH values stated in this paper are those existing throughout the entire suspension lifetime and subsequent transformation of the initial amorphous phase.

Figure 1 shows the effect of initial Ca/P a These reactions were conducted in Tris buffer, ionic strength = 0.15, pH = 7.40, with an initial Ca/P molar mixing ratio of 1.11 and constant gentle stirring at 25&quot;. Initial Ca2+ and HPOk2-concentrations are expressed as initial Ca X P millimolar products. molar mixing ratio, while Fig. 2 shows the effect of pH upon amorphous calcium phosphate suspension lifetime (tJ. A4s can be seen from t.hese figures, amorphous calcium phosphate stability is enhanced by solutions high in pH, rich in calcium, and poor in phosphat,e. The effect of varying ionic strength (LC) and dielectric constant (E) on L, are shown in Figs. 3 and4, respectively. These figures show that amorphous calcium phosphate is least stable when suspended in aqueous media of low dielectric constant and low ionic strength. In addition, we have found that amorphous calcium phosphat,e is 65% more stable in solutions whose calculated intrinsic viscosity has been increased to a value of 2.2 Cp by t.he addition of either 34% (w/v) glycerol or 26 % (w/v, sucrose. The effect of temperature on amorphous calcium phosphate stability was even more striking. For example, at pH = 7.70, all other solution conditions being identical to those described for Figs. 3 and4, amorphous calcium phosphate is three times less stable at X7&quot;, while being 16 times more stable at The effect of added ions on amorphous calcium phosphate suspension lifetime is shown in Table II. Sodium, potassium, and citrate were inactive in this test system even though these ions were added at three times their normal compact bone levels (20). As might possibly have been expected from previous investigations using higher concentrations of Mg2+ (21-23), COa2-(24, 25), and P20T4-(6, 26), we found all three of these ions effective amorphous calcium phosphate stabilizers even when used at very low relative concentrations. On the other hand, we were somewhat surprised to find that fluoride was an amorphous calcium phosphate stabilizer, since this ion has usually been thought of as an apat,ibe-perfecting agent. The data of Table II show that the effect of these four stabilizing ions is additive when they are used in combination and that their relative strengths in stabilizing ability are as follows: PZOT4-&gt; Mg2+ &gt; F-&gt;&gt; CO?-.

The effect of added model macromolecules on amorphous calcium phosphate suspension lifetime is shown in Table III. Whenever a macromolecule was found to be insoluble under the conditions listed in t,he table, (e.g., polyglycine or poly-L-tyrosine) it was used in suspension. In all instances with the exception of the more concentrated proteinpolysaccharide system lisbed in Table III, macromolecule-induced viscosity effects were negligible. Casein, phosvitin, Na polyacrylate, poly-L-glutamate, and the proteinpolysaccharides all showed significant amorphous calcium phosphate stabilization act,ivity. The relative stabilization strengths of these macromolecules were as follows: poly-L-glutamate &gt;&gt; Na polyacrylate &gt; phosvitin, casein &gt;&gt; protein-polysaccharide.

In light of the results obtained with the phosphoproteins, casein and phosvitin, the possible involvement of bound organic phosphate in amorphous calcium phosphate stabilization was examined further by testing both solutions of sRNA and emulsions of phospholipids. In both cases, we observed considerable stabilizing activity. Amorphous calcium phosphate suspension lifetime was increased by more than 100% at initial concentrations of 1.0 and 0.2 mg/ml for the sRNA and the phospholipid preparst,ions, respectively.

The protein-polysaccharide complex has been demonstrated to inhibit the ready sedimentation of freshly formed calcium phosphat,e precipitates (17, 18, 27) causing them tlo be split into two differently sedimentable centrifugal fractions. Therefore, we decided to determine whether a similar activity might also be demonstrated by other macromolecules and to examine any differenbly sedimentable centrifugal fractions that we might obtain for differences in mineral    content, crystallographic phase, and amorphous-crystalline conversion rate. Of all the macromolecules used in this study (outside of the protein-polysaccharide complex), only casein, polyacrylate, poly-L-lysine, and poly-L-glutamate were found to inhibit the ready sedimentation of amorphous calcium phosphate and crystalline apatite. These data, summarized in Table IV, showed that in no case did any kinetic, percentage of ash, or crystallographic difference exist between either of the two differently sedimenting centrifugal fractions obtained from any of these macromolecular systems at any time during t,he course of the entire calcium phosphak formation reaction. Hence, this inhibition of ready sedimentation may best be described as s flotation effect. lcurthtr, t,he dat,a of Table IV also indicate that this flotation phenomeuon is associated with either the coexistence of both high molecular lveight and high charge den&amp;y \vit,hin the same macromolecule (e.g., the prot.ein polysaccharide complex, polS-L-~lutl-Lmat.e) or the ability of :L given macromolrcule to form qggegstes or net norks which might, function in an exclusion process to difiPrrntially sediment, calcium phosphate prrciptates OII the basis of overall particle sixt&gt; (e.g., c:tsein).

The data presented in this paper demorlst.r:lt,e that the expected suspension lifetime of a.11 amorphous calcium phosphate precipitat.e is strongiy dependent, upon the particular environment in which it resides. Inasmuch as initial mineral phase separation is :llso dqwndent upon solution tnvironmcwt (7), it can thus be seen that exact cont,rol of: (1) initia.1 Wf, HPO%-, I'&amp;-, Al@+, F-, CY&amp;-concentration;

(2) pH, tot'al ionic strength, viscosity, and temperature; and (3) the concentration of all macromoleculnl polyelcctrolytes, will determine the complete sequence of cveuts occurring \vithin :IIQ given calcium phouph:rte-form2ltioIl system.

Tll~ po&quot;siblr role of mncromoleculev iI1 the tissue formation of calcium phosphate h:Ls been :tdequ:ltely reviewed elsewhere (20,. The findmgs of t.his rind the previous investigation (7) \vould support the contelltion that macromoleculrs can inflwnw bol 11 initial formation of amorphous calcium phosphate and the ultimtltrx formation of apatite through :lmoryhous-cr?-stallirle co11version.

The exact effect which a given macromolecule exhibits to\vurd nmorphous calcium phosphate formation is strongly dependent upo~l the initial degree of supersatur:rtiorl of its calcifying solution (i). It ma&gt;. be possible that the reversal from nctivit+-:w ;I phuse separation inhibitor at rel:tt,ivel&gt;: high initial supersnturation to that of :I mmcral phase separation ciLt,:LIyst :tt r&amp;itively lo\\-kvcls of initial supersnturat,ion obwrved for cnsrin (i), phosvitin (7), Iysozyme (7), and the protein-polysaccharidc complex (7, 27) ma?. reflect macromolecular partitioning or sheltering of the amorphous calcium phosphate nucleation and/or gro\vth process from total :w3ws to free solvent. For ex:implc, :it high supersatur:Ltioll, macromolecul:~r c&gt;ffects would not be tkspected to comlwtc cfficient.ly Gth the relativcl~ high driving forces fol amorphous calcium phosphnte formation existing \vit,hirt the solvent spice itself. Thas, under these collditiorls, m:~cro~noleculcs probably br:h:lw only, as C:i&quot;+ or HI'C),'binding agrats. Ho\vewr, at rtll:LtivoI&gt; lonlewls of initial sul)crs:ttur:itioIi, i.e., \vhtw solution :imorphous calcium ~'hosph&quot;tc formation lag times are quite long, specific m:tcromolecules could coutnin sites either in their illternal or solwtiowsh~~ll sp:w~ \vllich may actually be favored 1oc:lles for amorphous c:Llcium phosphnt e nucle:ltion :tr~d;or growth. Thus, undo thaw latter conditions, amoq)hous calcium phosphates fornm:ltion ~nllrl t:llcr plaw \vithitr thra protwtiw domain of the macromolecular species and not in free solution.

We did not find reconst'ituted collagen an eff ect,ive inhibitor of amorphous-crystalline conversion, but as might have been expected from t)he results of others (Z&amp;35), we did find it an excellent initiator of amorphous calcium phosphate phase separation (7). The additional finding (7, 36) t.hat gelatin can be an effective initial mineral phase sepal&amp;on catalyst \vould appear to indicate that native collagen conformation may not really be essential for this activit,y. However, the gelatin effect may not be so specific as the native collagen om since it occurs at higher relat.ive concentrations.

The results obtained in this overall invrstigation with model macromolecules 011 initial mineral phase separation (7), amorphous-crystalline conversion, and calcium phosphate flotat,ion provide ample evidence that macromolecules cm definit,ely int)eract wit,h calcium phosphate salts. Thus, these model system results are also compatible with previous suggesbions that functional groups contZained within acidic mucopolysaccharides such as the est,er sulfate, glycuronic carboxyl, or Kacet)yl groups (X-27, 37), charged amino acid side chains of proteins (%8,33,36,?&amp;40): and seryl or t)hreonyl ester phosphat,e 011 polypeptide chains (ZS, 41) might possibly serve as functional sites for matrix-mineral interactions lvithin connective tissue.

Specifically, the data obtained here with phospholipids, RNA, and the phosphoproteins, phosvitin and casein, and with the free carboxyl-containing polymers, polyacrglate and poly-L-glutamate, indicate that organically bound phosphate and acidic amino acid side chains may very well be the most potent, sites for any given macromolecule-mineral int,eraction. This view is reinforced by earlier apatite gel-chromatography data indicating that theyc two functional groups are the strongest receptor sit.es for the adsorption of proteins to calcium phosphate columns (4'2). However, the mild flotation result observed above for poly-Llysine and the initial mineral phase separn-t&amp;n catalysis activit)y found earlier (7) for both this polyumino acid and for lysozyme indicate that basic amino acid side chains could also serve as sites for macromolecule-mineral interact,ion. These latter findings are in agreement jvith previous d:ka implicating basic amino acid residues as potential sites for collagen-mineral attachment wit'hin bone tissue (28, 39, 40) and suggesting that lysyl-nnd,/or phosphoserylresidues in c:win may br the specific sites stabilizing amorphous calcium phosphate nit,hin casein-miner:11 miccllw isolat:~bl~ from bovirw milk (43).

The results obt:Gned in this investigation also indicate that, more than just side chain charact'eristics may be involved in the intrraction of :L given macromolecule with the calcium phosphates. For example, \ve have found that macromolecular charge and size charact)erist,ics are important in both initial mineral phase aeparat(ion catalysis (7) and mncromolecule~mineral fMat,ion reactions. We have also found t.lwk :t dtacrcused dirlwtric constant generally mhanccs both initial mineral phase separation (7) and amorphous-crystalline conversion. Thus, it is entirely possible that a local milieu favorable for either amorphous calcium phosphate OI npatite formation might, also be provided b) a partially apolar region Avithin a macromolecule as lvell as by its more polar regions. Consequently, macromolecular size :md conformation should also bc considewd as possible contributing fact,ors to any given macromolecule-mineral intertlction.

OF INITIAL CONCENTRATION ON THE SUSPENSION LIFETIME OF AMORPHOUS CALCIUM PHOSPHATEQ Ini&amp; (Ca X P) 131.6 rrul2 50.6 map 27.2 m~2 21.0 mM* 14.6 rn~~ Suspension lifetime (min)</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>~Zmcr. J. Anal</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Watsok</author>
				<author>Robinmix</author>
				<author>A It</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1053</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nature London</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Eiinics</author>
				<author>) Ili</author>
				<author>I</author>
				<author>, Ssi;N</author>
				<author>I Ii</author>
				<author>A Posrv~a</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1965</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Trans. S. 1.. Acad. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Elwm</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Crystal ~;rowt~h</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Eanicj</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>I. Chew</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Waltox</author>
				<author>W Bodin</author>
				<author>Li Fljrd:I)i</author>
				<author>Schw</author>
				<author>A \rtz</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>C&amp;if. 'I'issue</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Fr~ixcis</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>IY~. Biochem. Hiophys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Terminp</author>
				<author>) \nd Posneit</author>
				<author>A</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1970</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Cd+. Tissfte xcs</title>
			<authors/>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>I'osxI~:~t</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Tixmini~:</author>
				<author>Il)</author>
				<author>I W~jthikr</author>
				<author>Il</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Hid. dletl</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Sot</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>L. J., tsr. ./. illnrl. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Q~</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Rost;l</title>
			<authors>
				<author>I~i</author>
				<author>N</author>
				<author>J</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Cell. /Viol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Lkhningkr</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1964</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>r., niorhirn. Riophj/s</title>
			<authors>
				<author>I \c:H</author>
				<author>R&lt;</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1067</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>I. Cell. IJiol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1968</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Clin. Or/hop</title>
			<authors>
				<author>I I&lt;</author>
				<author>) Termini</author>
				<author>:</author>
				<author>J Ani) Posn~x</author>
				<author>A</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>A~rient?</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Ichs</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>I. Bird. Chm</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R \lvo</author>
				<author>J Iw</author>
				<author>Hr</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>~riysicd Chemistry of Elect~rolytic Solutions</title>
			<authors>
				<author>I~ Irnp;U</author>
				<author>H ~wis</author>
				<author>B K%</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1958</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Bwe</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Uwx</author>
				<author>M</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1968</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Arch. Riochem. Biophys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>I~oullt</author>
				<author>Ibl</author>
				<author>J \rier</author>
				<author>It</author>
				<author>I Ibsli</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1962</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title/>
			<authors>
				<author>B Bachii</author>
				<author>Tr</author>
				<author>\utz ; . I?</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>I rch. oI.uz Riol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1965</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>OYN</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Ii</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Ti.wrre Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Cc&amp;if</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1968</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>I rch. Hiochent. Biop&amp;</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B</author>
				<author>B 'i-R</author>
				<author>\t</author>
				<author>Tz</author>
				<author>Simon</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nhx#</title>
			<authors/>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>c&amp;if. Tis.soe Kes</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Anu ?~~uli~y</author>
				<author>H \n</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>N</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L%tvhlt\</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>ilrch. I'nlhol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>, Sorei</author>
				<author>D</author>
				<author>; \ni</author>
				<author>J Ja</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1960</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title/>
			<authors>
				<author>T \nu</author>
				<author>\n</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>E;xpct%?n</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N \nu S \n'i'h. ; #</author>
				<author>M</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1956</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Cak&lt;f. Tissue Rcs</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W \i) Kins</author>
				<author>C</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1968</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>r&amp;if. Tissrte Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B \(' Iir\</author>
				<author>B</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1968</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. fPiovrct/. Xaler. Rrs</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Fiukimin</author>
				<author>B Ani) Sc~wwtx</author>
				<author>A</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>I~ior+wnr. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Howssss</author>
				<author>K Ri</author>
				<author>Ii</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>CaZci.f. Tissue</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1969</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>&amp;kif. 'I'ksrle Ret?. 1</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Solomons</author>
				<author>J Iltvl~n</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1958</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Hiochem. Biophys. .Ida</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Z-Lo!) ; ) R~~i~ig~\rui</author>
				<author>C \nl) K.\tr.\s.\~cr</author>
				<author>T</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Ii., J. Dair!/ Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>: Rosr</author>
				<author>) \su Cor</author>
				<author>Vrx</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1966</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
</document>
