<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/chemrxiv-2025-v4cjh.pdf</file>
	<title>Moving Beyond PEG: Poly(2-oxazolines) and Poly(2-oxazines) Alter the Surface Properties of Lipid Nanoparticles</title>
	<date>2025</date>
	<doi_number>10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-v4cjh</doi_number>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/chemrxiv-2025-v4cjh.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>Josef Kehrein</author>
		<author>Robert Luxenhofer</author>
		<author>Alex Bunker</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>Nucleic acid carrying lipid nanoparticles have received great attention since the COVID-19 pandemic.</abstract>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>System Preparation</heading>
			<text>For modeling of spherical LNPs coated with various polymers, the three available end structures published by Trollmann and Böckmann (41) (simulation lengths: 240, 445 and 456 ns) for the full, unloaded Comirnaty® vaccine, prior to pEGylation, were used as starting point for running three individual replicas per polymer type (Table 2). Solvent was removed and lipids conjugated via a triazole linker with either linear pEG, pMeOx, pEtOx or pMeOzi of the same molecular weight (corresponding to 45, 23, 20 and 20 monomers respectively) were inserted and aligned to the coordinates of the unpEGylated ALC-0159 lipids via PyMOL (49). After alignment, the original ALC-0159 molecules (conjugated with only two EG monomers) were deleted. The resulting structure was then re-solvated with TIP3P water and a sodium chloride concentration of 150 mM, removing all solvent molecules placed within the LNP and keeping a 1.2 nm minimum distance of the solute to the cubic box border. To fix all clashes introduced by insertion of lipopolymers into the equilibrated monolayer, systems were then subjected to multiple short energy minimizations (applying a soft-core potential in the beginning as described in (50)) and simulation runs with 1 fs time steps that were gradually increased to 2 fs. All systems were further investigated for correction of potential ring penetrations of the initally inserted lipids with nearby CHL molecules. Initial equilibration was repeated once upon re-solvation into smaller boxes after polymers condensed onto the surface after several tens of nanoseconds.

In addition to the spherical LNPs, the impact of polymers on dynamics of the bilayer formed at and Böckmann enclosing the hydrophobic lipid core at neutral pH was also modeled analogously after multiplication by 9 along the x-y plane via packmol (51). This was performed to provide a sufficiently large system size for potentially studying interactions with serum proteins in future works.</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>These particles generally consist of four base components (2, 3): (i) cholesterol (CHL) or similar phytosterols that influence membrane ordering (4,5), (ii) helper lipids, such as phospholipids with a high phase transition temperature that increase LNP stability (2), (iii) protonizable aminolipids, which are essential for pH-induced structural re-arrangements enabling escape from the endosomal acidic environment (6), as well as (iv) lipids conjugated with poly(ethylene glycol) (pEG). Such lipopolymers are known to influence particle size (7) and increase shelf-life by preventing aggregation (8). Furthermore, in vivo, the hydrophilic polymer forms a protective &quot;stealth&quot;-inducing shield that reduces opsonization and, thus, immunogenicity (9). The effect these polymers have on the formation of a protein or, more broadly speaking, biomolecular corona, is an active topic of research. Aggregation of serum particles on the surface can modulate pharmakokinetics (10)(11)(12)(13).

For example, apolipoprotein E (ApoE) on the surface of Onpattro®, the very first marketed nucleic acid delivering LNP, was made responsible for its desired hepatocyte targeting (14). For many decades, pEG has been the gold standard for coating bioconjugates (15,16) and various delivery systems, e.g. liposomes (17) and LNPs (3). However, despite its broad recognition, continuous exposure to pEG can result in accelerated blood clearance (18) and is believed to induce production of anti-pEG antibodies that were made responsible for many immunogenic responses patients have experienced (19)(20)(21). Thus, alternative polymeric coating materials applicable for biomedical purposes are being developed (9,22,23).

Three aspects of LNPs need to be considered for optimizing current formulation designs: (i) overcoming liver tropism, hence LNP accumulation within hepatocytes, (ii) improving endosomal escape of genetic material after cellular uptake (which currently only amounts to about 4 % of the total amount of administered nucleic acids (24)), and (iii) reducing immunogenicity (3,25).

Experimental screenings have focused on alternatives to CHL (5) and helper lipids (26,27), the inclusion of other auxiliary components enabling selective organ targeting (28), as well as the applicability of novel aminolipids (29). However, ultimately, all of the mentioned aspects depend on surface properties (3) which are largely also defined by the outer polymeric sheath. Adjusting the molar ratio of pEGylated lipids within LNPs can optimize delivery e.g. to lung cells (30) and tuning the length of the carbon chains of pEGylated lipids has shown to influence desorption (3).

Moreover, replacing pEG entirely with poly(sarcosine) resulted in an improved safety profile (31).

Very recently, LNPs coated with another alternative, poly(2-ethyl-2-oxazoline), have successfully been tested for mRNA delivery to multiple target tissues in mice, showing reduced bloodstream clearance compared to the pEGylated counterpart (32). This family of polymers has been used for a broad range of medical applications, including as bioconjugation material (33)(34)(35)(36).

Complementary computational approaches can rationalize experimental designs by providing molecular insights, e.g. through molecular dynamics simulations (MDs) (37,38). Besides machine learning (39), molecular modeling has also expanded to nucleic acid carrying LNPs, for which relevant works were summarized in a review (40). In a recent atomistic study, Trollmann and Böckmann investigated the pH-dependent lipid phase transition of LNPs in detail and assembled, from the ground up, a full model of an mRNA-unloaded variant of the Comirnaty® vaccine (41) (Figure 1A). This work provided valuable insight into the distribution of individual LNP components. The oil-like core was composed of CHL and aminolipids. At neutral pH (conditions within the bloodstream), the core was enveloped by a monolayer consisting of CHL, DSPC, aminolipids, as well as the pEGylated lipids. At acidic pH, bilayer formation was observed, which might represent a structural re-arrangement necessary for mRNA loading during LNP formulation, but also for endosomal escape after cellular uptake. Interestingly, pEG on the surface preferably addressed neutral aminolipids of the outer monolayer, leaving CHL and DSPC molecules more solvent-exposed. This raises the question whether alternative polymers could yield a different interaction profile, modulating the LNP interface with biological media.

Based on these findings, in this work we performed MDs on LNPs coated with hydrophilic structures of pEG, poly(2-methyl-2-oxazoline) (pMeOx), poly(2-ethyl-2-oxazoline) (pEtOx) and poly(2methyl-2-oxazine) (pMeOzi), conjugated via a recently reported copper free alkyne-azide coupling reaction (Figure 1B) (42). Both molecular weight (MW)-equivalent lipopolymers and one example of a degree of polymerization (DP)-equivalent structure were compared to pEG chains with 45 units (≈ 2 kDa), as found within Comirnaty®. We dissected in detail how exchanging pEG with these alternative polymers might affect LNP surface properties, thereby providing researchers the necessary molecular insight for rationalizing the choice of polymer excipients used in LNPs. Based on (A-I) molar ratios within Comirnaty® dynamics of (A-II) small periodic patches at neutral and acidic conditions as well as (A-III) full-length, unloaded spherical LNPs were investigated. Upon equilibration of the core-shell structure, (A-IV) insertion of pEG 45 elements showed preferential coverage of hydrophobic aminolipids in the outer monolayer. Systems equilibrated to (A-V) a core composed of cholesterol and aminolipids, and (A-VI) an outer monolayer with DSPC helper lipids, lipopolymers, hydrophobic patches of neutral aminolipids and cholesterol near its solubility limit. (B) In this work, we replaced truncated pEG elements of equilibrated LNPs with alternative lipopolymers conjugated via a triazole linker. For studying the linker effect and using pEG as reference, we also simulated the corresponding pEG-triazole-lipopolymer. Membrane dynamics were further investigated by replacement of full-length ALC-0159 in the (A-II) periodic systems.

To study alternative polymer coatings for LNPs at an atomistic level, we replaced ALC-0159 within equilibrated, unloaded Comirnaty® systems previously obtained by Trollmann and Böckmann (41).

We investigated lipopolymers MW-equivalent to ALC-0159 and composed of pEG, pMeOx, pEtOx or pMeOzi. MW-based comparisons are often performed for polymers (36), however, this results in length-dependent differences for various analyses on a molecular level. Therefore, we additionally investigated a DP (and backbone length)-equivalent variant of pEtOx. Polymers were linked to two carbon chains via a click chemistry-based triazole structure. We recently reported the synthesis of such elements via electron-deficient acetylenedicarboxylate lipids, enabling efficient coupling of various polymer chains end-capped with suitable azide groups (42).

Exchanging ALC-0159 did not affect the overall core-shell structure found in the reference systems: integrated radial distribution function (RDF) curves, counting the absolute number of molecules from the LNP center outwards, were mostly identical for all systems (Figure 2A-I). An increase for shell components was detected in the 15-17 nm region, corresponding to the outer monolayer.

Next, we investigated potential differences in preferential interactions of polymers with the LNPs.

While in Figure 2 we compared SASA contributions between individual components, the coverage of polymers above the different molecule types was analyzed by deriving fractions of buried SASA from calculations with and without polymers (Figure 3). We detected a polymer-dependent surface coverage pattern for the most abundant components ALC-0315 and CHL: pEG showed a slightly higher tendency to cover hydrophobic aminolipids on the outer monolayer, as also reported by Trollmann and Böckmann (Figure 3A). This behavior was less observable for the pOx/pOzi alternatives. Variants with additional backbone or sidechain methylene groups compared to pMeOx showed increased aminolipid coverage, but all values, including for pEtOx 45 , were reduced compared to pEG. In contrast to these findings, the scenario was inversed, and differences more pronounced, for CHL: pEG showed the least coverage (Figure 3B). Interestingly, pMeOzi, a structural isomer to pEtOx, showed similar results to pEtOx in terms of ALC-0315 shielding.

For CHL however, values were more similar to pMeOx, suggesting that preferential coverage of CHL might be more dependent on the pOx/pOzi sidechain topology. Both ALC-0315 and CHL contain a hydroxyl group potentially serving as hydrogen bond (HB) donor. However, the number of HBs established per polymer was insignificant (Figure S1). Still, at relevant distances, RDF curves showed more defined peaks for pOx/pOzi types, containing carbonyl moieties potentially functioning as stronger HB acceptors compared to the ether oxygens of pEG. The latter instead showed a broad, more intense peak at larger distances (0.4-0.6 nm, Figure S1A-I), indicating more unspecific surface coverage and thereby allowing for entropically favorable water expulsion in more distant hydration layers. Interactions at generally smaller distances through pOx/pOzi were also supported by diffusion measurements of lipids, in particular CHL, being more affected compared to pEGylated systems (Figure S2). We visualized our findings by comparison of the coverage of the same hydrophobic aminolipid patches across different types of LNPs (Figure 3C).

These results could allow for different scenarios: on the one hand, a larger solvent-exposure of hydrophobic aminolipid patches may drive forward the subsequent fusion of multiple particles (not modelled in our systems) into larger-sized LNPs until the entire surface is sufficiently shielded. In accordance, the very first reported, recently experimentally characterized LNPs coated with pEtOx showed significantly larger hydrodynamic radii compared to MW-equivalent pEG systems (145 vs. 78 nm for 2 kDa chains, similar to our case) (32). The authors hypothesized differences in pEtOx and pEG lipid interactions which would conform to our observations -still, a more influential factor should be that this pEtOx variant is nearly 2.5 fold shorter in length than pEG. Correspondingly, DP-equivalent pEtOx 45 resulted in smaller particles and was also compared to pEG 45 , pMeOx 45 and pMeOzi 45 variants in another recent study on monoacyl lipopolymers (43). As the authors discussed there, many other size influencing factors such as molar ratio, lipid architecture and lipopolymers retained in solution need to be considered. On the other hand, the different coverage profiles could lead to variations in tissue accumulation due to modulation of the protein corona.

For example, if binding of ApoE to CHL enables targeting of hepatic cells (14), a less selective desolvation of aminolipids for the case of pOx/pOzi alternatives compared to pEG could alter this effect. The reported pEtOxylated LNPs showed delivery to multiple cell types (32). However, binding of serum proteins to the pOx/pOzi surface would in turn also influence tissue targeting.

Future modeling work on protein-lipopolymer interactions could further dissect such events.

Based on water contact angles, hydrophilicity of the investigated pOx/pOzi types increases in the order pEtOzi (39°) &lt; pEtOx (32°) &lt; pMeOzi (20°) &lt; pMeOx (12°), with pEG further being known as slightly less hydrophilic than pMeOx and more hydrophilic than pEtOx. Interestingly, antifouling properties of pOzi types outperformed their pOx counterparts, as recently reported for gold-tethered polymer chains (44,45). A higher backbone flexibility of pMeOzi was believed to result in enhanced hydration. We investigated the amount of nearby water molecules per repeating unit and found an agreement with the recently experimentally determined order of pOx/pOzi hydration for chains with DP = 25 (water molecules per repeating unit based on ellipsometry of swollen layers: pEtOx: 6 ≈ pMeOx: 7 &lt; pMeOzi: 13 ( 45)). Hydration of pEtOx and pMeOx was comparable (Figure 4A), while pEG, addressing the hydrophobic patches of aminolipids on the surface, showed the least amount of water molecules nearby per repeating unit. As described for gold-tethered pMeOzi, higher hydration suggests better shielding from protein adsorption, hence a reduced tendency of protein corona formation on the surfaces of LNPs. Compared to pEtOx, pEtOx 45 showed reduced hydration -as mentioned above, radii of pEtOx 45 were larger (Figure 2B andC). However, we observed that, instead of either enabling a larger coverage of the LNP surface in a linear DP-dependent fashion or becoming increasingly solvent-exposed via extension into the bulk water, these chains showed a higher tendency to &quot;clump&quot; together (Figure 4B). Such cluster formations are similar to our observations from previous modeling works on pEtOxylated liposomal membranes (46) as well as pEtOx-containing gel-forming triblock copolymers (47).

At last, we exchanged lipopolymers within periodic systems to analyze membrane dynamics at neutral and acidic pH. The latter leads to protonation of aminolipids which induces a monolayer-tobilayer phase transition that is believed to be a driving force for endosomal escape after transfection.

Exchanging ALC-0159 molecules with any of the triazole-linked variants resulted in DSPC deuterium order parameters in close accordance with results from Trollmann and Böckmann (Figure 5), indicating very high lipid flexibility at low pH and higher rigidity more similar to DSPC/CHL mixtures at neutral pH. Similar insights are given by membrane bending moduli, derived on the basis of the Helfrich-Canham theory for the systems at acidic pH: all patches showed relatively low moduli compared to binary DSPC/CHL mixtures (Table 1), which indicates high membrane elasticity and was postulated in the reference study to help both encapsulation and release of nucleic acids during formulation and endosomal escape at low pH.

In this work, we investigated at an atomistic level the biocompatible polymers pMeOx, pEtOx and pMeOzi for their applicability as pEG substitutes in LNPs. We modelled polymers conjugated via a recently reported triazole linker (42). Results for pEG were in accordance with previous modeling works of ALC-0159, suggesting desolvation of hydrophobic aminolipid patches. In combination with the analyzed membrane dynamics, these observations suggest that the utilized linker does not significantly alter the polymer's behavior. While we observed no fundamental change in the previously reported core-shell composition, pOx/pOzi alternatives exhibited a distinctly different LNP interaction profile, as they were less likey to preferentially shield solvent-exposed ALC-0315 molecules. Instead, coverage of CHL in the outer monolayer was increased. This could modify the particle size, as previously reported (32), and attract a different subset of proteins onto the LNP surface, ultimately affecting the biological fate in vivo. Exchanging pEtOx with a longer pEtOx 45 DP-equivalent to the pEG counterpart naturally increased also ALC-0315 coverage, however not quite to the same level as pEG. Despite not being the most hydrophilic candidate, pMeOzi showed the highest hydration, which could imply this polymer type to represent the most suitable pEG substitute out of the studied alternatives for decreasing protein adsorption on the LNP surface, similar to previous findings for gold-tethered analogs (45). We anticipate to characterize other polymer types and architectures in silico (e.g. a recently described &quot;super-hydrophilic&quot; poly(2hydroxymethyl-2-oxazoline) ( 48)), as well as study their interaction profiles with serum proteins to be able to assess tissue targeting effects of LNPs from a computational viewpoint.

For modeling of spherical LNPs coated with various polymers, the three available end structures published by Trollmann and Böckmann (41) (simulation lengths: 240, 445 and 456 ns) for the full, unloaded Comirnaty® vaccine, prior to pEGylation, were used as starting point for running three individual replicas per polymer type (Table 2). Solvent was removed and lipids conjugated via a triazole linker with either linear pEG, pMeOx, pEtOx or pMeOzi of the same molecular weight (corresponding to 45, 23, 20 and 20 monomers respectively) were inserted and aligned to the coordinates of the unpEGylated ALC-0159 lipids via PyMOL (49). After alignment, the original ALC-0159 molecules (conjugated with only two EG monomers) were deleted. The resulting structure was then re-solvated with TIP3P water and a sodium chloride concentration of 150 mM, removing all solvent molecules placed within the LNP and keeping a 1.2 nm minimum distance of the solute to the cubic box border. To fix all clashes introduced by insertion of lipopolymers into the equilibrated monolayer, systems were then subjected to multiple short energy minimizations (applying a soft-core potential in the beginning as described in (50)) and simulation runs with 1 fs time steps that were gradually increased to 2 fs. All systems were further investigated for correction of potential ring penetrations of the initally inserted lipids with nearby CHL molecules. Initial equilibration was repeated once upon re-solvation into smaller boxes after polymers condensed onto the surface after several tens of nanoseconds.

In addition to the spherical LNPs, the impact of polymers on dynamics of the bilayer formed at and Böckmann enclosing the hydrophobic lipid core at neutral pH was also modeled analogously after multiplication by 9 along the x-y plane via packmol (51). This was performed to provide a sufficiently large system size for potentially studying interactions with serum proteins in future works.

Following preparation of three replicas per polymer type (systems 1-15, Table 2), each model of a spherical LNP was simulated for around 1000 ns (665 ns in the reference work (41)). After applying the Berendsen thermostat and barostat (52) during multiple short initial equilibration runs of around 10 ns each (see above), a temperature of 310 K and a pressure of 4.5 x 10 -5 bar -1 in the NPT ensemble were applied using the Velocity-rescale thermostat ( 53) and the Parrinello-Rahman barostat (coupling constants of 0.1 and 5.0 ps respectively) (54). 2 fs time steps were used, in conjunction with the LINCS algorithm ( 55) and a treatment of long-range electrostatic interactions via the particle-mesh Ewald method (56). In analogy to Trollmann and Böckmann (41), periodic systems (systems 16-23, Table 2) were simulated for around 1000 ns with the same parameters, except for applying the Nosé-Hoover thermostat with coupling constants of 1.0 ps (57,58). All simulations were performed using GROMACS 2023.1 (59).

In order to continue from the equilibrated end structures used as starting point, parameters for CHL and DSPC were adapted from the newest CHARMM36 force field (July 2022) (60). For neutral and protonated aminolipids as well as all lipopolymers, like Trollmann and Böckmann (41), we adapted parameters via the CGenFF webserver (61,62). For the case of the triazole linker element that contained some dihedral parameters with penalty scores above 50, values were subsequently reassessed by following the force field toolkit (ffTK) workflow within VMD (63,64). Final optimized parameters derived from dihedral scans using second order Møller-Plesset (MP2) perturbation theory with the 6-31G* basis set via Gaussian16 RevC.02 (65) were in agreement with the torsional potential energy surface obtained from quantum-mechanical target data (Figure S3).

Analyses were performed using cpptraj (66) from AmberTools24 (67). Calculation of SASA was done using VMD (68). SASA buried by polymers were investigated by determining the difference in available surface area of individual lipid types between calculations with and without polymers (equation 1). A standard probe radius of 1.4 Å was used.

SASA buried = 100 -SASA LNP with polymer SASA LNP without polymer * 100%

Deuterium order parameters (69) and membrane bending moduli (70) were characterized via MDAnalysis scripts (71,72). Local lipid deuterium order parameters, calculated for each heavy atom in a carbon chain, are defined by the average angle 𝜃 between the C-H bond vectors and the relevant director axis, resembling the bilayer or monolayer normal (equation 2).

The membrane bending modulus can be derived using the Helfrich-Canham theory (73,74). Hereby, the membrane is represented as an elastic sheet determined by the lipid headgroups. Based on membrane undulations, a fast Fourier transformation of the height field ℎ defined by the positions of lipid headgroups in both leaflets can be performed to obtain the power spectrum ⟨|ℎ(𝑞)| 2 ⟩ which is a function of the wave number 𝑞. The corresponding value for the average intensity is correlated to the bending modulus 𝐾 𝐶 which can thus be extracted from a linear fit (equation 3) (41,70).

⟨|ℎ(𝑞)| 2 ⟩ = 𝑘 𝑏 𝑇 𝐾 𝐶 𝑞 4   (3)

Estimates of 𝐾 𝐶 were determined in this work based on linear fits for all 𝑞 values below 0.6 nm -1 , as recommended previously (70). The first 10% of the trajectories were discarded and the remaining simulation time was divided into 10 bins in order to derive mean and standard deviation values.

All time series plots were generated by calculation of rolling means across 40 snapshots. Boxplots contained data from the last 100 ns of each replica of one polymer type combined. RDF curves and mean squared displacements were calculated based on the last trajectory segment, equalling about 40 ns for all simulations. All visualizations were done using VMD 1.9.4 (68).

https://doi.org/10.26434/chemrxiv-2025-v4cjh ORCID: https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5567-7404 Content not peer-reviewed by ChemRxiv. License: CC BY-NC 4.0</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Nat. Rev. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>X Hou</author>
				<author>T Zaks</author>
				<author>R Langer</author>
				<author>Y Dong</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Acc. Chem. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Eygeris</author>
				<author>M Gupta</author>
				<author>J Kim</author>
				<author>G Sahay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2022</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adv. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Jia</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2024</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochimica et Biophysica Acta (BBA) -Biomembranes</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Róg</author>
				<author>M Pasenkiewicz-Gierula</author>
				<author>I Vattulainen</author>
				<author>M Karttunen</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2009</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nanomaterials</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Medjmedj</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2022</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Trends Pharmacol. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Patel</author>
				<author>N Ibrahim</author>
				<author>K Cheng</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Controlled Release</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Chen</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2014</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Polymers</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Pasarin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2023</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adv. Drug Delivery Rev</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Shi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2022</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Int. J. Biochem. Cell Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Zanganeh</author>
				<author>R Spitler</author>
				<author>M Erfanzadeh</author>
				<author>A Alkilany</author>
				<author>M Mahmoudi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>ACS Nano</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Ke</author>
				<author>S Lin</author>
				<author>W Parak</author>
				<author>T Davis</author>
				<author>F Caruso</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nat. Nanotechnol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Wheeler</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nat. Rev. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Mahmoudi</author>
				<author>M Landry</author>
				<author>A Moore</author>
				<author>R Coreas</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2023</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Bioconjugate Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>V Francia</author>
				<author>R Schiffelers</author>
				<author>P Cullis</author>
				<author>D Witzigmann</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2020</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>AIChE J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Russell</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2018</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Prog. Polym. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B Kaupbayeva</author>
				<author>A Russell</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2020</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Int. J. Pharm</title>
			<authors>
				<author>V Makwana</author>
				<author>J Karanjia</author>
				<author>T Haselhorst</author>
				<author>S Anoopkumar-Dukie</author>
				<author>S Rudrawar</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Mol. Pharmaceutics</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Liu</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2020</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Pharm. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Turecek</author>
				<author>M Bossard</author>
				<author>F Schoetens</author>
				<author>I Ivens</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Biomed. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C.-C Lee</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2020</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Commun. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Huckaby</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2020</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Qi</author>
				<author>A Chilkoti</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2015</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Polymers</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Thi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2020</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Bioeng. Transl. Med</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Schlich</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Mol. Pharmaceutics</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Amici</author>
				<author>D Pozzi</author>
				<author>C Marchini</author>
				<author>G Caracciolo</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2023</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adv. Healthcare Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Gomi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2023</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nat. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Liu</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nat. Nanotechnol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Q Cheng</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2020</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nat. Commun</title>
			<authors>
				<author>X Han</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nat. Biomed. Eng</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Lokugamage</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>ACS Appl. Nano Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Nogueira</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2020</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adv. Healthcare Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Da Silva</author>
				<author>Sanchez</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2024</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomaterials</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Lorson</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2018</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Bioconjugate Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Viegas</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2011</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>ACS Biomater. Sci. Eng</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Lühmann</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomacromolecules</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Hauptstein</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Bunker</author>
				<author>A Magarkar</author>
				<author>T Viitala</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Front. Mol. Biosci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Bunker</author>
				<author>T Róg</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2020</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Particuology</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Yuan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2024</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Eur. Phys. J. E</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Settanni</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2023</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biophys. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Trollmann</author>
				<author>R Böckmann</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2022</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>ChemRxiv</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Kaps</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2024</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomacromolecules</title>
			<authors>
				<author>X He</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2024</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Morgese</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2018</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Macromolecular Rapid Communications</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Svoboda</author>
				<author>N Lusiani</author>
				<author>R Sivkova</author>
				<author>O Pop-Georgievski</author>
				<author>O Sedlacek</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2023</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>European Journal of Pharmaceutical Sciences</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Magarkar</author>
				<author>T Róg</author>
				<author>A Bunker</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>ACS Nano</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Hahn</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2023</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. n/a</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Jana</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2024</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>The PyMOL Molecular Graphics System, Version 2.0 Schrödinger</title>
			<authors/>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Chem. Theory Comput</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Boyd</author>
				<author>E May</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2018</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Comput. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Martinez</author>
				<author>R Andrade</author>
				<author>E Birgin</author>
				<author>J Martinez</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2009</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Chem. Phys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Berendsen</author>
				<author>J Postma</author>
				<author>W Van Gunsteren</author>
				<author>A Dinola</author>
				<author>J Haak</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1984</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Chem. Phys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Bussi</author>
				<author>D Donadio</author>
				<author>M Parrinello</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2007</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Appl. Phys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Parrinello</author>
				<author>A Rahman</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1981</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Comput. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B Hess</author>
				<author>H Bekker</author>
				<author>H Berendsen</author>
				<author>J Fraaije</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1998</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>The Journal of Chemical Physics</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Darden</author>
				<author>D York</author>
				<author>L Pedersen</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1993</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Chem. Phys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Nosé</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1984</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Phys. Rev. A</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Hoover</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1985</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>SoftwareX</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Abraham</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2015</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nat. Methods</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Huang</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Vanommeslaeghe</author>
				<author>A Mackerell</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2012</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Chem. Inf. Model</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Vanommeslaeghe</author>
				<author>E Raman</author>
				<author>A Mackerell</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2012</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Comput. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Mayne</author>
				<author>J Saam</author>
				<author>K Schulten</author>
				<author>E Tajkhorshid</author>
				<author>J Gumbart</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Comput. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Pavlova</author>
				<author>J Gumbart</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2015</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Gaussian 16 Rev. C</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Frisch</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Roe</author>
				<author>T Cheatham</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>AMBER 2024</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Case</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2024</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Mol. Graphics</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Humphrey</author>
				<author>A Dalke</author>
				<author>K Schulten</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1996</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Chem. Theory Comput</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Melcr</author>
				<author>T Ferreira</author>
				<author>P Jungwirth</author>
				<author>O Ollila</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2020</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Soft Matter</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Fowler</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Journal of Computational Chemistry</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Michaud-Agrawal</author>
				<author>E Denning</author>
				<author>T Woolf</author>
				<author>O Beckstein</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2011</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Python in Science Conference</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Gowers</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Theor. Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Canham</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1970</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Zeitschrift für Naturforschung C</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Helfrich</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1973</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
</document>
