<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Differential adsorption and chemical affinities of proteins for apatitic surfaces.pdf</file>
	<title>Differential Adsorption and Chemical Affinities of Proteins for Apatitic Surfaces</title>
	<date>1979</date>
	<doi_number>10.1177/00220345790580024701</doi_number>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Differential adsorption and chemical affinities of proteins for apatitic surfaces.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>D.I. Hay</author>
		<author>E.C. Moreno</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>Studies are reviewed which identify the interacting groups involved in protein adsorption onto hydroxyapatite. Thus, carboxyl and phosphoester groups bind to calcium sites in the adsorbent, and basic groups bind to phosphate sites. Detailed adsorption studies have been performed to quantitate some of these interactions. An adsorption model, based on the Langmuir adsorption isotherm, adequately fitted the data from experiments using selected amino acids, bovine albumin and two human salivary proteins. Adsorption parameters (afffnities and maximum number of sites) were obtained for several apatitic adsorbents, with affinities increasing considerably in the series hydroxy- (HA), fluorhydroxy- (FHA) and fluor-apatite (FA). A modest increase in the number of sites was also noted. The change in adsorption behavior, with increasing fluoride content, was attributed to a reduction in the surface free energy of the adsorbent, with a concomitant decrease in the interaction of the adsorbent with water, and a consequent enhancement of the adsorption bond. It is suggested that this effect may play a role in the cariostatic effect of fluoride. Unusual structural aspects of the salivary proteins are discussed in relation to their adsorption behavior, and the molecular segments responsible for binding to the adsorbent tentatively identified.</abstract>
	<methods/>
	<full_text>of these macromolecule/mineral interactions, however, is not clearly understood. Similarly, although chromatography on HA columns has been extensively used to purify macro- molecules1, the basis for the separations obtained is unclear, and the chromatographic behavior of proteins correlates poorly with their molecular properties2. Studies of a phosphoprotein from den- tin3 have shown it to affect the crystal- linity of calcium phosphate precipitates4, and phosphoproteins from saliva have been shown to inhibit spontaneous and m solutions super- to calcium phosthe mechanisms not yet understood. e a particular bear- vhich occur between Uvary proteins, to rment of the tooth tailed mechanisms forms are unknown. have been taken ature of the reactive interactions9'10'l11 ctual measurements of selected amino acules13'14 for HA ose of this paper is from studies dealing )etween macromolephate salts, and to present knowledge nteractions relevant 4 e 4 i,ature OI tne aasorpuon centers oI proteins and HA.

Early studies failed to yield correlations between the chromatographic behavior of proteins on HA columns, and their mole- cular properties such as net charge, pro- portions of acidic and basic amino acids, isoelectric points or molecular size2. A single exception was the finding9 that the presence of ester phosphate groups resulted in exceptionally strong binding of proteins to HA during chromatography, buffers of relatively high molarity being required for the elution of phosphoproteins. A later systematic studyl of synthetic polymers of amino acids showed the im- portance of free carboxyl groups. Thus, homo and heteropolymers containing as- partate and glutamate residues required buffer concentrations for elution in approxi- mate proportion to their dicarboxylic amino acid content, whereas polymers lacking these residues, or where the carboxyl groups VoL

were esterified, were not retarded during chromatography. It was concluded that the mechanism of carboxyl and phosphoester binding to HA was by a direct interaction between calcium ions on the HA surface and the anionic groups in the macromolecule10. It was also argued that elution occurred as a consequence of displacement of the binding anionic group from the adsorption site, by the eluting buffer anions, and that ionic strength effects played minor roles. Thus, the elution of polyglutamate, by means of a phosphate gradient, occurred at the same phosphate concentration both in the presence, and absence, of IM KC1.

A subsequent report1t showed that basic residues also interact with HA, thus correcting a previous negative conclusion10. In fact poly(L-lysine), poly(L-arginine) and poly(L-ornithine), having molecular weights of 7,000 or greater, could not be eluted using 1M potassium phosphate, but were eluted by higher concentrations of monovalent electrolytes, with the cation being the active eluting species and the anions having little effect. Since basic polymers were relatively easily eluted by low concentrations of divalent cations, calcium and magnesium being almost equally effective, it was concluded that basic residues interacted with phosphate sites on the HA surface, from which they could be competitively displaced by high concentrations of monovalent cations, or, more effectively, by much lower concentrations of divalent cations; hence, adsorption is electrostatic in nature.

The behavior of native proteins10'll appears in most cases to be qualitatively understandable in terms of the foregoing generalizations. Accurate quantitative predic- tions, however, appear to be difficult to make, and many exceptions and anomalies occur. This seems consistent with the likeli- hood that behavior of the macromolecules will be strongly influenced by their second- ary and tertiary structures. Thus, polygluta- mate showed the same chromatographic behavior in the absence and presence of 8M urea. Native proteins, on the other hand, behaved quite differently after dena- turationll. Lysozyme, ribonuclease and cytochrome C in 8M urea were either not retarded on HA columns, or were eluted more easily than the native proteins. Tropocollagen, denatured by heating, gave products in which the proportion of non-retarded material increased with increasing tempera- ture, and in which the retarded constitu- ents required buffers of progressively lower molarities for elution. These results were explained in terms of clusters of charged residues on the surface of the native molecule, thus increasing the probability of binding, with this conformation being lost on denaturation.

Further evidence supporting the concept of interactions between phosphate and car- boxylate ions and calcium ion sites, and interactions between amino and guanidin- ium groups and phosphate sites in HA, has come from electron spin resonance studies of calcium phosphate-macromolecule co-precipitates 5,16. Using vanadyl ions as reporter groups for calcium ion interactions, and x-rradiation at low temp- eratures, followed by measurement of spin energy transfer between macromolecule and mineral led to confirmation of carboxylate ion and phosphoester-calcium ion inter- actions, and guanidinium and amino group- phosphate ion interactions, among others.

Adsorption model: studies of adsorp- tion of selected amino acids.

The foregoing studies yielded important qualitative information about the nature of the interacting groups, but the strength of an interaction could only be described quantitatively in arbitrary terms, such as the buffer concentration required for the elution of a particular macromolecule. While this enabled distinctions to be made between the strong interactions occurring between phosphoester groups and HA, and the relatively weakerinteractions of carboxyl and basic groups, classical techniques, e.g., adsorption isotherms, for quantitatively describing such interactions were only recently applied to this problem. Interpreta- tion of macromolecule adsorption isotherms and the elucidation of the adsorption mechanisms in physical/chemical terms are, however, exceptionally complex problems. Since several different functional groups of the macromolecule may be involved, and at least two possible adsorption sites exist on the apatite surface, simple compounds were chosen for initial studies12, in which only a limited number of functional groups could be involved. Adsorption isotherms were obtained for aspartic, glutamic, DL- ae-aminoadipic, DL-a-aminopimelic, succinic ing model geometry and molecular dimen- and adipic acids and arginine, by measure-sions were used to calculate the number of ment of the amount adsorbed per gram of sites available for each of the acids. The re- hydroxyapatite, Q (,M/g), at various equili-sults of this calculation, shown in Table I, brium concentrations, C (,M/ml). The gave a rather satisfactory matching consider- results were compatible with an adsorption ing uncertainties inherent in the assumptions model which closely matched the Langmuir which were made. In spite of this agreement, adsorption isotherm17,18, i.e, caution is still required in accepting its validity. Small, but significant deviations C = L + C * * * * [1] from predicted behavior were noted. Thus, Q KN N at high adsorbate concentrations, the isotherms of aspartic acid and glutamic

where N is the number of adsorption sites acid deviated slightly from predicted beha- per gram of adsorbent and K is a parameter, vior. This anomaly was explained in terms usually termed the affinity constant, which of a small degree of inhomogeneity of the reflects the strength of the bond between adsorbent surface, with the possible conse- the adsorbate molecules and the adsorption quence that all adsorption sites were not sites. In cases where comparison of dif-isoenergetic, so violating a requirement for ferent adsorbents is required, Q is expressed Eq.[11. However, if the results for the in terms of adsorbed solute per unit surface amount adsorbed at the low concentration area.

range of the isotherm (Q), are normalized In agreement with this model, plots of with respect to the number of adsorption C/Q against C gave straight lines, shown sites (N), and the resulting values of Q/N in Figure 1. From the slopes and intercepts (i.e. the fractional number of sites occupied of these were calculated values for the by adsorbate molecules) plotted against number of adsorption sites, N, and the the corresponding equilibrium concentraaffinity constants, K. These adsorption tions, all the points describe the same parameters, listed in Table 1, lead to several function, with the possible exception of interesting conclusions. Thus, the adsorpaminopimelic acid12. This indicates that tion affinities of the ce-amino acids are very the adsorption of all the molecules involves similar, indicating that the same functional the same energy levels, and that the ad- groups in the amino acid, and similar sites in sorption differences between the individual the adsorbent, are involved in the adsorp-members of the series are simply due to tion phenomenon. It is reasonable to ident-differences in availability of adsorption sites, ify the terminal carboxyls of the adsorbates, which appear to be dictated by geometric and calcium ions in the adsorbent surface, considerations.

as the reactive entities. The number of A further anomaly was that coverage of sites decreases, in a systematic way, with the adsorbent surface, by the adsorbates increasing molecular size. Based on the tested, was low compared to the apparently reported geometry20 of aspartic and glu-available surface, determined by nitrogen tamic acid molecules, and taking into adsorption. At least two factors may contri- account the crystallographic characteristics bute to this discrepancy. First, nitrogen and geometry of the HA crystals, it was molecules would have easier access to possible to develop a geometric model for surfaces, e.g. interstices and defects from the adsorption of the acids tested. A model which larger molecules would be excluded. in which the long axes of the molecule Second, there are probably vacancies at are arranged perpendicularly or horizontally calcium sites. Treatment of the adsorbent to the surface was not compatible with the with calcium chloride substantially increased experimental data. Rather, the data matched adsorption of aspartic acid (Table 1). Sim- a model where the molecules are anchored ilarly, adsorption of arginine is undetectable, by their terminal carboxyl groups, and are unless the adsorbent is first treated with inclined at an angle to the surface. Rotation phosphate, suggesting the presence of va- of the molecule generates a cone, and its cancies (or defects) in the crystal surface. projection onto the surface defines the Non-specific enrichment of the surface, extent of the adsorption site. An angle however, unrelated to filling vacancies, of 550 was adopted for aspartic acid, and would also be consistent with the results 400 for the other molecules, and the result-obtained. It seemed significant that the proposed adsorption model was also able to accom- modate two dicarboxylic acids (Table 1). The affinity constants are substantially higher, consistent with the higher probabil- ity for adsorption since the two carboxyl groups are equivalent, and good agreement was obtained between the experimentally determined number of sites, and the value predicted from the respective models.

Although the foregoing model for amino acid adsorption onto HA is still capable of further refinement, the agreement between the model and experimbntal data and the predictive value of the geometric model suggests that a relatively good understanding of the system has been obtained. The small deviations from predicted behavior, noted above, do not significantly impair the model; rather they indicate the value of using well-characterized, highly-purified sim- ple compounds as probes to investigate and characterize the HA crystal surface. This kind of preliminary study seemed a necessary step before embarking on similar studies using complex macromolecules, the results of which are not so amenable to the kind of detailed analysis described above.

Significance of selected macromole- cule/mineral interactions.

Although numerous biological systems exist in which macromolecule/HA inter- actions occur, few studies have been concerned with the interactions between the individual purified macromolecules, and well- characterized apatitic minerals. One system, for which some relevant studies have been performed, is the human tooth-saliva inter- face. The enamel surface, when exposed to saliva, acquires a well-defined integu-ment7'8'20, usually termed the acquired enamel pellicle2l. Histologically, the 0.1-1.0,m thick pellicle22 generally lacks structure, though older pellicles may possess a banded appearance. Analytical studies23'24 suggest that it forms from salivary pro- teins by a selective adsorption process, this being consistent with the observed selective adsorption of salivary proteins onto HA from in vitro systems25,26,27,28. The pellicle is biologically significant in that it strongly affects the initial attachment of microorganisms to the tooth sur- face29'30'3' and remains interposed between (M/ mi) Fig. 1 -Adsorption isotherms plotted accord- ingto Eq. [11].

the enamel and dental plaque. It reduces the extent of demineralization of enamel, both by acidic buffers32'33'34 and cario- genic microorganisms in vitro35. This may be the basis of its proposed ability to re- duce the severity of carious attack36'37 in vivo. Recently it has been suggested that the pellicle may have a further property in that some of its constituents block nucleation sites on the enamel sur- face, and so prevent the formation of unwanted mineral accretions on the teeth from the saliva, which is normally super- saturated with respect to the enamel min- eral38. These properties, both biologically interesting, and important for health reasons, have led to systematic studies of the inter- actions between salivary proteins and apatitic minerals. A particular area of interest is the possibility of different adsorp- tion behavior onto HA, FHA, and FA, differences which may affect the nature of the pellicle and contribute to the caries- reducing properties of fluoride.

Clearly, a 0.1-1.0,m thick pellicle is able to accommodate many layers of protein molecules. Most attention has been focused, however, on the possible specificity of proteins which may form the first monolayer on the apatite surface. This specificity could be determined by selective adsorption onto the mineral surface. Experiments specifically designed to reveal selective adsorption effects39A40 have identified several &quot;apatitereactive&quot; proteins. Thus, by equilibrat- ing different amounts of adsorbent with constant amounts of saliva, it was possible to determine the mineral/saliva ratio at which only a single constituent adsorbed40. This was identified as an unusual tyrosinerich phosphopeptide4l, which has been named statherin, the complete primary structure of which was recently reported6. This peptide could be nearly completely adsorbed from glandular salivas before significant adsorption of other con- stituents occurred. As statherin was depleted from solution, a histidine-rich phosphopeptide was next removed42, this being followed by the adsorption of a group of four unusual proline-rich phosphopro-teins43A445, partial sequences of which have recently been reported46A47. In parallel with the adsorption of these acidic macromolecules were adsorbed small amounts of a low molecular weight basic peptide, though whether this was a specific effect has yet to be determined. This com- bination of well-defined selective adsorption, progress in determining the molecular structure of the adsorbates6A6A7, and the detailed adsorption studies which have been conducted13'14, make this system parti- cularly amenable to analysis. An additional aspect of these studies was the discovery that statherin and the proline-rich proteins possessed the unusual ability to modify the solution and solid phase pro-perties of calcium phosphates. Thus the proline-rich proteins and statherin were found to be effective inhibitors of both seeded precipitation59 and of the reactions leading to the transformation of acidic salts, such as dicalcium phosphate dihydrate, to basic calcium phosphates48. In addition, statherin was shown to be a particularly potent inhibitor of precipitation from solutions which are strongly supersaturated with respect to calcium phosphate salts5S49. It seems that the inhibi- tory activities of these proteins, and their selective adsorption behavior, are likely to have similar bases, perhaps in some feature of their molecular structure. Also, since these effects clearly depend on interactions between a variety of calcium phosphate surfaces, and the macromolecules concerned, a systematic study of adsorption of the macromolecules onto well-defmed calcium phosphate surfaces would be expected to reveal important details of the interactions involved.

Adsorption studies of bovine serum albumin, statherin and one of the proline-nch proteins, PRP-343, and a specific molecular segment obtained by tryptic digestion have recently been obtained57. Essential prerequisites for these studies are pure, well-characterized adsorbents, purified mac- romolecules, and measurements made at the equilibrium state. The preparation of pure, 934

well-crystallized HA, FA and a series of fluorhydroxyapatites has been reported previously50. In the studies to be con- sidered, two FHA preparations (13 and 41% substitution of OH-by F-) were used. The adsorbents were all extensively characterized14. Under the polarizing mic- roscope, all four apatites appeared mostly as rosettes formed by acicular crystals about 3-6,m long by about 2-3,um thick. Some crystals ranged up to 10-15,m long by 5-7gm thick. The crystals displayed parallel extinction and had a mean index of refraction (white radiation, 250C) of 1.636± 0.002. The x-ray diffraction patterns for all four samples were sharp and characteristic of calcium apatites and the a and c crystallographic parameters for HA and FA, determined from the spectra50, agreed well with the literature values51'52.

Other analytical data and surface areas have been reported14.

The adsorbents were all well-purified proteins. These were a crystalline bovine serum albumin, a highly purified preparation of statherin6, shown to be pure by elec- trophoretic, immunochemical, amino-ter- minal and chromatographic analyses, and proline-rich proteins 1 and 343 which were similarly characterized except that no immunochemical analyses were performed.

Two steps were taken to ensure that measurements were made under conditions as close to equilibrium as practically possible. First, the solvent (0.05M NaC1) was sat- urated with respect to adsorbent before addition of the adsorbate. Second, time courses of adsorption were obtained to determine the time required for the ad- sorption process to reach equilibrium, so determining the experimentally-used equilibrium time. There were two reasons for using O.05M NaCl as solvent; first, it approximated the ionic strength of saliva, and second, it was required to maintain statherin in solution at the desired concen- trations, this macromolecule being less soluble in water than in the dilute electro- lyte solution. The experimental system used for the salivary proteins consisted, therefore, of a series of accurately weighed samples of the mineral adsorbates, preequilibrated with solvent (20 hr), to which appropriate samples of adsorbate were added. Further equilibration (4 hr) was performed before the concentration of adsorbate remaining in solution was deter- mined, and the adsorption isotherms ob- tained, as described above for the amino acids.

Initial adsorption studies, using bovine serum albumin and aspartic acid1 3, were conducted for two reasons. First, it was necessary to test the experimental system using a protein, and so determine if the approach, successfully used for amino acids, was suitable for examining macromolecules.

The second reason was to conduct experiments using an available well-defined macro- molecule and an amino acid, to determine if differences in adsorption behavior existed between HA, FHA and FA for small and more complex molecules. Such preliminary experiments seemed necessary, before em- barking on studies requiring large amounts of purified salivary proteins.

Plots of C/Q vs. C for the two adsorbates gave linear relationships13. The linearity of the plots extends the validity of this model to the adsorption of aspartic acid onto FHA and FA, and shows its validity for the adsorption of bovine albumin onto all three adsorbents. The greater scatter of the points for the protein presumably reflects the greater analytical difficulties involved in determining protein concentrations. The adsorption parameters, K and N, calculated from the linear plots are given in Table 2.

In general terms, the presence of fluoride as a lattice constituent increases both the maximum number of sites, N, and the affinity, K, for the two molecules tested.

The observed increase in the value of N may be related to better crystallinity, with increasing fluoride content, possibly result- ing in fewer calcium vacancies at the crystal surface, with a concomitant increase in number of sites. The data, however, strongly indicate that the fluoride itself is contribut- ing to the increase in the number of sites, and to the strength of the adsorption bond. Conceivably, the enhancement in adsorption may involve an interaction between fluoride sites and the amino group of aspartic acid, either alone, or in conjunction with a calcium-carboxyl bond. Bovine albumin, as with aspartic acid, shows an increase in the number of sites with increasing fluoridation, and a substantial increase in affinity. There seems, however, to be an upper limit for this increase, at least for bovine albumin. A possible explanation may be that fluoride contributes to albumin attachment by the possible increase in calcium sites, noted above, and by providing negative fluoride attachment centers for basic groups in the molecule. At high surface fluoride contents, however, this effect may be negated by an increased electrostatic repulsion of the pre- dominately negatively-charged albumin molecule. In any case, this effect has been seen only with bovine albumin, and does not occur with the salivary proteins, dis- cussed below. Thus, specific structural features of the albumin molecule may be responsible for the observed behavior.

Studies using human salivary sta- therin and proline-rich proteins.

The foregoing studies validated the ex- perimental approach, and the proposed adsorption model revealed significant dif- ferences between the properties of the adsorbents, and led to a detailed study of the adsorption behavior of two salivary proteins on the same adsorbents14. As with the previous studies, plots of C/Q vs.

C for statherin and PRP-3 were linear, so confirming the validity of the model for these proteins. Numerical values of K and N, calculated from the slopes and intercepts of the isotherms, are given in Table 3. The affinities of statherin for the adsorbents tested are less than one-half the corresponding values for PRP-3. For both proteins, the affinities increase markedly with an increas- ing fluoride content in the lattice, with the five-fold increase in affinity for PRP-3 being particularly striking. The maximum number of adsorption sites, N, for statherin is more than double the corresponding value for PRP-3. Only a modest increase in the number of sites was obtained for both adsorbates, with increasing fluoride content. It is also noteworthy that quite low levels of fluoride in the lattice (13% F-sites, equivalent to 4,400 ppm F-) markedly affect the extent of site occupancy.

It seems very significant that all adsor- bents tested show a greater affinity for fluoride-containing apatites than for HA.

Vol. 58 (B) This seems to be a generalized phenomenon for small (aspartate) and large (albumin) molecules. A probable explanation for this behavior is that the experimental isotherms reported here are composite iso-therms53'54'55, i.e. they represent the net result of the competitive adsorption of the solute and its solvent onto the same surface. In all probability, both adsorbate and solvent molecules are adsorbed at equilibrium, and the presence of the solvent molecules weakens the bond, presumably electrostatic, between the adsorbate mole- cules and the adsorption sites on the surface of the adsorbent. Incorporation of fluoride into the apatite lattice, or into the surface of HA adsorbents, results in a solid with a lower surface energy and, therefore, the interaction -with water should be weaker, as indeed has been found experimental-ly56. Thus the interaction between adsor- bate and the adsorption site will be aug- mented.

This concept was tested further by determining the adsorption isotherms of statherin on HA and FA in the presence of 1 0-3M NaF. The adsorption parameters are shown in Table 3. Clearly the presence of fluoride dramatically increases the affinity of statherin for HA, without affecting the number of sites. An increase was also noted for FA, though this was relatively smaller.

The low activities of Ca+' and F-in solution precluded the formation of CaF2; thus, it must be concluded that the adsor- bent surfaces were substantially changed without affecting the basic apatitic struc- ture. The most plausible explanation is that F-exchanges for OH-, decreasing the affinity of the adsorbent for water, and so increasing the strength of the adsorption bond. Undoubtedly, other factors are operating as well, otherwise the affinity of statherin for HA, in the presence of 10-3M NaF, should not be greater than its affinity for FA. The observed enhancement, however, may be explained, at least partly, by the presence of defects or vacancies which differ in the two adsorbents. The results also suggest that the FA, suspended in aqueous solutions, may contain fluoride positions occupied by hydroxyls which are displaced by fluoride ions from the solution, so enhancing the bond strength.

The adsorption experiments described above employed well-crystallized and thoroughly characterized adsorbents, highly purified adsorbates and an experimental system in which measurements were made as close to the equilibrium state as practically possible. The results clearly show that the presence of fluoride in the apatite lattice leads to a substantial increase in the strength of the adsorption bond, and to a small, but distinct, increase in the number of adsorption sites. These conclusions may appear to contradict those obtained in previous studies60'61 '62'63 where apatitic adsorbents, treated with fluoride, appeared to possess a lowered capacity for adsorbing various proteins. Some of the reasons underlying these apparent dis- agreements have already been critically examined 13,64. Generally, the adsorbents have not been well-defined, either in terms of surface area, or quality of their apatitic structure (stoichiometries resulting in Ca/P=1.5, rather than 1.67). In these studies, it was not intended that measurements would be made close to, or even approaching, equilibrium conditions. One other reason for disagreement centers on the possible modification of the surface of the adsor- bents. In studies reviewed here13'14, the adsorption of albumin and statherin onto HA and FA was examined in the presence and absence of 10-3M NaF. The ionic activity product for CaF2 in the experimental system was calculated to be 1.85xl10-1, compared to the solubility product of CaF2, 3.58x10-11. Thus, the system was half saturated with respect to CaF2, so precluding the formation of this salt on the adsorbent surface. A contrary situation exists in a study where HA was treated with the same concentration of NaF, but at a lower ionic strength63. The reduction of the modifying effect of the electrolyte on ionic activities would lead to the solubility product of CaF2 being exceeded, with the virtually inevitable formation of this salt on the adsorbent surface, and a consequent change in adsorp- tion properties.

A further adsorption parameter is the actual surface coverage (as opposed to site occupancy) of the adsorbent surface.

Calculation of molecular dimensions of adsorbed molecules, however, involves as- sumptions regarding both the shape and the orientation of non-spherical adsorbed mole- cules. Although reasonable coverages were calculated, and explanations developed for the deviations observed, definitive conclu-sions regarding coverages require more information regarding molecular structure and shape. This problem will be considered further below.

Adsorption and molecular structure.

It should be possible, ultimately, to define the reactive groups of molecular segments which mediate attachment of macromolecules to the apatitic adsorbents. A prerequisite here is knowledge of the primary structure of the molecule, with an understanding of the secondary and tertiary structures also being important in most cases. The complete primary structure of statherin is known6, the structures of PRP-1 and 3 nearly completed46'47 and the structures of important segments of PRP-2 and 4 determined47. Studies aimed at identification of the binding sites in sta- therin and the proline-rich proteins have only recently begun. Thus, removal of phos- phate from PRP-1 decreased its ability to bind to HA46. Also, it was possible to adsorb a reactive fragment from a tryptic digest of PRP-1 onto HA, the amino acid composition of which corresponded to the amino-terminal fragment46. A more speci- fic study57 led to the measurement of the adsorption affinity of this fragment, this being described below. More informa- tion about possible binding sites has come from studies of these proteins, and specific fragments obtained by enzymatic cleavage, with respect to their ability to inhibit precipitation from solutions supersaturated with respect to calcium phosphate salts. It seems almost certain that the molecular segments responsible for this inhibitory activity, and for binding to apatitic surfaces, will be the same.

Statherin has an unusual structure, the first 20 residues of this 43 residue peptide being: Ten of the twelve charge centers present occur in the first 13 residues, the remain- ing 30 residues being essentially uncharged.

A series of fragments obtained by enzymatic cleavage (1-18, clostridiopeptidase A; 1-9, clostridiopeptidase B; 1-7, chymotrypsin; 1-6, trypsin) possessed similar inhibitory activities in a standard assay system58

suggesting an important role for the seg- ment ASP-PSE-PSE-GLU-GLU-LYS. Re- moval of phosphate from the two phosphoserines (residues 2 and 3), using an alkaline phosphatase, abolished the activity, indi- cating a critical role for these vicinal phosphoserine residues. A similar result was obtained from studies of the proline-rich proteins. Amino-terminal tryptic fragments obtained from PRP-1 and 3 have the following identical structures,while the correspond- ing fragments from 1 5 PCA-ASP-LEU-ASN-GLU-ASP-VAL-PSE- 10 15 GLN-GLU-ASP-VAL-PRO-LEU-VAL-ILE-20 SER-ASP-GLY-GLY-PSE-ASP-GLU-GLN- 25 30 PHE-ILE-ASP-GLU-GLU-ARG-PRP-2 and 4, which are genetically distinct proteins from PRP-1 and 3, differ in small ways, residue 4, for instance, being ASP in PRP-2 and 447. As with statherin, the amino-terminal tryptic fragment contains both of the phosphoserine residues, and almost all of the anionic residues present in these proteins. This fragment is also the only one to possess inhibitory activity, from which, as with statherin, activity is lost on removal of phosphate from the phospho- serines. Unlike statherin, the phosphoserines, at residues 8 and 21, are well separated, suggesting that they may act independently, but cleavage of the active fragment with thermolysin (presumed to yield the separate phosphopeptides, residues 7-11 and 16-25)  diminished inhibitory activity to a very low level, suggesting possible cooperation be- tween these residues in the parent molecule. Measurement of the adsorption affinities of PRP-1, its active amino-terminal tryptic fragment and PRP-3 gave values (24,800, 25,300 and 26,000 respectively) which were the same within expenrmental error.

All these results, taken together, essentially confirm that the segment responsible for 938

mediating adsorption, and for inhibitory activity, lies within the first 30 residues of these molecules. The studies reviewed here were selected for their contribution to an understanding of the interactions occurring between macro- molecules and apatitic adsorbents. Information relevant to this problem has come from chromatographic9%10'11 and physical chemical studies12'13'14. The latter in- vestigations were aimed at gaining an under- standing of a specific system, i.e., the first steps in the formation of the ac- quired enamel pellicle, and the investi- gation of the effect of fluoride on the processes involved. The marked effect of fluoride on adsorption has interesting implications, since the pellicle is known to confer protection against demineralization35, presumably because of its permselective properties33. Pellicles formed on fluoride- rich tooth surfaces may well differ in these properties, with these differences contributing to the cariostatic effect of fluoride. The methods and results of the reviewed studies also have relevance to the interactions occurring in mineralized tissues, both during and after mineralization. Thus, the properties and effects of the dentin phosphoproteins3A4 have clear parallels with the effects caused by the salivary phosphoproteins5,6. In spite of these simi- larities, caution should be exercised in attempts to interpret the complex macromolecule/mineral relationships of mineralized tissues, formed under cellular control, in the simple physical chemical terms described above.

Dr. Arends: Could you tell a little bit about the substrates you used, I mean the BET values, particle size and the pretreat- ment you gave before you started the adsorption procedure? Dr. Hay: The adsorbents were prepared by Dr. Moreno, who is better able to answer your question.

Dr. Moreno: These apatites were prepared by a very slow precipitation process that takes about eight days, at boiling tempera- ture and high pH in order to minimize for- mation of more acid phosphates. The optical properties correspond to those of homo- geneous apatites. The x-ray diffraction patterns do not show any extraneous mater- ials, and the unit cell parameters calculated from the spectra of hydroxyand fluor- apatite check with the values reported by other investigators. The preparations show a distribution in the crystal size with a maximum length of about 15 um and 2-3 um in width down to lengths of 3-5 um and widths of 1-2 um.

Dr. Arends: And the BET value? Dr. Moreno: The BET value changes with the fluoride content of the apatite. For pure hydroxyapatite, the specific surface area is in the order of 12 m2/g whereas for fluorapatite, it is in the order of 6m2/g. Vol. 58(B) Dr. Arends: Do you have any indication of the presence of acid phosphate groups, on the surface or in the material? Dr. Moreno: No, we don't. Dr. Nancollas: It always amazes me that the Langmuir isotherm can be applied to so many systems. We began using it about 1953 for the adsorption of molecules on crystals, which, of course, have a very large number of imperfections. You would not expect an isotherm, which assumes homogeneity of sites to work. In the adsorp- tion of the carboxylates on apatite, I could not see whether the order follows the relative solubilities of the calcium salts or the dissociation constants of the calcium ion pairs. Dr. Hay: We have not attempted to es- tablish if adsorption behavior correlates with other molecular parameters. All we can say at the moment -is that the affinity constants vary only slightly within a series, and this variation may possibly correlate with other variables.

Dr. Gedalia: Both Dr. Hay's and Dr. Moreno's studies have far-reaching clinical implications. I would like to ask a question regarding topical application of fluoride. We are always instructed to remove the pellicle or to remove some microns of the surface enamel before fluoride application is carried out. But, I don't know if this is the right thing to do, if the pellicle protects the enamel. I know that some scientists have recommended that it should not be removed prior to application of a topical fluoride. I would like to know your opinion about it.

Dr. Hay: I think that the important point here is that the pellicle does re-form quite quickly on enamel surface after abrasive or acid treatments. For instance, a protein film, with the characteristic amino-acid composition of pellicle, is formed within two hours, in vivo, after abrasive treatment. There are longer term effects, such as those described by Dr. Moreno, where it takes seven days before the pellicle will provide the maximum protection against deminerali- zation. My answer to your question is that although some clinical treatments remove pellicle, it does re-form quite quickly and I don't think that its temporary loss would be particularly harmful.

Dr. Bell: I'd like to make one comment and then I have a question. I was pleased to hear that you pre-equilibrate the apatite prior to doing these studies. I think this is particularly important. As many of you are aware, the apatite surface can absorb many species, particularly calcium and phosphorus, and the surface charge will change dramatic- ally depending on pretreatment. It is impor- tant, in any adsorption work, that you characterize the surface prior to the study, so that you know what that surface looks like, e.g., you know what charge it has. A question in relation to the affinity constant of statherin on hydroxyapatite: I think it was 11 in the absence of fluoride, and 124 in the presence of 10-3M fluoride and that you interpreted that as the fluoride replacing hydroxyl. In essence you end up with a fluorapatite surface. But, the affinity constant of the molecule on fluorapatite was only 34 compared with 124 for hydroxy- apatite in sodium fluoride. Can you give an explanation for that?

Dr. Hay: As I said in the paper, we would not have expected the affinity constant of statherin on HA, in the presence of 10-3M fluoride, to be greater than the value for FA, under the same conditions (Table 3). I have no explanation for the higher value for HA in the presence of fluoride, but perhaps Dr. Moreno might like to comment.

Dr. Moreno: Dr. Bell, I am not sure I followed what you said. Are you referring to the fact that adsorption onto fluorapatite in the presence of fluoride in solution was higher than in the absence of this elec- trolyte? Yes, this seems to indicate that with the crystals of fluorapatite suspended in an aqueous solution, you do not have a uniformally fluoridated surface but some hydroxyl groups may also be present. The fluoride in solution apparently makes the crystal surfaces more uniform as far as the fluoride is concerned and the adsorption characteristics for the protein are conse- quently changed.

Dr. Bell: Just to follow that up, was the ionic strength the same, when you added the 1O-3M sodium fluoride? Did you, in fact, change the ionic strength?

Dr. Hay: I should have mentioned that the protein adsorption experiments were done in O.05M sodium chloride which was required to keep statherin in solution. We did not compensate for the addition of the fluoride, but I think that you will agree that this small change in ionic strength would have little effect.

Dr. Gray: A question on the mechanism by which statherin might be preventing precipitation of calcium phosphate: Do you think statherin acts by complexing or reacting with the calcium and the phosphate or do you think it might be inhibiting crystal growth analogous to the diphosphonates?

Dr. Hay: First of all, statherin, at a concentration of 1,M, inhibits precipitation from solutions having calcium and phosphate concentrations of 4mM and 10mM respectively. Complexing of calcium or phosphate, with a consequent reduction of ion activities, as a mechanism of action, is therefore hardly possible, since enormous amounts of either of the ions would have to be bound by the proteins to significantly reduce activities. Our data suggest that the mechanism by which statherin acts is rather similar to that proposed for other inhibitors of calcium phosphate precipitation, such as pyrophosphate and diphosphonates. Here, binding of the inhibitors to nuclei or to seed crystal surfaces is considered to block growth sites and so delay precipitation.

Our recent work has shown that the molecular segment of statherin, which is responsible for inhibitory activity in seeded systems, is the amino-terminal hexapeptide, which contains two vicinal phosphoserines and other negatively charged residues. Interestingly, although this fragment is more active than the parent molecule in seeded systems, it is very much less active than the parent molecule in systems where precipitation is initiated by homogeneous nucleation. This suggests an important function for the relatively uncharged carboxy-terminal segment of the molecule.

Dr. Ingram: I really have two questions. Did you in fact, determine the Ca/P ratio of the apatite which you prepared? And have you tried to treat the material with very dilute pyrophosphate, perhaps five or six micromolar? I would be interested to know whether this can compete for the potential sites for your statherin.

Dr. Hay: First, the Ca/P ratio was 1.67. Second, we intend to study this kind of competitive adsorption, but we don't have any data yet.

*Aspaitic acid was used as the reference molecule for calculating the remaining values of N for the geometic model.

by Sheraz Ahmad on July 19, 2014 For personal use only. No other uses without permission. jdr.sagepub.com Downloaded from</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Arch. Biochem. Biophys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Tiselius</author>
				<author>S Hjerten</author>
				<author>O Levin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1956</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Methods in Enzymology</title>
			<authors>
				<author>O Levin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1962</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochemistry</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Veis</author>
				<author>A Perry</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochemistry</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Nawrot</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1976</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcium Binding Proteins and Calcium Function</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Hay</author>
				<author>D Schlesinger</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Biol. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Schlesinger</author>
				<author>D Hay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Dent. Practnr. Dent. Rec</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Turner</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1958</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Meckel</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1965</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Bernardi</author>
				<author>W Cook</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1960</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Bernardi</author>
				<author>T Kawasaki</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1968</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochim. Biophys. Acta</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Bernardi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1972</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Coll. Int. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Kresak</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Caries Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>M Kresak</author>
				<author>R Zahradnik</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral BioL In Press</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>M Kresak</author>
				<author>D Hay</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biopolymers</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Peckauskas</author>
				<author>J Termine</author>
				<author>I Pullman</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1976</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title/>
			<authors>
				<author>R Peckauskas</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1972</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Amer. Chem. Soc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>I Langmuir</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1918</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Physical Chemistry of Surfaces</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Adamson</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1960</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Phys. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Momany</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1975</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Brit. Dent. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Leach</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Brit. Dent. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Dawes</author>
				<author>G Jenkins</author>
				<author>C Tonge</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1963</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Scand. J. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Lie</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Mayhall</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1970</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Caries Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Sonju</author>
				<author>G Rolla</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1973</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Hay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Hay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1973</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Pruitt</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1969</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Caries Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Armstrong</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1971</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Hillman</author>
				<author>J Van Houte</author>
				<author>R Gibbons</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1970</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Mcgaughey</author>
				<author>B Field</author>
				<author>E Stowell</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1971</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Infect. Immun</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Gibbons</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>D Spinell</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1976</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Caries Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Meckel</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1968</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Proc. Int. Symp. Acid Etch Technique</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1975</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Zahradnik</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>E Burke</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1976</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Propas</author>
				<author>R Zahradnik</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Proc. Roy. Soc. Med</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Darling</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1943</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Bnt. Dent. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Darling</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1956</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Gron</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1973</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Sonju</author>
				<author>G Rolla</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1974</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Hay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1973</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Hay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1973</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Hay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1975</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochemistry</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Oppenheim</author>
				<author>D Hay</author>
				<author>C Franz-Blau</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1971</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochem. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Bennick</author>
				<author>G Connell</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1971</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral BioL</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Hay</author>
				<author>F Oppenheim</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1974</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcium Binding Proteins and Calcium Function</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Bennick</author>
				<author>R Wong</author>
				<author>M Cannon</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Fifth American Peptide Symposium</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Schlesinger</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977-08</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Hay</author>
				<author>D Belensz</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Archs. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Gron</author>
				<author>D Hay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1976</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nature</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>M Kresak</author>
				<author>R Zahradnik</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1974</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Proc. Symp. React. Solkds. Part I</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Brasseur</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1954</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nature</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Elliot</author>
				<author>R Young</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adsorption, Surface Area and Porosity</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Gregg</author>
				<author>K Sing</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Trans. Farad. Soc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Sircar</author>
				<author>A Myers</author>
				<author>M Molstad</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1970</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Coll. Int. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Giles</author>
				<author>D Smith</author>
				<author>A Huitson</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1974</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chemie, Physikalisch Chemie und Anwendungstechnik der Grenz-Ffdchenaktiven Stoffe</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Glantz</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1973</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>th Gen. Session of the Int. Assn. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Kresak</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>D Hay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1978</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>th Gen. Session of the Int. Assn. Dent. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Hay</author>
				<author>S Schluckebier</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1978</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>This Symposium</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>R Zahradnik</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Helv. Odont. Acta</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Ericson</author>
				<author>Y Ericson</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Caries Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Rolla</author>
				<author>B Melsen</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1975</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Caties Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Rolla</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Caries Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Rolla</author>
				<author>S Hsu</author>
				<author>W Bowen</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Caries Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Hay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
	<reference_dois>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9861(56)90183-7</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/bi00860a017</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/bi00661a008</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0021-9258(17)40603-X</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9969(65)90004-X</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0021-9797(77)90010-8</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1002/bip.1976.360150312</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/ja02242a004</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/j100589a006</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9969(70)90021-X</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1159/000259822</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9969(67)90088-X</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9969(73)90127-1</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1177/00220345690480053501</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1159/000259749</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9969(70)90163-9</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1177/00220345710500042201</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1159/000259549</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9969(73)90112-X</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9969(74)90052-1</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9969(73)90127-1</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9969(73)90128-3</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9969(75)90073-4</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/bi00799a013</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9969(74)90130-7</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9969(76)90130-8</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1038/247064a0</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1039/tf9706602354</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0021-9797(74)90252-5</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1159/000260144</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1159/000260284</number>
	</reference_dois>
</document>
