<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Efficient downstream processing of maltodextrin phosphorylase from Escherichia coli and stabilization of the enzyme by immobilization onto hydroxyapatite.pdf</file>
	<title>Efficient downstream processing of maltodextrin phosphorylase from Escherichia coli and stabilization of the enzyme by immobilization onto hydroxyapatite</title>
	<date>Unknown</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Efficient downstream processing of maltodextrin phosphorylase from Escherichia coli and stabilization of the enzyme by immobilization onto hydroxyapatite.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>Christian Eis</author>
		<author>Richard Griessler</author>
		<author>Maria Maier</author>
		<author>Andreas Weinha</author>
		<author>Birgit Bo</author>
		<author>Klaus Kulbe</author>
		<author>Dietmar Haltrich</author>
		<author>Reinhard Schinzel</author>
		<author>Bernd Nidetzky</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>Downstream processing by biospecific chromatography of maltodextrin phosphorylase from Escherichia coli, overexpressed in E. coli, was substantially improved by a novel approach using ceramic hydroxyapatite. Wild-type and a less active mutant enzyme were purified from crude bacterial cell extracts in one efficient separation step that yielded phosphorylase in purity \95% in at least 90% recoveries. At pH 6.9 and 25°C, wild-type and mutant phosphorylases eluted from the hydroxyapatite column at a phosphate concentration of 0.4 M whereas calcium ions failed to displace the enzymes. The dynamic capacity for phosphorylase binding in the presence of bulk proteins was approximately 3 mg enzyme ml -1 matrix. The interaction of E. coli phosphorylase with hydroxyapatite seems to be mediated by surface amino groups, so that the bound enzyme retained almost full catalytic activity. Compared to the soluble enzyme, immobilization onto hydroxyapatite resulted in a more than 30-fold stabilization of wild-type phosphorylase against thermal and proteolytic inactivation and thus could improve the operational stability of phosphorylase during conversion of polysaccharide to glucose 1-phosphate.</abstract>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>Materials</heading>
			<text>A 5-ml column of ceramic hydroxyapatite type II (Econo-Pac HPT hydroxyapatite cartridge) with a particle size of 20 vm was obtained from BioRad (Richmond, CA, USA). For immobilized metal-ion affinity chromatography (IMAC), a Fractogel Chelat 650 (s) gel from Merck (Darmstadt, Germany) that had iminodiacetic acid (IDA) as chelating ligand was used. The material had a particle size of 25 -40 vm. Sepharose CL-4B, Phenylsepharose CL-4B high sub and Sephadex G 25 coarse were purchased from Pharmacia (Uppsala, Sweden). Maltodextrin (dextrin equivalents 19.4) was obtained from Agrana (Gmu ¨nd, Austria). Ethyleneglycol-bis(iaminoethyl ether) N,N,N%,N%-tetraacetic acid (EGTA) and Glc-1-P were purchased from Sigma (Deisenhofen, Germany).</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>The h-1,4-D-glucan phosphorylases catalyze the phosphorolytic degradation of storage polysaccharide into h-D-glucopyranosyl 1-phos-phate (Glc-1-P) and have thus an essential role in the mobilization of stored chemical energy. Hence, phosphorylases are known as key enzymes of cellular carbohydrate metabolism. In addition, they have been useful for several technical applications such as the conversion of starch to Glc-1-P or the synthesis of maltooligosaccharides. When phosphorylase is employed in enzymatic syntheses (Weinha ¨usel et al., 1995), bacterial or plant phosphorylase systems are preferred because they seem to exist in a constitutively active form (Newgard et al., 1987) and lack the complex regulatory properties of mammalian glucan phosphorylases (Barford andJohnson, 1989, Johnson, 1992).

In Escherichia coli, a glycogen phosphorylase and a maltodextrin phosphorylase are found, of which the latter is inducible by maltose and prefers short maltodextrins as substrates to polysaccharides such as glycogen or starch (Schwartz and Hofnung, 1967). This maltodextrin phosphorylase has proved to be a good model for studying the catalytic mechanism of h-1,4-D-glucan phosphorylase (Palm et al., 1990) and for probing structure-function relationships of phosphorylases from bacteria. The role of specific amino acid residues in the active site of this enzyme in substrate binding and catalysis has been investigated by site-specific mutagenesis methods (Schinzel and Palm, 1990, Schinzel and Drueckes, 1991, Becker et al., 1994, Drueckes et al., 1996). Concomitantly, crystallographic studies have been carried out with natural or variant phosphorylase (O'Reilly et al., 1997, Watson et al., 1997). A prerequisite for most of these studies is the availability of pure enzyme in sufficient quantities, thus requiring rapid and high-yield purification strategies. Traditionally, maltodextrin phosphorylase is overexpressed using induction by maltose (Schinzel andDrueckes, 1991, Weinha ¨usel et al., 1995), and wild-type or mutant enzymes are purified by repeated chromatography on an affinity column of maltodextrin - (Thanner et al., 1975) or glycogen -glycine Sepharose (Scha ¨chtele et al., 1978). The affinity method, however, does not fulfill several requirements of an efficient purification protocol. The separation is slow, and considerable prepurification of the phosphorylase is required before the sample can be loaded onto the affinity column. The efficiency of the affinity matrix decreases quite rapidly with the number of passes through the column. Phosphate ions that stabilize maltodextrin phosphorylase against thermal inactivation (Weinha ¨usel et al., 1995) cannot be added to equilibration and elution buffers, at least at room temperature, because otherwise phosphorolytic degradation of the affinity ligand during chromatography is expected to occur. Finally, purification requires biospecific interaction of phosphorylase and the glycogen ligand. For mutant enzymes with altered substrate binding properties, this interaction may not be sufficiently strong to guarantee efficient separation of phosphorylase from other E. coli bulk proteins. Pertaining to the application of E. coli phosphorylase for the production of Glc-1-P, a purification protocol that allows the separation of phosphorylase and phosphatase activities is important (Weinha ¨usel et al., 1995). Glucose 1phosphate is a naturally activated sugar that will serve mainly as an intermediate in chemoenzymatic syntheses. Contamination of phosphorylase by phosphatase will decrease the product yields because of hydrolytic degradation of Glc-1-P by this latter adverse enzyme action. Until now, the separation of phosphorylase and phosphatase activities could only be accomplished by affinity chromatography.

In order to simplify the established procedure, we have developed a new method based on hydroxyapatite chromatography that allows the efficient purification of maltodextrin phosphorylase in one single step in high yields. As a consequence, the phosphorylase is free of contaminating phosphatase activity. The interaction of maltodextrin phosphorylase with hydroxyapatite seems to involve surface amino groups of the protein. Hence, a mutant enzyme with altered catalytic properties could be purified with equal efficiency as the wild-type phosphorylase. Here, chromatography on the hydroxyapatite matrix is compared with two methods known to be efficient for purifying recombinant proteins with genetically introduced polyhistidine affinity peptides: immobilized metal affinity chromatography (Porath et al., 1975, Arnold, 1991) and affinity precipitation with bifunctional reagents (Lilius et al., 1991, Carlsson et al., 1996), a fast and inexpensive procedure for the purification of oligomeric, Histagged proteins.

A 5-ml column of ceramic hydroxyapatite type II (Econo-Pac HPT hydroxyapatite cartridge) with a particle size of 20 vm was obtained from BioRad (Richmond, CA, USA). For immobilized metal-ion affinity chromatography (IMAC), a Fractogel Chelat 650 (s) gel from Merck (Darmstadt, Germany) that had iminodiacetic acid (IDA) as chelating ligand was used. The material had a particle size of 25 -40 vm. Sepharose CL-4B, Phenylsepharose CL-4B high sub and Sephadex G 25 coarse were purchased from Pharmacia (Uppsala, Sweden). Maltodextrin (dextrin equivalents 19.4) was obtained from Agrana (Gmu ¨nd, Austria). Ethyleneglycol-bis(iaminoethyl ether) N,N,N%,N%-tetraacetic acid (EGTA) and Glc-1-P were purchased from Sigma (Deisenhofen, Germany).

The Asn112 Ala mutant enzyme was created as published elsewhere (O'Reilly et al., 1997;Schinzel, unpublished results). The C-terminal hexahistidine tail was introduced by polymerase chain reaction (PCR) using the plasmid pMAP101 as template. A 55 base pair (bp) oligonucleotide (G GAA TTC TTA CAC TAC CAC TAC CAC TAC GCG TTT TGC CTG CCA GAT ACG AGC) and a 21 bp oligonucleotide (GGT AAA GAA GCT CCC GGT ACC) were used as primer pair. The former oligonucleotide has a 24 bp overlap with the malP gene. It was designed to substitute the stop-codon of the malP gene by an alanine and to introduce six histidine codons, a new stop-codon and an EcoRI restriction site. The latter oligonucleotide primer contained a KpnI restriction site. The amplification was performed using a standard protocol (Innis and Gelfland, 1990). The PCR product (485 bp) was digested by EcoRI and KpnI and purified by gel electrophoresis and elution from a 1% agarose gel with glass milk. The PCR fragment was ligated to the 4581 bp KpnI-EcoRI fragment of pMAP101. The sequence was confirmed by sequencing on an Applied Biosystems Model 373 sequencer.

Wild-type maltodextrin phosphorylase, an Asn112 Ala mutant enzyme, and phosphorylase carrying the C-terminal hexahistidine tail were overexpressed in E. coli, strain JM 109 harboring the plasmid pMAP101 (Palm et al., 1986), using induction with maltose. The organism was cultivated under controlled growth conditions in an aerated 7-liter bioreactor (Weinha ¨usel et al., 1995) in the presence of 20 g l -1 glucose and 5 g l -1 maltose. Cells were harvested by centrifugation when both D-glucose and maltose had been completely consumed (approximately 7 h). Then, the cell extracts were prepared as described previously (Weinha ¨usel et al., 1995). Phosphorylase was estimated to account for approximately 15% of the total bacterial protein.

Rabbit muscle phosphorylase a, which is the phosphorylated enzyme form, was purchased from Boehringer (Mannheim, Germany). Phosphorylase from potato tubers (Hollo et al., 1964) and Corynebacterium callunae (Weinha ¨usel et al., 1994) were purified to apparent homogeneity by reported methods including a step of affinity chromatography using maltodextrin as a biospecific ligand in case of the latter enzyme (Weinha ¨usel et al., 1997).

All purification steps were carried out at room temperature on a Pharmacia fast protein liquid chromatography system equipped with a UV recording unit for the detection of eluting protein at 280 nm. Both natural and a variant form of maltodextrin phosphorylase were purified from the crude bacterial cell extracts or from a prefrac-tionated enzyme preparation. The latter was obtained by ammonium sulphate precipitation at 35% saturation followed by hydrophobic interaction chromatography on Phenylsepharose CL-4B (Weinha ¨usel et al., 1995). Concentration of protein solutions was carried out by 30-kDa cutoff ultrafiltration using Centriprep 30 (Amicon, Danvers, MA, USA) or Ultrafree CL (Millipore, Bedford, CN, USA) tubes. All buffers were degassed and protein solutions were filtered through a 0.45 vm filter.

A 5-ml hydroxyapatite column (height 63 mm, diameter 10 mm) was equilibrated with 0.05 M potassium phosphate buffer, pH 6.9 or 7.5, at a flow rate of 1.0-3.0 ml min -1 . The soluble bacterial cell extract (maximally 2 ml, corresponding to approximately 30 mg protein) or the partially purified preparation (maximally 100 mg protein) were applied directly to the column. The column was washed with equilibration buffer until the absorbance of the effluent reached that of pure buffer. Then, adsorbed proteins were eluted with a linear 0.05-1.0 M gradient of potassium phosphate at a flow rate of 2 ml min -1 . Fractions (1 ml) were collected; those containing phosphorylase activity were pooled and concentrated. After more than ten runs through the column, cleaning of the matrix was accomplished by washing with several column volumes of 1 M NaOH followed by 50 mM phosphate buffer.

A 5-ml Fractogel Chelate column (height 63 mm, diameter 10 mm) was washed with 0.1 M NaCl, loaded with 100 mM CuSO 4 and again washed with 0.1 M NaCl. Finally, the column was equilibrated with 20 mM potassium phosphate buffer, pH 7.0, containing 0.5 M NaCl. Three milligrams of the crude protein or less were applied per 1 ml of matrix. Bound protein was eluted with a linear 0.0 -0.30 M imidazole gradient at a flow rate of 1 ml min -1 .

Affinity precipitation of phosphorylase carrying a polyhistidine tail was carried out on ice with a preformed ZnCl 2 -EGTA reagent complex (Carlsson et al., 1996). The crude cell extract or the supernantant of the ammonium sulphate precipitation at 35% saturation was used in final protein concentrations of 0.5 mg ml -1 dissolved in 50 mM phosphate buffer, pH 6.9. Pelleted protein was washed twice in the same buffer and then dissolved in buffer containing 0.3 M imidazole. Biospecific purification of maltodextrin phosphorylase included the affinity step on glycogen-glycine Sepharose CL-6B (Weinha ¨usel et al., 1995).

Phosphorylase activity was measured at 30°C in the direction of glucan phosphorolysis by a coupled spectrophotometric assay in the presence of rabbit muscle phosphoglucomutase (10 vg ml -1 ; Sigma) and NAD-dependent D-glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase from Leuconostoc mesenteroides (10 vg ml -1 ; Sigma) (Weinha ¨usel et al., 1995). The reaction mixture contained 10 g l -1 maltodextrin, 50 mM potassium phosphate (pH 6.8), 0.1 mM NAD, 10 vg ml -1 D-glucose-1,6bisphosphate, 10 mM MgCl 2 and 1 mM EDTA. Phosphatase activity was measured according to Bergmeyer (1988) using 2.5 mM p-nitrophenylphosphate as substrate. Column fractions were analyzed by denaturing polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis using precast Phast gels 8-25 and stained by Coomassie brilliant blue G-250. Protein concentrations were determined by using the BioRad dye binding assay and bovine serum albumin as standard. Titration of accessible amino groups in phosphorylase was carried out by the colorimetric method of Fields (1971). A 1000-fold molar excess of 2,4,6-trinitrophenylsulphonic acid over phosphorylase was used, and the formation of the 2,4,6-trinitrophenyl -aminosulphite complexes was measured at 420 nm (= 19.2 mmol -1 cm -1 ).

Phosphorylase (approximately 10 units) was applied to a 2-ml hydroxyapatite column (diameter 10 mm, height 25.5 mm) equilibrated in 250 mM phosphate buffer, pH 7.5. The immobilized phosphorylase was incubated at temperatures of 30, 40 and 50°C, and in regular time intervals the remaining enzyme activity was assayed. The activity measurement was carried out by feeding substrate (10 mg ml -1 maltodextrin, 250 mM phosphate, pH 7.5) with a flow rate of 0.1 ml min -1 . Under these conditions, no elution of phosphorylase occurred, and the concentration of Glc-1-P in the effluent of the column was directly proportional to enzyme activity. To investigate the resistance against proteolyis of hydroxyapatite-bound phosphorylase, incubations were made at 37°C in the presence of 9 vg proteinase K ml -1 matrix (50 mM phosphate, pH 7.5). The residual enzyme activity after 3, 7, and 13 h was measured. The results were compared with the stabilities of the soluble phosphorylase in 50 mM phosphate buffer, pH 7.5.

One major goal of this work was to simplify the purification of E. coli maltodextrin phosphorylase. Unlike mammalian glycogen phosphorylase isozymes (Luong et al., 1992), purification to near homogeneity in one single step by IMAC was not possible with the wild-type E. coli maltodextrin phosphorylase. The phosphorylase and phosphatase activities could not be separated by IMAC. Conventional ion exchange chromatography (IEX) failed to separate phosphorylase from phosphatase activities, so that IMAC followed by IEX or IEX followed by IMAC was not further pursued. Dye-ligand pseudo-affinity chromatography of the phosphorylase in crude cell extracts was attempted using 17 different textile dyes (Scopes, 1986;Lowe et al., 1986). In 1-ml batch binding experiments (: 5 mg protein ml -1 gel; 10 mM phosphate, pH 6.9), phosphorylase interacted too weakly with all dye -Sepharose CL 4B matrices to allow efficient purification.

When testing overall different chromatographic methods, we observed that maltodextrin phosphorylase strongly interacts with ceramic hydroxyapatite manufactured by BioRad. Thus, in a single purification step, the phosphorylase could be purified to greater than 95% purity from crude bacterial cell extracts. Almost all other bacterial proteins in the cell extracts did not bind to hydroxyapatite in the presence of 100 mM phos-phate. Compared to other proteins (Gorbunoff, 1984), elution of maltodextrin phosphorylase occurred at higher concentrations of phosphate. Depending on the pH of the elution buffer, phosphorylase desorbed from the column at 0.40-0.45 M (pH 6.9) or 0.30 M (pH 7.5) phosphate. The elution profiles obtained with crude bacterial cell extract (Fig. 1) or prepurified phosphorylase (not shown) were identical. Approximately 3 mg phosphorylase could be loaded onto 1 ml of packed bed even when working with the E. coli homogenate.

For pure phosphorylase, however, the capacity of the column was at least 10 mg ml -1 hydroxyapatite matrix. Calcium ions used in concentrations up to 1 M could not displace the phosphorylase from the column (Tris acetate buffer, pH 6.9). The analysis by SDS-PAGE of the fraction containing phosphorylase activity in Fig. 1 showed that phosphorylase was nearly free of contaminating protein (Fig. 2, lane 1). The specific phosphorylase activity was 18 92 U mg -1 (Table 1), a value that agrees well with the specific activity obtained after affinity chromatography using The processed material contained 84.6 U ml -1 phosphorylase and had a total protein content of 44.1 mg ml -1

. In case of the Asn112 Ala mutant the activity was 42.4 U ml -1 , the protein concentration 48.7 mg ml -1 . HA, hydroxyapatite; IMAC, immobilized metal affinity chromatography; MAP, metal affinity precipitation; AC, affinity chromatography using glycogen as biospecific ligand; His-tag, maltodextrin phosphorylase with C-terminal (His) 6 -tail; n.d., not detectable.  Lanes 2 and 3 contained the His-tagged phosphorylase after IMAC (0.16 mg ml -1 ) and affinity precipitation (0.12 mg ml -1 ), respectively. Lanes 4 and 5 contained wild-type phosphorylase (0.25 mg ml -1 ) and the Asp112Ala mutant (0.15 mg ml -1 ) after hydroxyapatite chromatography, respectively. Lane 6 contained the crude cell extract of E. coli, and lane 7 the wild-type phosphorylase after purification on Phenylsepharose. All samples were reduced and then alkylated by iodoacetimide. Staining with silver was used for visualizing protein bands.

glycogen-glycine Sepharose CL-4B (Weinha ¨usel et al., 1995). However, in comparison to the affinity method, purification on the hydroxyapatite matrix was faster and gave at least 25 -30% higher yields (Table 1). The resulting phosphorylase did not contain any detectable phosphatase activity, measured with p-nitrophenyl-phosphate and Glc-1-P (10 mM) as substrate. Hence, it seems suitable for use in kinetic studies as well as enzymic syntheses. Using the crude E. coli cell extract, ten chromatographic runs could be carried out before changes in the elution profile were noticed, and regeneration of the column was necessary.

The failure of calcium ions to displace E. coli phosphorylase bound to hydroxyapatite suggests that binding of the enzyme is mediated by posi-tively charged protein residues that form electrostatic interactions with the negatively charged phosphate groups of the matrix (Gorbunoff, 1984). The almost complete retention of activity of the bound phosphorylase indicates that the residues involved in hydroxyapatite binding are located at the protein surface rather than in, or close to, the active site. This conclusion is reinforced by the fact that the substrate, maltodextrin, in concentrations of 10-40 mg ml -1 did not induce elution of the phosphorylase. We were interested in whether other glucan phosphorylases interact with hydroxyapatite too. If so, hydroxyapatite chromatography could be a convenient purification method for members of the glucan phosphorylase family. The phosphorylases from rabbit muscle (a-form), potato tuber and C. callunae did not bind to the matrix in the pH range 6.0-8.0, even when the phosphate concentration of the equilibration buffer was decreased to 10 mM. The differential chromatographic behavior of various phosphorylases could be understood when the accessible amino groups in each protein were measured. Amino groups are thought to act in the adsorption of proteins to hydroxyapatite primarily as a result of non-specific interactions between their positive charges and the negative charge of the matrix (Gorbunoff, 1984). Thirtyseven amino groups per maltodextrin phosphorylase protomer were titrated by chemical derivatization with 2,4,6-trinitrophenylsulfonic acid. In contrast, the number of accessible amino groups in rabbit muscle and C. callunae phosphorylase was only 22 and 20, respectively.

Various mutants of maltodextrin phosphorylase that have been constructed by site-directed mutagenesis exhibit extremely low catalytic activity or have drastically impaired substrate binding properties (Drueckes et al., 1996). Thus, they are more difficult to purify than wild-type phosphorylase since affinity chromatography may be inappropriate. To further evaluate our novel purification protocol, we purified the Asn112Ala mutant of maltodextrin phosphorylase by hydroxyapatite chromatography (Fig. 2, lane 5). Although the mutant phosphorylase has a twofold lower specific activity (9.891.0 U mg -1 ) than the wildtype enzyme, the elution profiles of natural and variant enzyme form were identical (pH 7.5). The pure Asn112 Ala mutant enzyme was recovered in \ 90% yield (Table 1). Hydroxyapatite matrices should therefore be considered as efficient tools for the purification of new mutants of maltodextrin phosphorylase. The mechanism of glucan binding and recognition at the active site of phosphorylase is currently investigated by sitedirected mutagenesis methods and crystallographic analysis (Drueckes et al., 1996, O'Reilly et al., 1997). Hence, the rapid and high-yield isolation of mutant enzymes with altered glucan binding properties is expected to be increasingly important in the very near future. The lacking competence of maltodextrin to displace wild-type phosphorylase from the hydroxyapatite column clearly shows that the ability to bind the glucan substrate tightly is not a prerequisite for the interaction of phosphorylase with the chromatographic matrix.

The thermal stability of maltodextrin phosphorylase bound to hydroxyapatite (5 U ml -1 matrix) was compared with that of the enzyme free in solution. The activity of immobilized phosphorylase was measured in a continuous-flow system operated at substrate saturation and under initial rate conditions. Hence, the concentration of Glc-1-P in the effluent is proportional to the residual enzyme activity. The specific activity of hydroxyapatite-bound phosphorylase was estimated to be at least 90% of that of the free enzyme. The time-dependence of phosphorylase inactivation, recorded at three different incubation temperatures, is shown in Fig. 3. When compared to enzyme dissolved in buffer, the stability of maltodextrin phosphorylase at 40 and 50°C was more than 30-fold improved by matrix binding. The inactivation of soluble phosphorylase oc-Fig. 3. Thermal stability of maltodextrin phosphorylase bound to hydroxyapatite. Wild-type phosphorylase was immobilized (approximately 5 U ml -1 matrix) and incubated at temperatures of 30°C (), 40°C () and 50°C () in the presence of 250 mM phosphate buffer, pH 7.5. At times indicated, the enzyme activity was measured at 30°C. See Section 2 for details. Fig. 4. Resistance against proteolytic inactivation of maltodextrin phosphorylase bound to hydroxyapatite. Soluble and hydroxyapatite-immobilized (approximately 5 U ml -1 matrix) wild-type phosphorylase were incubated in the presence of 9 vg proteinase K ml -1 buffer or packed bed at 37°C using 50 mM phosphate buffer, pH 7.5. At times indicated, the residual phosphorylase activity was measured at 30°C. The symbols denote immobilized () and soluble () phosphorylase. See Section 2 for details.

Glc-1-P by phosphorylase is specifically hampered by the moderate solubility of the polysaccharide at 25-30°C. Hence, an increase of the conversion temperature to 40 or 50°C would certainly be important the standpoint of substrate solubility.

A widely used method for the purification of recombinant proteins exploits the metal binding properties of polyhistidine tails in IMAC (Arnold, 1991). It has recently been shown that oligomeric proteins can be precipitated with bifunctional, metal-charged ligands when each protomer contains the affinity tail (Lilius et al., 1991, Carlsson et al., 1996). Since maltodextrin phosphorylase is a dimeric protein, the latter method seemed applicable for this enzyme. Using phosphorylase carrying a hexahistidine Cterminal tail, (-His) 6 , we were interested how the performances of IMAC and affinity precipitation compare with that of hydroxyapatite chromatography of the wild-type phosphorylase in terms of recoveries and purity. Phosphorylase -(His) 6 eluted from a copper-loaded chelating column at an imidazole concentration of 280-300 mM. The enzyme was pure (Fig. 2, lane 2) and had a specific activity of approximately 18 U mg -1 (Table 1). The recoveries, however, were only moderate (18-20%). Similar results concerning purity (Fig. 2, lane 3) and yield (15-18%; Table 1) were obtained by precipitating phosphorylase with a Zn 2 + -EGTA reagent followed by dissolving the washed pellet in buffer with 300 mM imidazole. The yields of recoverable activity of phosphorylase -(His) 6 in IMAC and in the affinity precipitation experiment could be increased by approximately 5% when a phosphorylase preparation was employed that had been prefractionated by ammonium sulphate precipitation at 30% saturation. However, the results demonstrate clearly that the affinity methods based on histidine tags introduced in maltodextrin phosphorylase cannot compete with hydroxyapatite chromatography for downstream processing of the enzyme (Table 1). curred within hours (40°C) or even minutes (50°C) and is thus not shown in Fig. 3. The corresponding half-lives of the soluble phosphorylase at 40 and 50°C were only 2.5 and 0.5 h, respectively. At 30°C, both soluble and immobilized enzyme were perfectly stable for at least 10 days. Maltodextrin phosphorylase was completely resistant against proteinase K treatment when bound to hydroxyapatite (37°C; Fig. 4). After a 13-h incubation period with protease, more than 95% of the original phosphorylase activity could be eluted from the column using 0.4 M phosphate buffer, pH 7.5. In contrast, free phosphorylase was inactivated fully under otherwise identical incubation conditions (50 mM phosphate buffer, pH 7.5). The improved operational stability of maltodextrin phosphorylase immobilized onto hydroxyapatite could considerably extend the range of applications of this enzyme. While the upper limit of the reaction temperature and the corresponding half-life of the enzyme are key aspects of all enzymatic conversion processes, the degradation of starch to</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Bio/Technology</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Arnold</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1991</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nature</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Barford</author>
				<author>L Johnson</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1989</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Biol. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Becker</author>
				<author>D Palm</author>
				<author>R Schinzel</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1994</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Methods of Enzymatic Analysis</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Bergmeyer</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1988</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biotechnol. Bioeng</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Carlsson</author>
				<author>K Mosbach</author>
				<author>L Bu ¨low</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1996</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochemistry</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Drueckes</author>
				<author>B Boeck</author>
				<author>D Palm</author>
				<author>R Schinzel</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1996</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochem. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Fields</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1971</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Anal. Biochem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Gorbunoff</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1984</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Starch/Sta ¨rke</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Hollo</author>
				<author>E Laszlo</author>
				<author>A Hoschke</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1964</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>PCR Protocols</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Innis</author>
				<author>D Gelfland</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1990</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>FASEB J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Johnson</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Eur. J. Biochem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Lilius</author>
				<author>M Persson</author>
				<author>L Bu ¨low</author>
				<author>K Mosbach</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1991</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Chromatogr</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Lowe</author>
				<author>S Burton</author>
				<author>J Pearson</author>
				<author>Y Clonis</author>
				<author>V Stead</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1986</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Chromatogr</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Luong</author>
				<author>M Browner</author>
				<author>R Fletterick</author>
				<author>B Haymore</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>CRC Crit. Rev. Biochem. Mol. Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Newgard</author>
				<author>P Hwang</author>
				<author>R Fletterick</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1987</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Ann. New York Acad. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B Nidetzky</author>
				<author>A Weinha ¨usel</author>
				<author>D Haltrich</author>
				<author>K Kulbe</author>
				<author>R Schinzel</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1996</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nat. Struct. Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M O'reilly</author>
				<author>K Watson</author>
				<author>R Schinzel</author>
				<author>D Palm</author>
				<author>L Johnson</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Z. Naturforsch</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Palm</author>
				<author>R Goerl</author>
				<author>G Weidinger</author>
				<author>R Zeier</author>
				<author>B Fischer</author>
				<author>R Schinzel</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1986</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochemistry</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Palm</author>
				<author>H Klein</author>
				<author>R Schinzel</author>
				<author>M Buehner</author>
				<author>E Helmreich</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1990</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nature</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Porath</author>
				<author>J Carlsson</author>
				<author>I Olsson</author>
				<author>G Belfrage</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1975</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Eur. J. Biochem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K.-H Scha ¨chtele</author>
				<author>E Schiltz</author>
				<author>D Palm</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1978</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>FEBS Lett</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Schinzel</author>
				<author>P Drueckes</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1991</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochemistry</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Schinzel</author>
				<author>D Palm</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1990</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Eur. J. Biochem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Schwartz</author>
				<author>M Hofnung</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1967</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Chromatogr</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Scopes</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1986</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>FEBS Lett</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Thanner</author>
				<author>D Palm</author>
				<author>S Shaltiel</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1975</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>EMBO J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Watson</author>
				<author>D Palm</author>
				<author>R Schinzel</author>
				<author>L Johnson</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Appl. Microbiol. Biotechnol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Weinha ¨usel</author>
				<author>B Nidetzky</author>
				<author>B Blauensteiner</author>
				<author>M Rohrbach</author>
				<author>K Kulbe</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1994</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Enzyme Microb. Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Weinha ¨usel</author>
				<author>B Nidetzky</author>
				<author>C Kysela</author>
				<author>K Kulbe</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1995</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochem. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Weinha ¨usel</author>
				<author>R Griessler</author>
				<author>A Krebs</author>
				<author>P Zipper</author>
				<author>D Haltrich</author>
				<author>K Kulbe</author>
				<author>B Nidetzky</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
</document>
