<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Enhanced fluoride removal behaviour and mechanism by dicalcium phosphate from aqueous solution.pdf</file>
	<title>Enhanced fluoride removal behaviour and mechanism by dicalcium phosphate from aqueous solution</title>
	<date>2018</date>
	<doi_number>10.1080/09593330.2018.1484523</doi_number>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Enhanced fluoride removal behaviour and mechanism by dicalcium phosphate from aqueous solution.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>Chongling Yang</author>
		<author>Litao Guan</author>
		<author>Jiyuan Wang</author>
		<author>Xueqin Yang</author>
		<author>Mengya Lin</author>
		<author>Gexin You</author>
		<author>Shouzai Tan</author>
		<author>Xiaolin Yu</author>
		<author>Maofa Ge</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>Dicalcium phosphate was prepared by ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid as a calcium chelating agent, and further explored to remove the fluoride ions from aqueous solution. The as-prepared samples main existed in the monetite phase from the result of XRD. The dried sample consisted of small nanoparticles and displayed irregular particles with a size of ca. 3 μm due to the agglomeration. The fluoride removal ability was evaluated by batch adsorption experiments. The as-prepared adsorbent exhibited the enhanced fluoride removal behavior with the maximum adsorption capacity of 66.72 mg/g from the Langmuir isotherm model, which was higher than that of other previously reported calcium phosphate. The adsorbent could be utilized in the wide pH range of 3-10. The adsorption kinetics could be better described by the pseudo-second-order model than first-second-order model. The co-existing anions had a negligible influence on the fluoride adsorption. The investigation of adsorption mechanism suggested that the chemical reaction and/or dissolution -precipitation mechanism should be dominant in the fluoride adsorption process, accompanying with electronic interaction and ions exchange, which enhanced the fluoride removal performance.</abstract>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>Materials</heading>
			<text>The chemicals are of analytical reagent grade and used without any further purification. Calcium chloride (CaCl 2 ), Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA), Ammonium hydrogen phosphate ((NH 4 ) 2 HPO 4 ), urea were purchased from local chemical agent suppliers. Ultrapure water (18.2 MΩcm) was used for all the experiments.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Synthesis of dicalcium phosphate (DCP) adsorbent</heading>
			<text>Dicalcium phosphate adsorbent was synthesized by hydrothermal method using EDTA as a calcium chelating agent. Typically, a solution containing 1 mol/L CaCl 2 and 0.1 mol/L EDTA was prepared by dissolving CaCl 2 and EDTA in distilled water.

Then, 60 mL of above solution and 60 mL of 0.6 mol/L (NH 4 ) 2 HPO 4 solution were sequentially added into 24 mL of 1 mol/L urea solution under vigorous stirring. After adjusting the pH value of the mixed solution to pH 4 with 0.1 mol/L HCl, the solution was continuously stirred for 30 min. Subsequently, the solution was transferred into a 200 mL autoclave with a Teflon liner at 180 ºC for 1 h. The resulting precipitate was collected by centrifugation, washed three times with distilled water and dried in vacuum at 80 ºC for 10 h. The samples were denoted as DCP-X, where X means the reaction time.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Characterization of dicalcium phosphate adsorbent.</heading>
			<text>The morphology of the adsorbent was observed by scanning electron microscope (SEM, Hitachi SU8020) and transmission electron microscope (TEM, Hitachi 7700).

The Brunauer-Emmett-Teller (BET) specific surface of the products was calculated from N 2 adsorption-desorption isotherms at 77 K by an automated gas sorption analyzer (Quantachrome Instruments, autosorb-iQ). The phase characterization of the powders was investigated by X-ray diffraction (XRD) using a Rigaku D/max 2500 diffractometer at a voltage of 40 kV and a current of 200 mA with Cu Kα radiation (λ=1.5406 Å), employing a scanning rate 4° min -1 in the 2θ ranging from 10 to 65°.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Batch adsorption experiments</heading>
			<text>Fluoride mother solution (2000 mg/L) was prepared by dissolving NaF into the distilled water, and the other fluoride solution was diluted from the mother solution.

The adsorption experiments were carried out at 200 rpm and 25 ±1 ºC, and the adsorption dose was kept at 1 g/L for all the adsorption experiments. Expect the effect of pH, the initial pH value was not adjusted. The initial fluoride concentration for adsorption kinetic and pH effect experiments was 50 mg/L, while the effect of coexisting ions and effect of hydrothermal time used 36 and 75 mg/L as the initial fluoride concentration, respectively. The adsorption isotherm was performed in the concentration range of 0-200 mg/L. The residual fluoride concentration in the solution was measured by an ion chromatography (ICS-900, Dionex). The adsorption capacity at equilibrium for fluoride was calculated according to the following equation:

where C 0 (mg/L) and C e (mg/L) present the initial and equilibrium fluoride concentration, respectively, V (L) is the volume of the fluoride solution and m (g) is the amount of the adsorbent.

The Langmuir isotherm assumes the monolayer adsorption with the uniform energy on the surface of adsorbent, while the Freundlich isotherm described heterogeneous surfaces with nonenergetically equivalent sites, which can be expressed as [15,26]:

where C e (mg/L) is the equilibrium fluoride concentration in solution; q e (mg/g) is the equilibrium adsorption capacity; Q max (mg/g) is the maximum adsorption capacity per gram of sorbent; b (L/mg) is the Langmuir constant related to the energy of adsorption; K f (mg/g) is Freundlich constants related to adsorption capacity and n is the Freundlich exponent, which indicates the adsorption intensity.

The pseudo-first-order and the pseudo-second-order models were applied to evaluate the adsorption kinetic data, which can be expressed as [27,28]:

Where q e (mg/g) is the amount of adsorbed fluoride at equilibrium, and q t (mg/g) is the amount of adsorbed fluoride at time t; k 1 (1/min) and k 2 (g/( mg min)) are the rate constant of the pseudo-first-order and pseudo-first-order model, respectively.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Structure characterization of the samples</heading>
			<text>The crystal structures of the samples were evaluated by XRD. Fig. 1 shows the XRD patterns of the samples by hydrothermal for different time. DCP-0.5 exhibited the main diffraction peaks of monoclinic brushite phases (JCPDF card no. 72-1240) mixed with a little triclinic monetite phases (JCPDF card no. 71-1759). With increasing the time to 1 h, the diffraction peaks assigned to brushite phases decreased (Fig. 1b), indicating that brushite was transformed into monetite by dehydration [24].

Further prolonging the reaction time, the diffraction peaks of hydroxylapatite (JCPDF card no. 70-0794) appeared in Fig. 1c, until DCP-10 were completely converted into the hydroxylapatite. This is due to the hydrolysis of monetite in alkali solution [29].

According to the above XRD results, it is obvious that the samples by hydrothermal for different time consist of the different compositions. Thus, it is necessary to assess the effect of hydrothermal time on the fluoride removal. As shown in Fig. 2, the samples displayed the distinct fluoride removal ability. The sample DCP-1 had the highest fluoride adsorption capacity, while the hydroxylapatite DCP-10 exhibited the worst adsorption ability. We could exclude the influence of BET area on the removal of fluoride, because BET area of DCP-1 (15.1 m 2 /g) was inferior to those of DCP-3 (33.9 m 2 /g) and DCP-10 (33.7 m 2 /g), which was just slightly higher than that of DCP-0.5 (13.8 m 2 /g). It was deduced that there must be other factor to control the adsorption behavior of DCP. By analyzing the composition of samples, the reason might be speculated that monetite, the main phase in DCP-1, could expose more adsorption sites towards fluoride, or it easily captured fluoride ions to form the news species. The hypothesis will be confirmed in the following investigation of adsorption mechanism. The sample DCP-1 was used for the further characterization and adsorption experiment, and DCP-1 was abbreviated to DCP unless otherwise specified in the following investigation.

The morphology and structure of DCP were investigated by SEM and TEM in Fig. 3. The SEM images (Fig. 3 a and b) showed that DCP samples consisted of irregular particles with a size of ca. 3 μm. The surface of DCP samples was relatively smooth, and some smaller particles appeared on this surface. Such large particles were presumably attributed to the agglomeration of small particles in the drying process.

TEM images (Fig. 3 c andd) further demonstrated the existence of numerous smaller particles with a wide size distribution, revealing that smaller grains could aggregate into the large particles in the drying process.</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>The chronic ingestion of excess fluoride in drinking water has harmful influence on human health, such as dental or skeletal fluorosis, brain damage and thyroid disorder [1,2,3]. The guideline value of fluoride recommended by World Health Organization (WHO) is 1.5 mg/L, and acceptable concentration is in the range of 0.5-1.5 mg/L, which provides the positive protection against tooth decay [4]. An excess or absence of fluoride in drinking water is detrimental to mankind. Fluoride contamination seems ubiquitous in developing country, such as India, Mexico, Argentina, China and Bengal [4]. The purification of fluoride-contaminated water becomes a global environmental concern in the past decades.

A multitude of defluoridation methods are proposed to eliminate the excess fluoride from water, such as precipitation [5], electrodialysis [6,7], ion exchange [8], reverse osmosis [9] and adsorption [10,11,12,13]. Most methods suffer from relatively high operation costs, risk of secondary pollutants and complex treatment processes [14].

Adsorption is regarded as the most efficient and applicable approach in defluoridation because it can solve the aforementioned problems [15,16]. Activated aluminum oxide is often utilized in practical defluoridation application due to the low cost, but its drawback is also distinct, such as relatively low adsorption capacity and weak stability [17,18]. To date, numerous efforts still have been devoted to explore and engineer the novel adsorbent for defluoridation.

Calcium phosphate-based materials, which can be essentially divided into cements or ceramics, including calcite, apatite, dicalcium phosphate, hydroxyapatite (HA), have wide applications in bone repair, drug delivery, orthopedics, cancer therapy and biological matrixes due to their non-toxicity and low cost [19]. Recently, there are a large number of attempts to abate the fluoride contamination by calcium phosphate [14,20,21,22]. To some extent it exhibits the outstanding potential as a candidate for fluoride removal. Zhang  Dicalcium phosphate (DCP) is an important class of calcium phosphate, which consists of brushite (DCPD) and monetite (DCPA). Brushite exhibited the weak mechanical property, and easily was transformed to monetite [23], while monetite is stable under acidic conditions (pH below 4.8) [24]. Thus, it is speculated that monetite will be more suitable for use as fluoride adsorbent. Shen et al. fabricated the well-dispersed monetite bundles inlaid in chitosan beads (MONs@CS) with a maximum fluoride adsorption capacity of 50.01 mg/g, and further proposed that the possible mechanism for fluoride removal should be the ion exchange and electrostatic interactions that originated from the pre-protonated amine groups of chitosan matrix [25].

Herein, we reported the fabrication of dicalcium phosphate (main monetite phase) adsorbent, and investigated the defluoridation performance. The adsorbent was evaluated in terms of adsorption isotherm, effect of pH, adsorption kinetic. The possible adsorption mechanism was proposed by means of proper characterization.

The chemicals are of analytical reagent grade and used without any further purification. Calcium chloride (CaCl 2 ), Ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA), Ammonium hydrogen phosphate ((NH 4 ) 2 HPO 4 ), urea were purchased from local chemical agent suppliers. Ultrapure water (18.2 MΩcm) was used for all the experiments.

Dicalcium phosphate adsorbent was synthesized by hydrothermal method using EDTA as a calcium chelating agent. Typically, a solution containing 1 mol/L CaCl 2 and 0.1 mol/L EDTA was prepared by dissolving CaCl 2 and EDTA in distilled water.

Then, 60 mL of above solution and 60 mL of 0.6 mol/L (NH 4 ) 2 HPO 4 solution were sequentially added into 24 mL of 1 mol/L urea solution under vigorous stirring. After adjusting the pH value of the mixed solution to pH 4 with 0.1 mol/L HCl, the solution was continuously stirred for 30 min. Subsequently, the solution was transferred into a 200 mL autoclave with a Teflon liner at 180 ºC for 1 h. The resulting precipitate was collected by centrifugation, washed three times with distilled water and dried in vacuum at 80 ºC for 10 h. The samples were denoted as DCP-X, where X means the reaction time.

The morphology of the adsorbent was observed by scanning electron microscope (SEM, Hitachi SU8020) and transmission electron microscope (TEM, Hitachi 7700).

The Brunauer-Emmett-Teller (BET) specific surface of the products was calculated from N 2 adsorption-desorption isotherms at 77 K by an automated gas sorption analyzer (Quantachrome Instruments, autosorb-iQ). The phase characterization of the powders was investigated by X-ray diffraction (XRD) using a Rigaku D/max 2500 diffractometer at a voltage of 40 kV and a current of 200 mA with Cu Kα radiation (λ=1.5406 Å), employing a scanning rate 4° min -1 in the 2θ ranging from 10 to 65°.

ESCALab 250Xi using 200 W monochromatic Al Kα radiation. Typically the hydrocarbon C1s line at 284.8 eV from adventitious carbon is used for energy referencing. The Fourier transform infrared (FTIR) spectra of the obtained samples were recorded with a Tensor 27 FTIR spectrometer in the range of 4000-400 cm -1 .

Fluoride mother solution (2000 mg/L) was prepared by dissolving NaF into the distilled water, and the other fluoride solution was diluted from the mother solution.

The adsorption experiments were carried out at 200 rpm and 25 ±1 ºC, and the adsorption dose was kept at 1 g/L for all the adsorption experiments. Expect the effect of pH, the initial pH value was not adjusted. The initial fluoride concentration for adsorption kinetic and pH effect experiments was 50 mg/L, while the effect of coexisting ions and effect of hydrothermal time used 36 and 75 mg/L as the initial fluoride concentration, respectively. The adsorption isotherm was performed in the concentration range of 0-200 mg/L. The residual fluoride concentration in the solution was measured by an ion chromatography (ICS-900, Dionex). The adsorption capacity at equilibrium for fluoride was calculated according to the following equation:

where C 0 (mg/L) and C e (mg/L) present the initial and equilibrium fluoride concentration, respectively, V (L) is the volume of the fluoride solution and m (g) is the amount of the adsorbent.

The Langmuir isotherm assumes the monolayer adsorption with the uniform energy on the surface of adsorbent, while the Freundlich isotherm described heterogeneous surfaces with nonenergetically equivalent sites, which can be expressed as [15,26]:

where C e (mg/L) is the equilibrium fluoride concentration in solution; q e (mg/g) is the equilibrium adsorption capacity; Q max (mg/g) is the maximum adsorption capacity per gram of sorbent; b (L/mg) is the Langmuir constant related to the energy of adsorption; K f (mg/g) is Freundlich constants related to adsorption capacity and n is the Freundlich exponent, which indicates the adsorption intensity.

The pseudo-first-order and the pseudo-second-order models were applied to evaluate the adsorption kinetic data, which can be expressed as [27,28]:

Where q e (mg/g) is the amount of adsorbed fluoride at equilibrium, and q t (mg/g) is the amount of adsorbed fluoride at time t; k 1 (1/min) and k 2 (g/( mg min)) are the rate constant of the pseudo-first-order and pseudo-first-order model, respectively.

The crystal structures of the samples were evaluated by XRD. Fig. 1 shows the XRD patterns of the samples by hydrothermal for different time. DCP-0.5 exhibited the main diffraction peaks of monoclinic brushite phases (JCPDF card no. 72-1240) mixed with a little triclinic monetite phases (JCPDF card no. 71-1759). With increasing the time to 1 h, the diffraction peaks assigned to brushite phases decreased (Fig. 1b), indicating that brushite was transformed into monetite by dehydration [24].

Further prolonging the reaction time, the diffraction peaks of hydroxylapatite (JCPDF card no. 70-0794) appeared in Fig. 1c, until DCP-10 were completely converted into the hydroxylapatite. This is due to the hydrolysis of monetite in alkali solution [29].

According to the above XRD results, it is obvious that the samples by hydrothermal for different time consist of the different compositions. Thus, it is necessary to assess the effect of hydrothermal time on the fluoride removal. As shown in Fig. 2, the samples displayed the distinct fluoride removal ability. The sample DCP-1 had the highest fluoride adsorption capacity, while the hydroxylapatite DCP-10 exhibited the worst adsorption ability. We could exclude the influence of BET area on the removal of fluoride, because BET area of DCP-1 (15.1 m 2 /g) was inferior to those of DCP-3 (33.9 m 2 /g) and DCP-10 (33.7 m 2 /g), which was just slightly higher than that of DCP-0.5 (13.8 m 2 /g). It was deduced that there must be other factor to control the adsorption behavior of DCP. By analyzing the composition of samples, the reason might be speculated that monetite, the main phase in DCP-1, could expose more adsorption sites towards fluoride, or it easily captured fluoride ions to form the news species. The hypothesis will be confirmed in the following investigation of adsorption mechanism. The sample DCP-1 was used for the further characterization and adsorption experiment, and DCP-1 was abbreviated to DCP unless otherwise specified in the following investigation.

The morphology and structure of DCP were investigated by SEM and TEM in Fig. 3. The SEM images (Fig. 3 a and b) showed that DCP samples consisted of irregular particles with a size of ca. 3 μm. The surface of DCP samples was relatively smooth, and some smaller particles appeared on this surface. Such large particles were presumably attributed to the agglomeration of small particles in the drying process.

TEM images (Fig. 3 c andd) further demonstrated the existence of numerous smaller particles with a wide size distribution, revealing that smaller grains could aggregate into the large particles in the drying process.

The adsorption isotherm can evaluate the adsorption process, which describes the relationship between the adsorbate in the liquid phase and the adsorption sites on the adsorbent surface. The common Langmuir and Freundlich isotherms are used in the present study [26,30]. The results of fitting curves are shown in Fig. 4a, and the corresponding calculated parameters are listed in Table 1. It was observed that the adsorption capacity of fluoride increased with increasing the fluoride concentration.

The correlation coefficient (R 2 ) values proved that the Langmuir isotherm model is more suitable than the Freundlich isotherm model for describing the adsorption process. This suggested that the fluoride should be adsorbed on the homogeneous surface of absorbent in the form of monolayer. In addition, the positive Langmuir constant b and the high Freundlich constant n (&gt;1) implied the good affinity of DCP adsorbent towards fluoride. The theoretical maximum adsorption capacity of fluoride from the Langmuir isotherm model is 66.72 mg/g, which is higher than that of other calcium phosphate reported in Table 2.

The solution pH has a vital influence on the surface charge of the adsorbent and the dissociation of surface functional groups. The effect of initial pH on fluoride adsorption is presented in Fig. 4b. It could be seen that the fluoride adsorption capacity reached the maximum value 40.5 mg/g at pH 3. At low pH 2.1, the adsorption capacity dramatically decreased to 6.4 mg/g, and kept constant 26 mg/g in the pH rang of 6-10. It is generally accepted that the electrostatic interaction and ion-exchange dominated the adsorption ability of calcium-based adsorbent toward fluoride [27,36]. The protonation enhanced the electrostatic interaction between the positive charged surface and the negative charged fluoride at low pH, thereby improving the adsorption ability of DCP. However, DCP took the risk of dissolving at lower pH, resulting in the reduction of adsorption sites as well as the abatement of electrostatic interaction due to the formation of hydrofluoric acid (HF). While with the increase of pH, the degree of surface protonation would decrease gradually, and the negative charge surface would be not beneficial to the electrostatic interaction with the negative anionic fluoride ions. In addition, the large amounts of OH -ions might compete with fluoride ions for the adsorption sites [37]. These reasons will give rise to the reduction of fluoride adsorption capacity. It is worth noting that pH value had the neglected influence on the adsorption capacity in the pH range of 6-10. This means that there must be other factor to control the adsorption behavior besides electronic interaction and ions exchange, such as chemical reaction.

The adsorption rate is a crucial criterion to evaluate the adsorption efficiency. The effect of contact time on fluoride adsorption was shown in Fig. 5a. It was observed that the adsorption capacity quickly increased in the initial 60 min, subsequently increased at a slower rate and reached the adsorption equilibrium in 240 min. The kinetic data was further fitted by the pseudo-first-order and the pseudo-second-order models. As shown in Fig. 5b, the plots can be fitted well by pseudo-second-order model with the high R 2 value 0.962 (pseudo-first-order value: 0.254), implying that the rate limiting step may be chemisorption involving valence forces by sharing or electron exchange between adsorbent and adsorbate [38,39]. The adsorption capacity q e (30.96 mg/g) obtained from the kinetic curve coincided with the experimental value (28.92 mg/g).

The thermodynamic parameters, such as standard Gibbs free energy (ΔG 0 ), standard enthalpy change (ΔH 0 ), and standard entropy change (ΔS 0 ) were calculated to evaluate the thermodynamic feasibility and the nature of adsorption process according to the following equations [40]:

where K 0 is the distribution coefficient (mL/g); R is the universal gas constant; T is the absolute temperature (K). The values of ΔH 0 and ΔS 0 were obtained from the slope and intercept of lnK 0 against 1/T.

The thermodynamics plots are displayed in Fig. 6a, and the parameters are listed in Table 3. It was seen that ΔG 0 at all evaluated temperature exhibited the negative values, demonstrating the feasible and spontaneous adsorption process, and the degree of spontaneity increased with the increase of temperature. The adsorption process was endothermic in nature, as confirmed by the positive ΔH 0 value (4.48 kJ/mol). It was deduced that chemical adsorption should be involved in the whole process, implying the occurrence of chemical reaction. Moreover, the positive ΔS 0 (36.37 J/mol•K) reflected the affinity of adsorbent towards fluoride.

In natural water environment, several common anions, such as Cl -, NO

Dicalcium phosphate adsorbent was synthesized by a facile method, and it could effectively be used to remove the fluoride ions from aqueous solution. XRD result indicated that monetite was the dominant phase in the as-prepared dicalcium phosphate. The adsorbent showed the relatively high adsorption capacity in the wide pH range of 3-10. The adsorption of fluoride onto DCP followed the Langmuir isotherm model with a maximum adsorption capacity of 66.72 mg/g, which is higher than other calcium phosphate-based materials. The adsorption kinetic data could be described by pseudo-second-order kinetic model. The co-existing anions had a negligible influence on the fluoride adsorption. The adsorption mechanism was investigated by XRD, FTIR and XPS, and the chemical reaction and/or dissolutionprecipitation mechanism, dominated the whole adsorption process, in conjunction with electronic interaction and ions exchange, cooperatively enhanced the fluoride removal. Hydroxyapatite/multi-walled carbon nanotubes 30.22 [31] Cellulose@hydroxyapatite nanocomposites 4.2 [32] Hydroxyapatite nanoparticles 19.7 [20] Brushite 6.59 [21] Al modified calcium 32.57 [33] Sulfate-doped hydroxyapatite microspheres 28.3 [34] Hydroxyapatite-coated-limestone 8.8 [14] n-HAp@Gel composite 4.16 [35] Dicalcium phosphate 66.72 This study</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem Eng J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Bhatnagar</author>
				<author>E Kumar</author>
				<author>M Sillanpaa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2011</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Mol Liq</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Chi</author>
				<author>Y Chen</author>
				<author>C Hu</author>
				<author>Y Wang</author>
				<author>C Liu</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem Eng J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Xiang</author>
				<author>G Zhang</author>
				<author>Y Zhang</author>
				<author>D Tang</author>
				<author>J Wang</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2014</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Environ Sci Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>V Sternitzke</author>
				<author>R Kaegi</author>
				<author>J Audinot</author>
				<author>E Lewin</author>
				<author>J Hering</author>
				<author>C Johnson</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2012</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Environ Sci Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Reardon</author>
				<author>Y Wang</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Desalination</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Lahnid</author>
				<author>M Tahaikt</author>
				<author>K Elaroui</author>
				<author>I Idrissi</author>
				<author>M Hafsi</author>
				<author>I Laaziz</author>
				<author>Z Amor</author>
				<author>F Tiyal</author>
				<author>A Elmidaoui</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2008</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chemosphere</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Ghosh</author>
				<author>C Medhi</author>
				<author>M Purkait</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2008</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Meenakshi</author>
				<author>N Viswanathan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2007</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Desalination</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Ndiayea</author>
				<author>P Moulin</author>
				<author>L Dominguez</author>
				<author>J Millet</author>
				<author>F Charbit</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2005</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Clean Prod</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Agarwal</author>
				<author>K Rai</author>
				<author>R Shrivastav</author>
				<author>S Dass</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2003</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Environ Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Xu</author>
				<author>X Chai</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2018</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Desalination and Water Treatment</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Wu</author>
				<author>G Zhang</author>
				<author>D Tang</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem Eng J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Kang</author>
				<author>X Yu</author>
				<author>M Ge</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Environ Sci Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Kanno</author>
				<author>R Sanders</author>
				<author>S Flynn</author>
				<author>G Lessard</author>
				<author>Scb Myneni</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2014</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>RSC Adv</title>
			<authors>
				<author>X Yu</author>
				<author>D Kang</author>
				<author>Y Hu</author>
				<author>S Tong</author>
				<author>M Ge</author>
				<author>C Cao</author>
				<author>W Song</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2014</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem Eng J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Tang</author>
				<author>G Zhang</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>RSC Adv</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Kang</author>
				<author>S Tong</author>
				<author>X Yu</author>
				<author>M Ge</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2015</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chemosphere</title>
			<authors>
				<author>X Wu</author>
				<author>Y Zhang</author>
				<author>X Dou</author>
				<author>M Yang</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2007</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>RSC Adv</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Mirkovic</author>
				<author>Tdl Pasti</author>
				<author>A Dosen</author>
				<author>M Cebela</author>
				<author>A Rosic</author>
				<author>B Matovic</author>
				<author>B Babic</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Hazard Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Zhang</author>
				<author>H Luo</author>
				<author>L Zheng</author>
				<author>K Wang</author>
				<author>H Li</author>
				<author>Y Wang</author>
				<author>H Feng</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2012</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Desalination</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Mourabet</author>
				<author>El Boujaady</author>
				<author>H</author>
				<author>El Rhilassi</author>
				<author>A Ramdane</author>
				<author>H Bennani-Ziatni</author>
				<author>M</author>
				<author>El Hamri</author>
				<author>R Taitai</author>
				<author>A</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2011</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Environmental Earth Sciences</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Jayarathne</author>
				<author>R Weerasooriya</author>
				<author>R Chandrajith</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2015</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Journal of Materials Chemistry B</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Sahin</author>
				<author>M Ciftcioglu</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Crystengcomm</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Chen</author>
				<author>K Grandfield</author>
				<author>S Yu</author>
				<author>H Engqvist</author>
				<author>W Xia</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem Eng J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Shen</author>
				<author>L Wu</author>
				<author>Y Chen</author>
				<author>S Li</author>
				<author>S Rashid</author>
				<author>Y Gao</author>
				<author>J Liu</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Mater Chem A</title>
			<authors>
				<author>X Yu</author>
				<author>S Tong</author>
				<author>M Ge</author>
				<author>J Zuo</author>
				<author>C Cao</author>
				<author>W Song</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Carbohydr Polym</title>
			<authors>
				<author>X Yu</author>
				<author>S Tong</author>
				<author>M Ge</author>
				<author>J Zuo</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Water Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Singh</author>
				<author>T Townsend</author>
				<author>D Mazyck</author>
				<author>T Boyer</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2012</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Ceram Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Yu</author>
				<author>Y Zhu</author>
				<author>C Qi</author>
				<author>J Wu</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem Eng J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Wang</author>
				<author>X Yu</author>
				<author>C Yang</author>
				<author>X Yang</author>
				<author>M Lin</author>
				<author>L Guan</author>
				<author>M Ge</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Appl Surf Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Z Ruan</author>
				<author>Y Tian</author>
				<author>J Ruan</author>
				<author>G Cui</author>
				<author>K Iqbal</author>
				<author>A Iqbal</author>
				<author>H Ye</author>
				<author>Z Yang</author>
				<author>S Yan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Atmos Environ</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Carslaw</author>
				<author>G Rhys-Tyler</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Hazard Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Nie</author>
				<author>C Hu</author>
				<author>C Kong</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2012</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem Eng J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Chen</author>
				<author>K Zhang</author>
				<author>J He</author>
				<author>W Xu</author>
				<author>X Huang</author>
				<author>J Liu</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Int J Biol Macromol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Pandi</author>
				<author>N Viswanathan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2015</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Chen</author>
				<author>C Shen</author>
				<author>S Rashid</author>
				<author>S Li</author>
				<author>B Ali</author>
				<author>J Liu</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Environ Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Zhang</author>
				<author>X Liu</author>
				<author>X Huang</author>
				<author>W Wang</author>
				<author>P Sun</author>
				<author>Y Li</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2018</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Journal of Environmental Sciences</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Kang</author>
				<author>X Yu</author>
				<author>M Ge</author>
				<author>F Xiao</author>
				<author>H Xu</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem Eng J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Toor</author>
				<author>Jin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2012</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem Eng J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Kang</author>
				<author>X Yu</author>
				<author>M Ge</author>
				<author>M Lin</author>
				<author>X Yang</author>
				<author>Y Jing</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2018</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Water Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Hokkanen</author>
				<author>A Bhatnagar</author>
				<author>M Sillanpaa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Solid State Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Tortet</author>
				<author>J Gavarri</author>
				<author>G Nihoul</author>
				<author>A Dianoux</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomaterials</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Antonakos</author>
				<author>E Liarokapis</author>
				<author>T Leventouri</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2007</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Mater Sci Eng C-Mater Biol Appl</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Karimi</author>
				<author>M Ramsheh</author>
				<author>S Ahmadi</author>
				<author>M Madani</author>
				<author>M Shamsi</author>
				<author>R Reshadi</author>
				<author>F Lotfi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
	<reference_dois>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2011.05.028</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.molliq.2017.07.026</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2014.03.118</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/es202750t</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/es990542k</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2007.11.027</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.chemosphere.2008.08.041</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2006.12.032</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2004.07.042</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0959-6526(02)00065-3</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/09593330.2017.1301569</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/19443994.2016.1138331</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2017.07.140</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/es405135r</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1039/C4RA05601A</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2015.08.019</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1039/C4RA13688H</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.chemosphere.2007.05.075</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1039/C5RA27554G</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2012.09.066</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2011.05.068</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s12665-014-3998-7</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1039/c3tb20130a</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1039/C5CE02078F</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2016.05.103</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1039/C2TA00315E</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.carbpol.2012.09.045</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.watres.2011.11.007</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.ceramint.2017.02.073</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2017.03.155</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.apsusc.2017.03.215</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.atmosenv.2013.09.026</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2012.07.020</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2015.10.036</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.ijbiomac.2014.12.004</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2016.12.032</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jes.2016.04.022</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2012.01.089</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2018.03.174</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.watres.2016.01.008</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1006/jssc.1997.7383</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.biomaterials.2007.02.028</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.msec.2017.03.217</number>
	</reference_dois>
</document>
