<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/European union regulatory developments for new vaccine adjuvants.pdf</file>
	<title>European union regulatory developments for new vaccine adjuvants and delivery systems</title>
	<date>2004</date>
	<doi_number>10.1016/j.vaccine.2003.11.071</doi_number>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/European union regulatory developments for new vaccine adjuvants.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>Dorothea Sesardic</author>
		<author>Roland Dobbelaer</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>Interest in vaccine adjuvants and new delivery systems has grown rapidly over the past few years. New vaccine candidates have emerged, which, because of their poor immunogenicity, rely on adjuvants to improve their presentation and targeting and to potentiate their protective immune response. Better understandings of the mechanisms of action, together with logistic and economical considerations have resulted in an explosion of technologies. However, there have been few new registered products for human use, and antigens incorporated into immunostimulating reconstituted influenza virosomes have only relatively recently been licensed in European Union (EU) countries. Influenza vaccine, adjuvanted with water in oil emulsion containing squalene (adjuvant MF59C1) is now also approved.</abstract>
	<methods/>
	<full_text>New and improved vaccines and delivery systems are increasingly being developed for prevention, treatment and diagnosis of human diseases. Prior to their use in humans, all new biological products must undergo pre-clinical evaluation. These pre-clinical studies are important not only to establish the biological properties of the material and to evaluate its possible risk to the public, but also to plan protocols for subsequent clinical trials from which safety and efficacy can be evaluated. For vaccines, evaluation in pre-clinical studies is particularly important as information gained may also contribute to identifying the optimum composition and formulation process and provide an opportunity to develop suitable indicator tests for quality control [1]. Data from pre-clinical and laboratory evaluation stud-ies, which continue during clinical studies, is used to support an application for marketing authorisation. Addition of a new adjuvant and exploration of new delivery systems for vaccines presents challenges to both manufacturers and regulatory authorities. Because no adjuvant is licensed as a medicinal product in its own right, but only as a component of a particular vaccine, pre-clinical and appropriate toxicology studies need to be designed on a case-by-case basis to evaluate the safety profile of the adjuvant and adjuvant/vaccine combination. Current regulatory requirements for the pharmaceutical and pre-clinical safety assessment of vaccines are insufficient and initiatives are in place to develop more specific guidelines for evaluation of adjuvants in vaccines.

Vaccine adjuvants can be defined as substances that are added to vaccine antigens to enhance and/or target the immune response to these antigens. Charles Janeway appropriately called vaccine adjuvants &quot;the immunologist's dirty little secrets&quot; in 1989. Indeed they were 'secrets', and limited knowledge about their mode of action meant that development of vaccines was largely an empirical process [2]. It is now known that adjuvants are critical for determining the magnitude and direction of the immune response by mechanisms including increased antigen presentation, uptake, distribution and selective targeting. The ambitious aim of future vaccines is to provide maximum efficacy with minimum number of doses, delivered safely and easily. It is clear that adjuvants will have an essential role in the development of these new vaccines. Nevertheless, the complete mechanisms underlying the mode of action of the most widely used adjuvant, aluminium salt, still remains to be defined [3].

A number of new vaccine adjuvants, such as oil emulsions and virosomes, are currently in use for human vaccines, with many more under pre-clinical or clinical development. The development of new adjuvants is stimulated by a number of factors, including the low immunogenicity of newly developed pure antigens and DNA vaccines, the generally poor immune response in certain age groups, such as the poor response to influenza antigens in the elderly, and a better knowledge of immune response mechanisms. Furthermore, new routes of delivery are being explored, such as transdermal, mucosal and intranasal, and there are attempts to more accurately target the immune response. Better adjuvants may also allow the use of a lower amount of antigen and provide needle-free delivery.

However, the development of new adjuvants is hampered by safety concerns precipitated by their reactogenicity in some of the new substances. A lack of universality has been another factor as only a few of the new adjuvants seem suitable for a wide range of antigens. Because the adjuvant is not the active ingredient in a vaccine, and the action of the vaccine/adjuvant combination is the result of multiple factors, immune responses obtained with one antigen/adjuvant cannot be extrapolated to another antigen or even to the same combination given by different routes. It is the individual vaccine/adjuvant combination that is licensed, necessitating case-by-case evaluation and leading to difficulties in the preparation of guidelines that would apply to all situations. The absence of relevant animal models and surrogate markers of protection needed to demonstrate the efficacy of a modified antigen/adjuvant combination is one of the critical factors blocking development and faster acceptance of new adjuvants. The current attitude regarding risk-benefit of vaccination puts a large emphasis on safety because the vaccine is given to a predominately healthy population. Thus manufacturers and authorities have been slow in introducing products or regulations involving adjuvants other than established aluminium-salts leading to stay with aluminium as long as possible (STALL). However, for therapeutic vaccines, where the benefit of the vaccine is substantial, an additional level of risk may be more acceptable.

Key components in safety assessment of any new vaccine comprise of many stages and many years of work. These include initial laboratory studies performed during development stages and extensive pharmacology and toxicology studies during pre-clinical evaluation, which are prerequisite to the initial clinical trials and eventual clinical studies in which safety and efficacy are established. Once a product is given marketing approval, monitoring of batch-to-batch consistency provides ongoing evaluation of the product using assays developed and established during pre-clinical and early clinical studies. Post marketing surveillance is used to monitor the quality and performance of a vaccine in the target population under routine use, and inspection of manufacturing sites are performed to ensure compliance with good manufacturing practice and relevant national guidelines.

Currently applicable regulatory texts concerning adjuvants in vaccines for human and veterinary use can be found in the European Pharmacopoeia (Ph Eur) and in several guidance documents of the committee for proprietary medicinal products (CPMP). Although the Ph Eur general monographs for vaccines for human use [4] allow the use of adjuvants other than aluminium-salts, requirements at present mainly pertain to the latter. Regulatory expectations for established and new adjuvants can also be found, in general terms, in the CPMP guidance documents on combined vaccines [5] and on pre-clinical and clinical testing of new vaccines [6,7]. The CPMP is the primary scientific body in EU regulatory matters. Within the framework of the European Medicines Evaluation Agency's (EMEA) activities, the CPMP, through several working parties (biotechnology working party (BWP), the safety working party (SWP) and the efficacy working party (EWP), has established a number of &quot;notes for guidance&quot; that provide information for both Industry and regulatory authorities on the content and evaluation of marketing authorisation applications.

With respect to adjuvants alone, CPMP document on pre-clinical pharmaceutical and toxicological testing of vaccines [6] stress the need for demonstration of compatibility with all antigens, efficient and stable adsorption (if the antigens are adsorbed) and acceptable toxicity. In addition, the guidelines include the need for studying, in an appropriate animal model, the safety profile of the adjuvant-antigen combination, representing the intended clinical route of administration, in comparison with &quot;mock&quot; vaccine.

The required toxicity studies on the adjuvant alone depend on information available in the existing literature. The pharmacological and toxicological parameters mentioned include:

• Injection site reactions, fever and other systemic effects including immune mediated events, teratogenicity and genotoxicity.

• The adjuvant effects on the immune response.

• Repeated dose toxicity to study hypersensitivity reactions e.g. using &quot;mock&quot; vaccines. • Distribution studies.

With respect to adjuvants, this note for guidance underlines the need for an antigenically similar comparator and distribution studies are explicitly mentioned when a new adjuvant is present. As a general recommendation, any extrapolation from clinical efficacy data from a licensed vaccine must be scientifically justified.

However, these regulatory guidelines are insufficient and initiatives are ongoing to draft more adequate guidance for the new generation of adjuvants. The CPMP has requested the newly created vaccine expert group (VEG) to combine and update the currently available CPMP recommendations concerning adjuvants and to try to give more detailed and specific guidance. Due to its multi-disciplinary nature, the VEG is a suitable forum for this subject and guidance related to quality, pre-clinical safety and clinical safety and efficacy will be given in this document [8].

The content of the latest draft of the note for guidance at the time of the VAMD meeting in Dublin, June 2003 is summarised below, although changes to the format and content may occur in later versions. The points described do give a reliable account of the lines of thinking of the EU experts in the field.

Currently, the scope includes types of adjuvants, categorised on the basis of mode of action, physical properties or source and include:

• Mineral salts: aluminium hydroxide and aluminium or calcium phosphate. • Oil emulsions and surfactant: MF59 (microfluidised detergent stabilised oil in water emulsion), QS21 (purified saponin), Montanides (stabilised water in oil emulsion). • Particulate: virosomes (unilamellar liposomal vehicles with influenza antigens), ISCOMS (structured complex of saponins and lipids), PLG (poly-lactic-co-glycolic acid), Chitosan. • Microbial (natural and synthetic) derivatives: CpG ODN, MDP analogues, bacterial (mutant) toxins (CT, LT). • Endogenous human immunomodulators: human granulocyte macrophage stimulating factor (HgM-CSF) and interleukins (IL-12, IL-2).

A distinction is made between parameters to be studied during development and characterisation and those to be tested for routinely.

During development studies of the adjuvant and the adjuvant/vaccine combination, pharmaceutical and pharmaco-dynamics studies should include the quality-related aspects of demonstration of the 'proof of concept', the mechanism of action and the compatibility of adjuvant with antigens.

Characterisation of the adjuvant would include:

• Qualitative and quantitative composition.

• Physical characteristics (e.g. visual appearance, density, viscosity, pH, size and size distribution, surface charge). • Biochemical characteristics (e.g. adsorption, binding or coupling of an antigen). • Microbiological and chemical purity (e.g. endotoxin content, bioburden, manufacturing residuals).

A selection of such tests should be made for routine QC testing of the adjuvant bulks and for stability studies.

Developmental studies of the adjuvant-antigen combination would include the mechanism and efficiency of association between antigen and adjuvant, and compatibility studies on the intended combination of adjuvant(s) and antigen(s).

Characterisation of the adjuvant-antigen combination would include the consistency and stability of the association of antigen and adjuvant, the integrity of the antigen in the combination, the effect of adjuvant on the ability to assay the antigen. Other parameters may include chemical and physical characteristics (e.g. particle size, viscosity).

Again, tests for routine QC use and stability studies should be selected.

Pre-clinical safety studies on the adjuvant alone would include local tolerance (e.g. inflammation), induction of hypersensitivity and anaphylaxis, pyrogenicity, systemic toxicity to tissues or organs (single-dose), reproduction toxicity, genotoxicity, carcinogenicity and adsorption by and elimination from tissues.

Pre-clinical safety studies on the antigen-adjuvant will again include. local tolerance, systemic toxicity (repeat dose toxicity) together with reproductive toxicity and characterisation of immune response.

Clinical assessment requires suitably controlled studies on the adjuvant(s) alone, and on its combination with the antigen(s) from which the following information can be obtained:

• Inclusion of the adjuvant must be justified.

• Benefit in terms of enhancement of immune response without undue increase in local and systemic reactions must be demonstrated. • For combined vaccines benefit without detrimental effect to other antigen(s) must be demonstrated. • Risk-benefit relations must be considered case-by-case and for a modified product should be at least as favourable as for existing product. • Superiority for immune responses to the antigen or to at least one of the antigens • Non-inferiority for responses to any other antigen(s) Replacement of one or more adjuvant(s) in a licensed vaccine with one or more novel or established adjuvant(s) If primary aim is to enhance immunogenicity, studies to demonstrate:

• Superiority for immune responses to the antigen or to at least one of the antigens • Non-inferiority for responses to any other antigen(s) If primary aim is to enhance safety, studies to demonstrate:

• Superiority for safety (if possible) • Non-inferiority for immune responses (s)

In addition, the clinical section describes various scenarios to be considered for confirmatory clinical studies. These scenarios, together with the expected clinical study approach are summarised in Table 1.

Although scientific progress has given us technology to make better vaccines, against most infectious diseases acceptance of vaccines is driven by public concerns and perceptions. To some extent, the benefits from use of vaccines are now 'assumed' and the risk of reactions to the vaccines are perceived as greater than the risk of the disease [9]. Any vaccine associated reaction leads to high profile news. Within a week of the Dublin conference the evening standard of 27th May 2003 had a front-page article &quot;war vaccines poisoned us&quot; in which it was claimed that British soldiers have developed Iraq syndrome from the vaccines.

Although history has shown that the majority of vaccine associated claims are scientifically unproven, public perception of vaccine safety has an important impact on the development process. The famous pertussis controversy of 1970-1980, which marked the most significant setback for the cause of immunisation [10] in Great Britain, influenced the introduction of acellular DTaP vaccine as a replacement for whole cell DTwP. More recent controversies involve the use of MMR and the mercury based preservative, thiomersal, and their possible association with autism [11]. In the latter case, the controversy may have influenced the introduction of more expensive single-dose vaccines, thus avoiding the need for preservatives. The unproven association between aluminium hydroxide and macrophagic myofasciitis, recently, publicised in France, may well be a driving force in the replacement of existing alum based adjuvanst with new formulations.

Nevertheless, there have been several serious incidents resulting in death or illness of scores of vaccines, when vaccines were first introduced. Often quoted examples include cases of paralytic poliomyelitis caused by inappropriately inactivated killed polio vaccine, tuberculosis caused by the use of a virulent strain of mycobacteria to make BCG, and examples where incomplete detoxification of toxin-derived vaccines were used. These unfortunate incidents have led to the introduction of quality control and safety testing procedures so that such problems are unlikely to happen again [12].

Furthermore, it must be recognised that vaccines can cause adverse effects or reactions. The most frequent reactions are benign and include transient pain, redness and swelling at the site of reaction. However, systemic reactions such as fever, malaise or headache can also be associated with vaccination. Serious reactions are rare and it is often not easy to establish scientifically that an observed association is casual. However, it is known that all vaccines can cause an anaplylaxis reaction, at a frequency of some 1 in 50,000-100,000 recipients [11].

With the introduction of new technologies, regulators are faced with issues that cannot be easily addressed during development, pre-clinical and even clinical studies, using existing models and technologies. Currently, very little is known about the possible modes of action of existing and new adjuvants and even less in known about their possible interactions. It is difficult to generate useful comparative studies in current animal models to adequately provide information on the effectiveness of adjuvants. However, as knowledge of fundamental biological mechanisms increase and genetic engineering becomes applicable to a widening range of species, the construction of more appropriate animal models in which to evaluate new adjuvants is likely to improve the situation. There is currently work to develop relevant infection animals models for pertussis, tuberculosis, HIV and other diseases.

The power of multi-parametric methods for evaluating global changes in expression at all levels (mRNA via transcriptomics, proteins via proteomics, metabolic products via metabonomics) is leading to intense effort to develop novel biomarkers of both toxicity and response for a wide range of endpoints. Whilst such approaches are resource-intensive, albeit costs are declining, and pose formidable challenges in bioinformatics, there is a strong conviction in both the public and private sectors that judicious study design will enable the identification and development of a range of novel biomarkers. These will help in inter-species comparison, particularly from laboratory animals to humans. One of the main advantages of such biomarkers is their sensitivity. It is anticipated that it will be possible to detect effects, indicative of an adverse response, at sub-clinical exposures and hence before any harm ensues in the population.

In addition to a deeper understanding of the basic biology of the immune response, knowledge of the genetic heterogeneity of the population is rapidly increasing. This is giving rise to the concept of genetically-determined individual responsiveness and susceptibility. The extent to which this will impact on the use of adjuvants is presently unclear. However, it might be possible to identify certain genotypes who are at greater risk or who will exhibit a markedly lower response, because of mutations in specific target genes. The various human single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) projects will undoubtedly identify some loci responsible for interindividual variability in immune response. One of the challenges will be to capitalise on such information as it applies to the use of adjuvants.

If progress is to be made in developing new adjuvants it is essential that such novel approaches be embraced. Fundamental to this is adequate validation of both the models and methods to be used. This is not a trivial undertaking. It will also be vital to harmonise the strategies adopted, facilitating inter-laboratory comparisons with appropriate use of standardisation and data sharing. Joint public-private initiatives may have a role to play in this area, given the overall cost of much of this work, it is probable that only through collaborative efforts will real progress be made.</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Antigen delivery systems: immunological and technical issues</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Sesardic</author>
				<author>M Corbel</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Curr Opin Immunol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Vejc Schijns</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Eur J Immunol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Brewer</author>
				<author>M Conacher</author>
				<author>A Satoskar</author>
				<author>H Bluethmann</author>
				<author>J Alexander</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1996</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>General Monograph: Vaccines for Human Use</title>
			<authors/>
			<date>2002</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>CPMP</title>
			<authors/>
			<date>1998</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Note for Guidance on the Pre-clinical, Pharmaceutical and Toxicological Testing of Vaccines</title>
			<authors/>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Note for Guidance on the Clinical Evaluation on New Vaccines</title>
			<authors/>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>EMEA/CPMP/EWP/17/03-Draft</title>
			<authors/>
			<date>2003</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Vaccine</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Ehreth</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2003</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Vaccine</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Baker</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2003</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Vaccine</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Andre</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2003</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Safety of vaccines</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Chen</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
	<reference_dois>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0952-7915(00)00120-5</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1002/eji.1830260915</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0264-410X(02)00623-0</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0264-410X(03)00302-5</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0264-410X(02)00702-8</number>
	</reference_dois>
</document>
