<document>
  <file>./pdf-files/J of Applied Toxicology - 2022 - Rosa - Impact of solid lipid nanoparticles on 3T3 fibroblasts viability and lipid profile .pdf</file>
  <title>Impact of solid lipid nanoparticles on 3T3 fibroblasts viability and lipid profile: The effect of curcumin and resveratrol loading</title>
  <date>Unknown</date>
  <authors>
    <author>Antonella Rosa</author>
    <author>Mariella Nieddu</author>
    <author>Giulia Pitzanti</author>
    <author>Rosa Pireddu</author>
    <author>Francesco Lai</author>
    <author>Maria Cardia</author>
  </authors>
  <abstract>This study focused on the impact in 3T3 fibroblasts of several types of empty and curcumin-and resveratrol-loaded solid lipid nanoparticles (SLN) on cell viability and lipid metabolism in relation to their lipid content and encapsulated drug. SLN, prepared by hot homogenization/ultrasonication, were characterized with respect to size, polydispersity index, and zeta potential. Compritol ® 888 ATO at different concentrations (4%, 5%, and 6% wt/wt) was chosen as lipid matrix while Poloxamer 188 (from 2.2% to 3.3% wt/wt) and Transcutol (TRC; 2% or 4%) were added as nanoparticle excipients. Prepared SLN were able to encapsulate high drug amount (encapsulation efficiency percentage of about 97-99%). All empty SLN did not show cytotoxicity (by MTT assay, at 24 h of incubation) in 3T3 cells independently of the lipid and TRC amount, while a viability reduction in the range 5-11% and 12-27% was observed in 3T3 cells treated with curcumin-loaded and resveratrol-loaded SLN, respectively. SLN without TRC did not affect cell lipid metabolism, independently from the lipid content. Empty and loaded SLN formulated with 4% of Compritol and 4% of TRC significantly affected, after 24 h of incubation at the dose of 5 μl/ml, cell polar lipids (phospholipids and free cholesterol) and fatty acid profile, with respect to control cells. Loaded compounds significantly modulated the impact of the corresponding empty formulation on cell lipids. Therefore, the combined impact on lipid metabolism of SLN and loaded drug should be taken in consideration in the evaluation of the toxicity, potential application, and therapeutic effects of new formulations.</abstract>
  <methods>
    <method>| Materials: Pluronic F68 (Poloxamer 188, P188), CUR, RSV, standards of FA, cholesterol, 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT), 1,2-dipalmitoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 16:0/16:0), 1,2-dioleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 18:1/18:1), 1-palmitoyl-2-oleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 16:0/18:1), 1-oleoyl-2-palmitoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 18:1/16:0), 2-linoleoyl-1-palmitoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 16:0/18:2), 2-arachidonoyl-1-palmitoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 16:0/ 20:4), 1,2-dilinoleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 18:2/18:2), 1,2-dieicosapentaenoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 20:5/20:5), and all solvents (purity &gt; 98%) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Milan, Italy). Compritol ® 888 ATO (esters of behenic acid) and Transcutol ® P (TRC) (Figure 1A) were kindly supplied by Gattefossè. Cell culture materials were purchased from Invitrogen (Milan, Italy). All the other chemicals used in this study were of analytical grade. The formulations obtained were stored at 25 C prior to use and characterized 24 h after preparation. The encapsulation efficiency (EE %) of the SLN was calculated using the following equation:</method>
    <method>| Experimental design for cell treatment: Preliminarily, a series of unloaded SLN formulated with different amounts (4%, 5%, and 6% wt/wt) of Compritol 888 ATO was tested in murine fibroblasts for the evaluation of cell cytotoxicity and lipid profile modulation in relation to their lipid amount to individuate the most biocompatible formulation useful for drug encapsulation. Then a series of SLN prepared with 4% wt/wt of the lipid matrix, different percentages of Transcutol ® P (0, 2, 4% wt/wt), and loaded with CUR and RSV were assessed for cytotoxicity and lipid profile modulation in 3T3 to study whether the nature of the loaded compound could affect the impact of SLN on cells viability and lipid metabolism.</method>
    <method>| Extraction and preparation of cell lipid components: Total lipids were extracted from 3T3 cell pellets by the addition of the mixture CHCl 3 /CH 3 OH/H 2 O 2:1:1 as previously reported (Rosa et al., 2015). Aliquots of the CHCl 3 fraction from each cell sample, containing cell liposoluble compounds, were dried down, dissolved in CH 3 OH, and directly injected into the liquid chromatograph (highperformance liquid chromatography [HPLC]) for the analysis of lipid components (PL and FC) (Rosa et al., 2015(Rosa et al., , 2019) ) and CUR. Another aliquot of the CHCl 3 fraction was subjected to mild saponification for FA separation as reported (Rosa et al., 2015(Rosa et al., , 2019)).</method>
    <method>| SLN characterization: In this study, different empty (unloaded), CUR-loaded, and RSVloaded SLN formulations (Table 1) were prepared by a hot homogenization technique followed by ultrasonication. The concentrations of the different components in SLN formulations were chosen on the basis of a preformulation study (data not shown) and our previous research (Pitzanti et al., 2020)  and RSV formulations was very high (EE% 97-99%) and independent of the TRC concentration (Table 2).</method>
  </methods>
  <full_text>on cell homeostasis and physiological functions and represent indispensable substrates for β-oxidation and ATP production (Ferreri et al., 2016;Maulucci et al., 2016). Following the biosynthesis, desaturase enzymes introduce a methylene group in saturated FA (SFA) leading to the monounsaturated FA (MUFA), while polyunsaturated FA (n-6 and n-3 PUFA) are produced by elongation and desaturation of the essential linoleic (18:2 n-6) and α-linolenic (18:3 n-3) acids, respectively (Ferreri et al., 2016;Maulucci et al., 2016). Free cholesterol, together with phospholipids, is an essential component in the plasma membrane of mammalian cells and plays diverse structural and functional roles (Paukner et al., 2022). Changes in lipid organization (FA and cholesterol) can largely affect membrane functional and biophysical properties (fluidity and lipid rafts organization), severely altering cellular functions such as membrane trafficking, protein dynamics, and signal transduction (Ferreri et al., 2016;Maulucci et al., 2016;Paukner et al., 2022;Santos &amp; Schulze, 2012). These membranerelated effects can cause disease in living organisms (Paukner et al., 2022). FA profile has been considered as a homeostatic and metabolic biomarker in normal and pathological cells (Maulucci et al., 2016). Recent studies have proposed FA ratios as a suitable way to efficiently replace the original FA data set for FA metabolism analysis (Graeve &amp; Greenacre, 2020). Cholesterol and/or FA metabolism represent the target for the treatment of several pathological conditions such as metabolic syndrome (Denisenko et al., 2020), diabetes (Langlois et al., 2021), and cancer (Santos &amp; Schulze, 2012). Targeting altered lipid metabolic pathways (FA biosynthesis and desaturation, phospholipids and cholesterol metabolism, and lipid droplet synthesis) has become a promising anticancer strategy (Liu et al., 2017;Rosa et al., 2019;Santos &amp; Schulze, 2012). Moreover FA, in a free form or incorporated into complex lipids, are crucial to proper functions of the epidermis and its appendages (Lin &amp; Khnykin, 2014), and the alteration of skin lipid composition can lead to several dermatological disorders (Drakou et al., 2021). Several phenolic compounds act through the membranes by interacting with membrane lipids and changing the general lipid membrane biophysical properties (structure, organization, fluidity, and packing), membrane dynamics, and the expression of lipogenic enzymes involved in FA metabolism (Kühn et al., 2018;Reis &amp; de Freitas, 2020;Rosa et al., 2020).

Nanoparticles, a class of functional materials with overall dimensions in the nanoscale range, are amply used in pharmacology and medicine (Dhiman et al., 2021;Faraji &amp; Wipf, 2009). Lipid-based nanoparticles (LN), made from biocompatible and biodegradable lipids, are well tolerated in living systems, and represent important systems for enhanced incorporation of hydrophobic compounds into the lipid matrix (Dhiman et al., 2021;Pizzol et al., 2014;Severino et al., 2012). Among these nanostructures, solid lipid nanoparticles (SLN), characterized for presenting a solid lipid matrix at room temperature and body temperatures, have been extensively used in pharmaceutical and cosmetic formulations (Faraji &amp; Wipf, 2009;Pizzol et al., 2014). SLN are generally regarded as nontoxic, biocompatible, and easy-toproduce formulations and are widely being explored for improving dermal/transdermal and oral delivery of drugs, nutraceuticals, and cosmeceuticals (Dhiman et al., 2021;Faraji &amp; Wipf, 2009;Musielak et al., 2022;Pizzol et al., 2014;Severino et al., 2012). Particularly, SLN main molecular constituents are physiologically compatible lipids (FA, glycerides or other FA esters, sterols, sterol esters, waxes, etc.) and surfactants commonly used as emulsifying agent and food additive (Dhiman et al., 2021;Pizzol et al., 2014;Scioli Montoto et al., 2020).

Plainly, safe, and effective utilization of LN and SLN requires that they do not result in an adverse biological response (Scioli Montoto et al., 2020). LN and SLN cannot be viewed as a simple delivery system but can play an active role in mediating biological effects, affecting viability and cell physiology, in particular lipid metabolism (Falchi et al., 2015;Pitzanti et al., 2020;Rosa et al., 2015). Numerous articles were devoted to exploring the LN and SLN cytotoxic effects (Acevedo-Morantes et al., 2013;Pizzol et al., 2014;Scioli Montoto et al., 2020;Weyenberg et al., 2007) and up-regulation of proinflammatory cytokines (Schöler et al., 2002) in cell systems. Previous studies evidenced the toxicity in mouse 3T3 fibroblasts, J774 macrophages, HaCaT keratinocytes, and red blood cells of SLN formulated with stearic acid (Pizzol et al., 2014;Weyenberg et al., 2007). Remarkably, only a small amount of research was undertaken to investigate the LN and SLN impact on the cell lipid profile (in terms of FA and lipid classes) (Falchi et al., 2015;Pitzanti et al., 2020;Rosa et al., 2015). Previous studies evidenced changes in lipid components (incorporation of oleic acid 18:1 n-9 in the phospholipid and triacylglycerol fractions and lipid droplets accumulation) occurring in human carcinoma HeLa cells when exposed to short-term treatments with monoolein-based cubosomes stabilized by Pluronic F108 (Falchi et al., 2015;Rosa et al., 2015). Moreover, in a preliminary study, we evidenced the effect of SLN loaded with 8-methoxypsoralen in modulating FA and polar lipid profile in fibroblasts, without affecting cell viability (Pitzanti et al., 2020). Therefore, LN should not be considered only as simple carriers for drug delivery, but also as a platform able to modulate specific lipid biosynthetic pathways (Falchi et al., 2015;Rosa et al., 2015). Curcumin (CUR) and resveratrol (RSV) (Figure 1A) are bioactive liposoluble polyphenolic compounds (Goel et al., 2008;Rosa et al., 2014). The dietary polyphenol CUR has been reported to possess a variety of biological and pharmacological activities (anti-inflammatory, antimicrobial, anticarcinogenic, and antioxidant properties).

The natural polyphenol RSV is consumed worldwide as food items and possesses safety profiles with diverse biological and pharmacological actions, including antioxidation, anti-inflammation, antidiabetic, and anticancer activity (Gomes et al., 2020;Gumireddy et al., 2019).

Because of their low water solubility, several studies have been devoted to improving CUR and RSV bioavailability by incorporation in different formulations (liposomes, nanosuspensions, SLN, and nanostructured lipid carriers) (Gumireddy et al., 2019;Sakellari et al., 2021). Moreover, previous studies evidenced the ability of CUR and RSV to affect cell membrane fluidity and FA metabolism (Kühn et al., 2018;Naeini et al., 2019).

In addition to effects on cell viability, the interaction of SLN with cell lipids is an essential focus in assessing and understanding their toxicity and compatibility, because SLN-induced changes in cell lipids can influence biological membrane properties and affect cellular processes. Starting from all these considerations, the aim of this study was to evaluate the simultaneous impact of different types of unloaded and loaded SLN on cell viability and lipid metabolism in relation to their composition (lipid content, penetration enhancer, and encapsulated compounds). SLN were prepared with different amounts of Compritol ® 888 ATO (monoesters, diesters, and triesters of behenic acid 22:0; the structure of glyceryl behenate is reported in Figure 1A) as lipid matrix, Poloxamer 188 (P188) as nanoparticle stabilizer, and Transcutol ® P (TRC) (Figure 1A) as penetration enhancer, excipients amply used in cosmetic and pharmaceutical products for their tolerability (Björklund et al., 2016;Cortés et al., 2021;Devi &amp; Agarwal, 2019). In a previous study, we demonstrated that the use of TRC in a SLN formulation containing 4% of Compritol 888 ATO could enhance the cellular uptake of nanoparticles and cell lipid modulation (Pitzanti et al., 2020). CUR and RSV were chosen as loaded compounds for their high liposolubility, bioactivity, and ability to affect lipid metabolism. Prepared SLN were tested in 3T3 fibroblasts, a normal cell line previously used to assess the toxicity and biocompatibility of empty and loaded SLN (Pitzanti et al., 2020;Pizzol et al., 2014;Weyenberg et al., 2007). Moreover, the mouse fibroblast plasma membrane is considered an excellent model system to study how FA influence the membrane (Ibarguren et al., 2014). The effect of unloaded, CUR-loaded, and RSV-loaded SLN (at 24 h of incubation) on 3T3 cell viability was evaluated by the MTT assay. Changes in lipid components occurring in SLN-treated 3T3 fibroblasts (24 h of incubation) were explored monitoring cell phospholipids (PL), free cholesterol (FC), FA composition, and FA ratio profile.

Pluronic F68 (Poloxamer 188, P188), CUR, RSV, standards of FA, cholesterol, 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide (MTT), 1,2-dipalmitoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 16:0/16:0), 1,2-dioleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 18:1/18:1), 1-palmitoyl-2-oleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 16:0/18:1), 1-oleoyl-2-palmitoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 18:1/16:0), 2-linoleoyl-1-palmitoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 16:0/18:2), 2-arachidonoyl-1-palmitoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 16:0/ 20:4), 1,2-dilinoleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 18:2/18:2), 1,2-dieicosapentaenoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (PC 20:5/20:5), and all solvents (purity &gt; 98%) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (Milan, Italy). Compritol ® 888 ATO (esters of behenic acid) and Transcutol ® P (TRC) (Figure 1A) were kindly supplied by Gattefossè. Cell culture materials were purchased from Invitrogen (Milan, Italy). All the other chemicals used in this study were of analytical grade. The formulations obtained were stored at 25 C prior to use and characterized 24 h after preparation. The encapsulation efficiency (EE %) of the SLN was calculated using the following equation:

Preliminarily, a series of unloaded SLN formulated with different amounts (4%, 5%, and 6% wt/wt) of Compritol 888 ATO was tested in murine fibroblasts for the evaluation of cell cytotoxicity and lipid profile modulation in relation to their lipid amount to individuate the most biocompatible formulation useful for drug encapsulation. Then a series of SLN prepared with 4% wt/wt of the lipid matrix, different percentages of Transcutol ® P (0, 2, 4% wt/wt), and loaded with CUR and RSV were assessed for cytotoxicity and lipid profile modulation in 3T3 to study whether the nature of the loaded compound could affect the impact of SLN on cells viability and lipid metabolism.

Cytotoxicity of SLN was evaluated in 3T3 fibroblasts by the MTT assay (Pitzanti et al., 2020;Rosa et al., 2015). 3T3 cells were seeded in 96-well plates (density of 3 Â 10 4 cells/well) in 100 μl of serumcontaining media. Experiments were carried out 2 days after seeding (at 90% cell confluence). Fibroblasts were treated for 2 and 24 h with different concentrations (1.25, 2.5, and 5 μl/ml, corresponding to 1:800, 1:400, and 1:200 v/v) of SLN formulations in 100 μl of complete fresh medium. We previously used the same concentrations of nanoparticle formulations to evaluate the effect on cell viability of monoolein-based cubosomes stabilized by Pluronic F108 (Falchi et al., 2015;Rosa et al., 2015) and 8-methoxypsoralen-loaded SLN formulated with Compritol 888 ATO (Pitzanti et al., 2020). After incubation, cells were subjected to the MTT test as reported (Pitzanti et al., 2020;Rosa et al., 2015). A preliminary study of SLN cytotoxicity after 2 h of incubation highlighted a decrease of viability in fibroblasts treated with empty SLN, maybe due to a variation in the cell redox status that affects mitochondrial metabolization of MTT, as previously observed at short time of incubation with LN (Falchi et al., 2015). Therefore, 24-h incubation time was chosen for successive studies in 3T3 cells.

3T3 fibroblasts were seeded in T-75 culture flasks at a density of about 10 6 cells/10 ml of complete medium and were used for FA profile modulation experiments at 2 days post-seeding (90% cell confluence). 3T3 fibroblasts were treated with SLN (at a concentration of 5 μl/ml) in fresh medium and incubated at 37 C for 24 h. After treatment, cells were washed with phosphate-buffered saline (PBS), scraped, and centrifuged for 5 min at 1200 g at 4 C. Cell pellets were then separated from supernatants and used for lipid extraction and analyses (Rosa et al., 2015).

Total lipids were extracted from 3T3 cell pellets by the addition of the mixture CHCl 3 /CH 3 OH/H 2 O 2:1:1 as previously reported (Rosa et al., 2015). Aliquots of the CHCl 3 fraction from each cell sample, containing cell liposoluble compounds, were dried down, dissolved in CH 3 OH, and directly injected into the liquid chromatograph (highperformance liquid chromatography [HPLC]) for the analysis of lipid components (PL and FC) (Rosa et al., 2015(Rosa et al., , 2019) ) and CUR. Another aliquot of the CHCl 3 fraction was subjected to mild saponification for FA separation as reported (Rosa et al., 2015(Rosa et al., , 2019)).

Analyses of lipid compounds and CUR extracted from 3T3 cell pellets were carried out with an Agilent Technologies 1100 HPLC (Palo Alto, CA, USA) equipped with a diode array detector (DAD) and an Agilent

Technologies 1260 Infinity ELSD (HPLC-DAD/evaporative light scattering detector [ELSD] system). Separation of PL and FC in cell lipid extracts was performed with an Inertsil ODS-2 column and CH 3 OH as the mobile phase, at a flow rate of 0.7 ml/min, as previously reported (Rosa et al., 2015(Rosa et al., , 2019)). The same chromatographic conditions were used for the analysis of CUR, detected at 450 nm with DAD. Analyses of unsaturated (detected at 200 nm with DAD) and saturated (ELSD detection) free FA, obtained from cell lipid saponification, were carried out with a XDB-C 18 Eclipse column equipped with a Zorbax XDB-C 18 Eclipse guard column (Agilent Technologies), with a mobile phase of 75% of acetonitrile and 25% of acetic acid (0.5%) in water, at a flow rate of 2.3 ml/min (Rosa et al., 2015(Rosa et al., , 2019)). The Agilent OpenLAB

Chromatography data system was used for the recording and integration of the chromatogram data. The identification of cell lipid compounds and CUR was made using standard compounds and conventional UV spectra. Calibration curves of all compounds were constructed using standards and were found to be linear (DAD) and quadratic (ELSD), with correlation coefficients &gt;0.995 (Rosa et al., 2015(Rosa et al., , 2019)). The calibration curve equation, limit of detection (LOD), and correlation coefficient (R 2 ) of the individual FA standards are provided in Table S1.

Data were expressed as a mean ± standard deviation (SD). Evaluation of statistical significance of differences was performed using Graph-

In this study, different empty (unloaded), CUR-loaded, and RSVloaded SLN formulations (Table 1) were prepared by a hot homogenization technique followed by ultrasonication. The concentrations of the different components in SLN formulations were chosen on the basis of a preformulation study (data not shown) and our previous research (Pitzanti et al., 2020)  and RSV formulations was very high (EE% 97-99%) and independent of the TRC concentration (Table 2).

In the first part of the study, empty SLN formulated with different amounts of the lipid matrix and without TRC (empty-TRC 0%-SLN 4%, empty-TRC 0%-SLN 5%, and empty-TRC 0%-SLN 6%) were tested in 3T3 fibroblasts for the evaluation of their impact on cell viability and lipid profile in relation to the lipid content.

Figure S1 shows the viability (expressed as percentage of the control) measured in control 3T3 fibroblasts (0) and cells treated for 2 h (Figure S1A) and 24 h (Figure S1B) with various aliquots (1.25, 2.5, and 5 μl/ml) of empty SLN prepared with different amounts of Compritol (4%, 5%, and 6%). The treatment with all empty SLN formulations induced, after 2 h-incubation, a significant cytotoxic effect in 3T3 cells from the dose of 2.5 μl/ml, and a cell viability reduction, with respect to control cells, in the range 26-29% was observed at 5 μl/ml. However, SLN prepared with different amounts of Compritol ® 888 ATO were not toxic in 3T3 cells at 24-h incubation time (Figure S1B) and cell viability measured at the maximal tested dose (5 μl/ml) ranged from 94% to 98%. Starting from the consideration that the SLN cytotoxicity observed at short time of incubation (2 h) could be due to a variation in the cell redox status that affects mitochondrial metabolization of MTT (Falchi et al., 2015), a 24 h-incubation time was chosen for successive studies in 3T3 cells.

Unloaded SLN prepared with different amounts of lipid matrix were then tested in 3T3 cells to assess their effects after 24-h incubation on cell lipid composition (main polar lipid classes and total FA profile). Figure 2 shows the chromatographic profiles (Figure 2A) and percentage area values (Figure 2B) of polar lipid compounds, mainly constituted by PL and FC, of 3T3 control cells and cells treated for 24 h with Compritol ® 888 ATO (4%, 5%, and 6%) (at 5 μl/ml) obtained by HPLC-ELSD analysis. Polar lipid profiles of control 3T3 were characterized by a peak of FC and two main peaks of PL, corresponding to saturated/monounsaturated PL (S/M-PL) and polyunsaturated PL (P-PL). Standard mixtures of phosphatidylcholines (S/M-PL and P-PL), and FC were used to assign the chromatographic region for each lipid class, as previously reported (Rosa et al., 2015(Rosa et al., , 2020)). Cell polar lipids were separated on the basis of ECN (=CNÀ2n, where CN is the number of acyl group carbons and n is the number of double bonds) (Rosa et al., 2015(Rosa et al., , 2020)). The 24-h treatment of 3T3 cells with unloaded SLN prepared with different amounts of Compritol ® 888 ATO (4%, 5%, and 6%) did not significantly affect cell lipid profile, independently from the lipid content. A similar slight decrease in the percentage amount of P-PL (in the range 8.1-9.1%) and an increase in the percentage of S/M-PL (in the range 1.9-4.3%) were observed in cell treated with unloaded SLN with respect to control cells.

Figure 3 shows the chromatographic profile, values (expressed as μg/plate and percentage of total FA) of unsaturated and saturated FA, and their ratios measured in control 3T3 cells. Control fibroblasts showed an FA composition characterized by a high level of oleic acid 18:1 n-9 (17.7 ± 5.2 μg/plate, 25.4% of total FA), palmitic acid 16:0 (12.9 ± 2.6 μg/plate, 18.8%), and stearic acid 18:0 (12.6 ± 2.8 μg/ plate, 18.4%), while linoleic acid 18:2 n-6 (6.6 ± 1.7 μg/plate, 9.4%) and arachidonic acid 20:4 n-6 (6.2 ± 1.7 μg/plate, 8.9%) represented the most abundant FA among polyunsaturated FA (PUFA), followed by docosahexaenoic acid 22:6 n-3 (Figure 3B,C). Values of ratios among main FA determined in 3T3 cells were 8.4 ± 3.4, 4.6 ± 0.9, 3.6 ± 1.2, 2.9 ± 0.4, 2.8 ± 0.6, and 1.6 ± 0.1 for 16:0/16:1 n-7, 18:1/22:6 n-3, 16:0/22:6 n-3, 18:1 n-9/20:4 n-6, 18:1 n-9/20:4 n-6, 18:1 n-9/18:2 n-6, and 20:4 n-6/22:6 n-3, respectively (Figure 3D). The incubation of fibroblasts with SLN prepared with different amounts of Compritol ® 888 ATO (empty-TRC 0%-SLN 4%, empty-TRC 0%-SLN 5% and empty-TRC 0%-SLN 6%) did not induced marked changes in the FA amounts (Figure 4A) and their ratios (Figure 4B) with respect to untreated-control cells.

The increase in the percentage amount of the lipid matrix did not induce a significant change in 3T3 cell viability and lipid profile; therefore, the empty-TRC 0%-SLN 4% was then selected as starting formulation, subsequently modified by adding different TRC percentages (Pitzanti et al., 2020) and loading the two bioactive liposoluble polyphenolic compounds CUR and RSV (Figure 1). The concentration of 0.1% for CUR and RSV was chosen on the basis of a preliminary screening conducted to find the concentration of polyphenols that Figure 5 shows the viability (expressed as percentage of the control) (MTT assay) measured in control 3T3 fibroblasts and cells treated for 24 h with different aliquots (1.25, 2.5, and 5 μl/ml) of empty and CUR-and RSV-loaded SLN 4% (with TRC 0%, 2%, and 4%). Treatment with pure compounds CUR and RSV, tested at the same dose present in SLN, is also reported. No significant changes in cell viability, with respect to control cells, were observed in 3T3 fibroblasts treated with unloaded SLN with TRC (TRC 2%-SLN 4% TRC 4%-SLN 4%) (Figure 5A). CUR-loaded SLN with different amounts of TRC (0%, 2%, and 4%) (Figure 5B) did not show a marked toxic effect on 3T3 cells; however, a viability reduction in the range 5-10% was observed at the different tested concentrations. A statistically significant viability reduction (≤10%) was observed for all CUR-loaded SLN at 5 μl/ml; however, percentages of cell viability above 90% are generally considered as noncytotoxicity. RSV-loaded SLN with 0%, 2%, and 4% of TRC (Figure 5C) showed a certain cytotoxic effect, higher than other SLN and pure RSV. Reduction of viability (in the range 21-27% at 5 μl/ml) was similar in cells treated with all types of RSV-loaded SLN, independently from TRC amount. Therefore, unloaded and loaded SLN with 4% TRC were chosen for the evaluation of the impact on lipid profile. Pure RSV slightly affected cell lipid profile, and RSV-treated cells showed a lipid profile very similar to that of control cells.

Values of the main FA (expressed as percentage of total FA) and their ratios measured in control 3T3 fibroblasts and cells treated for

Values of the main fatty acids (FA) (expressed as percentage of total FA) (A) and their ratios (B) measured in control 3T3 fibroblasts (Ctrl) and cells treated for 24 h with 5 μl/ml of empty solid lipid nanoparticles (SLN) prepared with different amounts of Compritol ® 888 ATO (4%, 5%, and 6%). Data are presented as mean ± SD (n = 6). No significant differences were observed among samples (oneway ANOVA and Bonferroni post hoc test). [Colour figure can be viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com] 24 h with 5 μl/ml of unloaded (empty-TRC 4%-SLN 4%) and loaded SLN (CUR-TRC 4%-SLN 4% and RSV-TRC 4%-SLN 4%) are shown in evident for 16:0 (p &lt; 0.05) and 18:0 (p &lt; 0.01), coupled to a significant increase in the level of monounsaturated FA (MUFA), manly represented by 18:1 n-9 (p &lt; 0.001 vs. untreated cells), and to a minor extent, polyunsaturated FA (PUFA). Differences with respect to control cells were also observed in the values of FA ratios (Figure 7B).

The loading of SLN with CUR and RSV significantly modulated the impact of nanoparticles on cells. An evident, but not significant, decrease of SFA (16:0 and 18:0) was also observed in CUR-loaded SLN, coupled to a small increase in the PUFA level (mainly 20:4 n-6 and 18:2 n-6). Significant changes, with respect to unloaded SLN, were observed for 16:0/18:2 n-6, 16:0/20:4 n-6 and 16:0/22:6 n-3 ratios. Cells treated with RSV-TRC 4%-SLN 4% showed an FA profile significantly different from that of fibroblasts treated with unloaded SLN and similar to control cells. However, some differences were observed in the FA ratios (16:0/18/2 n-6, 16:0/20:4-n-6, and 16:0/22:6 n-3) with respect to control cells, with values similar to unloaded SLN-treated cells, confirming the modulatory effect of RSVloaded SLN on lipid components.

A preliminary study was performed to determine the CUR absorption in 3T3 cells. Figure S2 shows the chromatographic profiles and

UV spectra (at the wavelength of 450 nm) of peak measured in the chloroform fractions obtained from control 3T3 cells and cells treated for 24 h with 0.5 μg/ml of pure CUR and 0.5 μl/ml of CUR-TRC 4%-SLN 4%. The presence of the phenol in cell extract was assessed by comparison with the retention time and spectrum of the CUR standard. 3T3 cells treated with pure CUR did not show, in our experimental condition, the compound in cell pellets, while a CUR value of 6.0 ± 2.3 μg/plate was measured in the pellet of 3T3 fibroblasts treated with CUR-loaded SLN (Figure S2).

SLN can be used to deliver drugs orally, topically, or via inhalation (Faraji &amp; Wipf, 2009;Battaglia &amp; Ugazio, 2019). The knowledge of SLN interaction with living systems is essential in the perspective of implementing nanotechnologies in a safe way (Severino et al., 2012). physiological compounds leading to the metabolic pathways, minimizing adverse side effects (Musielak et al., 2022;Severino et al., 2012).

In this study, several empty and CUR-or RSV-loaded SLN formulations were physiochemically characterized and tested in 3T3 murine fibroblasts for the evaluation of their impact on cell viability and lipid profile in relation to the lipid content and incorporated compound.

All the empty formulations did not show cytotoxic effect in 3T3 cells at long-term exposure (24 h of incubation), independently of the lipid and TRC amount; therefore, this incubation time was chosen for all cell viability assessments. Components (Compritol ® , TRC and Poloxamer 188) of empty SLN are safe and well-tolerated compounds, used in many cosmetic and pharmaceutical products for skin and/or oral delivery (Björklund et al., 2016;Cortés et al., 2021;Devi &amp; Agarwal, 2019).

In our experimental conditions, CUR and RSV loading in the lipid matrix determined an increase of SLN size and PI values, without significant effects on the nanoparticle surface charge. EE% values of 97-99% were measured for all CUR and RSV formulations, and it is reasonable to believe that this high loading capacity is due to both the high hydrophobicity of the loaded molecules and the imperfect crystalline structure produced by Compritol ® during re-crystallization, which reduces drug expulsion from the lipid matrix. (Müller et al., 2000;Righeschi et al., 2016). The results obtained in this work confirmed that the higher encapsulation efficiency and long-term physical stability of the SLN have been assured by the following component composition: Compritol 888 ATO 4%, Transcutol 0-4%, Poloxamer 188 2.2%, and drug 0.1%. (Pitzanti et al., 2020).

All CUR-loaded SLN formulated with different amounts of TRC (0%, 2%, and 4%) showed a slight toxic effect on 3T3 fibroblasts, with a statistically significant viability reduction (≤10%) observed at the highest tested dose (5 μl/ml). Previous study showed minimal cytotoxicity of a series of CUR-loaded solid lipid-polymer hybrid nanoparticles (SLPN) in human epithelial Caco-2 cells, used as model to study the CUR cellular uptake (Wang et al., 2018). RSV loading significantly improved SLN cytotoxic effect, independently from the TRC amount, with a viability reduction in the range 21-27% at the highest tested dose. Some toxicity was previously reported for RSV-loaded SLN and nanostructured lipid carriers in an immortalized cell line of human keratinocytes (HaCaT) (Rocha et al., 2017).

Empty SLN without TRC did not affect phospholipids and FA profile of treated 3T3 cells, which showed values like control cells, indicating a very slight ability of SLN to interact with cell membranes, independently from the lipid matrix amount. The incorporation of TRC into SLN (empty-TRC 4%-SLN 4%) increased their capacity to interact with cells, modulating phospholipids and FA profile of fibroblasts with respect to control cells after 24-h incubation, without affecting cell viability. TRC is a penetration enhancer, a safe and well-tolerated solvent/vehicle used in the formulation or manufacturing process of pharmaceuticals, cosmetics, and food additives (Björklund et al., 2016;Sullivan et al., 2014). The observed significant increase in the cell level of S/M-PL and MUFA, mainly 18:1 n-9, after the treatment with empty-TRC 4%-SLN 4% could be probably ascribable to an enhanced cellular uptake of nanoparticles (Panariti et al., 2012) helped by TRC, coupled to the metabolism of behenic acid (22:0), the main FA of Compritol ® (Devi &amp; Agarwal, 2019). After SLN membrane interaction/ uptake, behenic acid, derived from the lipolysis of its glyceryl derivatives, was possibly metabolized/oxidized by fibroblasts into the shorter-chain FA 18:1 n-9, which was then used for the synthesis of phospholipids. A previous study reported the cellular uptake of SLN composed of Compritol ® 888ATO as lipid material (Yuan et al., 2008).

In humans, dietary behenic acid is poorly absorbed because of its low bioavailability compared with other FA (Cater &amp; Denke, 2001); therefore, the modulation of lipid profile observed in 3T3 cells after treatment with empty-TRC 4%-SLN 4% is a clear indication of SLN uptake/interaction with plasma membrane (Panariti et al., 2012).

The loading of SLN with CUR and RSV significantly modulated the impact of nanoparticles on cell lipids with respect to empty SLN.

CUR-TRC 4%-SLN 4% induced a noticeable increase in FC cell level, a less marked decrease of SFA and increase of 18:1 n-9 than empty-TRC 4%-SLN 4%, coupled to a small increase in the PUFA level. CUR is a hydrophobic compound, and previous studies evidenced its ability to accumulate in cell membranes (partition into lipid bilayers), leading to an alteration of the membrane environment and particular membrane properties as the fluidity and the phase transition temperature (Duda et al., 2020;Leite et al., 2018). CUR acts through the membranes by changing the general lipid membrane organization and exerts its antitumor activity in cancer cells by inhibiting the expression of enzymes involved in lipid metabolism like FA synthase and stearoyl-CoA desaturase (Naeini et al., 2019). In this study, we assessed the modulatory effect on lipid profile of CUR-loaded SLN at the concentration of 5 μl/ml approximately corresponding, considering the EE% value of 97-99%, to CUR 13 μM. Previous study demonstrated that at concentrations of the order of 100 μM, CUR exhibits destabilization effects on membranes, but at much lower concentrations it modulates the function of membrane proteins (Leite et al., 2018). Taking into consideration the differences observed between the effect on lipid profile of empty-TRC 4%-SLN 4% and CUR-TRC 4%-SLN 4%, the modulatory effect on the lipid components observed in 3T3 fibroblasts treated with CUR-loaded SLN was possibly the result of the synergistic/combined impact of the lipid matrix and pure CUR on cell lipid metabolism. Previous studies evidenced synergistic effects of nanostructured lipid carriers with the encapsulated compound (Beloqui et al., 2016;Huguet-Casquero et al., 2020).

The presence of CUR in the cell pellets of 3T3 fibroblasts treated with CUR-TRC 4%-SLN 4%, corresponding approximately to 12% of the applied amount, confirmed the uptake of CUR-loaded SLN and the interaction/penetration of the phenol in cell membranes whereas in our experimental conditions, CUR was not detected in cells treated with the pure compound.

Also, the treatment of 3T3 cells with RSV-loaded SLN modulated PL and FA profile differently from unloaded and CUR-loaded SLN. Cell treatment with RSV-TRC 4%-SLN 4% induced, with respect to unloaded SLN, a significant increase in the amount of P-PL and FC, together to a decrease in the S/M-PL level. Cells treated with RSV-TRC 4%-SLN 4% showed an FA profile more similar to control cells than unloaded SLN-treated cells; however, some differences were observed in the profile of FA ratios versus controls, confirming the modulatory effect of RSV-loaded SLN on lipid components. FA ratios data have been indicated as a suitable data set that effectively replaces the original data set for a quantitative comparative evaluation of cell FA composition, being irrespective of the number of FA included in the studies and the units of quantitative measurement (Graeve &amp; Greenacre, 2020). In our experimental conditions, the 5 μl/ml concentration of RSV-loaded SLN used for lipid profile modulation corresponded, considering the EE% of 97-99%, approximately to an RSV concentration of 21 μM. A previous study demonstrated the impact of RSV on FA metabolism in cultured hepatocytes (Kühn et al., 2018). Incubation of human HepG2 cells with RSV 40 μM induced a significant reduction in the levels of MUFA (16:1 n-7, 18:1 n-9, 18:1 n-7, and 20:1 n-9), coupled to an increase in SFA levels (mainly stearic acid), due to a modulatory activity on the expression of enzymes involved in lipid metabolism like desaturases (Kühn et al., 2018). Moreover, RSV showed the ability to modify PL and FA composition in cancer cell lines after 24-h treatment, at the dose of 80 and 200 μM in MCF-7 and MDA-MB-231 cells, respectively (Gomes et al., 2020). As observed for CUR-loaded SLN, the effect of RSV-loaded SLN on 3T3 cell lipid profile was maybe the consequence of the synergistic impact (Beloqui et al., 2016;Huguet-Casquero et al., 2020) of the lipid matrix and pure RSV on cell lipid metabolism, taking into consideration the difference observed in the lipid modulatory effect with respect to the empty-TRC 4%-SLN 4%.

Taken together, our results showed the impact of CUR-loaded and RSV-loaded SLN on lipid metabolism, with a slight toxic effect on cell viability, more marked in the presence of RVS as encapsulated drug. The PL and FA modification observed in 3T3 cells after SLN treatment is physicochemically relevant. Alterations in cell membrane lipid composition, like changes in the ratio between SFA and MUFA chains of the PL, can directly influence the biophysical properties of biological membranes, deeply altering fluidity, the lipid raft thermodynamic properties, and microdomain organization (Hagen et al., 2010). Changes in lipid composition influence many cellular functions such as signal transduction, cell adhesion, lipid trafficking, ion channel function, receptor mobility/interaction, and the biological response to the drugs (Hagen et al., 2010). Therefore, the evaluation of the modulatory effect on cell lipids is essential in the study of biocompatibility of new SLN formulations. In addition, SLN formulated with a specific combination of the lipid matrix and loaded compound could represent a potential platform to target lipid metabolism in those pathological conditions characterized by altered lipid metabolic pathways.

SLN are generally considered nontoxic and highly compatible but could affect cell viability and lipid profile. In this study, we demonstrated the impact of CUR-and RSV-loaded SLN on lipid metabolism (cell polar lipids and fatty acid profile), with a slight toxic effect on cell viability. The incorporation of TRC into SLN (empty-TRC 4%-SLN 4%)

increased their capacity to interact with cells. Empty-TRC 4%-SLN 4%, CUR-TRC 4%-SLN 4%, and RSV-TRC 4%-SLN 4% showed the capacity to modify the lipid profile/metabolism of 3T3 cells due to the SLN uptake; however, this effect changed in relation to the encapsulated compound. The lipid modulatory effect of SLN in cells has important biochemical and physiological implications because changes in the cell lipid composition can influence biological membrane properties and affect several cellular processes. Our results highlighted how the combined impact on lipid metabolism of SLN and loaded drug should be taken into consideration in the evaluation of toxicity, potential application, and therapeutic effects of new formulations. This study represents an initial step for future studies that could explore more in depth the dose-response relationship of CUR-loaded-and RSV-loaded SLN on lipid profile modulation for the assessment of their biocompatibility and potential therapeutic application in lipid disorders.

Abbreviations: CUR, curcumin; RSV, resveratrol; SLN, solid lipid nanoparticles.EE% ¼ ðdrug concentration after purification= drug concentration before purificationÞ Â 1002.4 | Cell culture

Abbreviations: CUR, curcumin; RSV, resveratrol; SLN, solid lipid nanoparticles.EE% ¼ ðdrug concentration after purification= drug concentration before purificationÞ Â 100

Abbreviations: CUR, curcumin; RSV, resveratrol; SLN, solid lipid nanoparticles.

10991263, 2023, 2, Downloaded from https://analyticalsciencejournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/jat.4379 by Cochrane Latvia, Wiley Online Library on [17/03/2026]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License</full_text>
  <references>
    <reference>
      <title>Evaluation of the cytotoxic effect of camptothecin solid lipid nanoparticles on MCF7 cells</title>
      <authors>
        <author>C Acevedo-Morantes</author>
        <author>M Acevedo-Morantes</author>
        <author>D Suleiman-Rosado</author>
        <author>J Ramírez-Vick</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2013</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Lipid nano-and microparticles: An overview of patent-related research</title>
      <authors>
        <author>L Battaglia</author>
        <author>E Ugazio</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2019</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>A comparative study of curcuminloaded lipid-based nanocarriers in the treatment of inflammatory bowel disease</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Beloqui</author>
        <author>P Memvanga</author>
        <author>R Coco</author>
        <author>S Reimondez-Troitiño</author>
        <author>M Alhouayek</author>
        <author>G Muccioli</author>
        <author>M Alonso</author>
        <author>N Csaba</author>
        <author>M De La Fuente</author>
        <author>V Préat</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2016</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>The effects of polar excipients transcutol and dexpanthenol on molecular mobility, permeability, and electrical impedance of the skin barrier</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Björklund</author>
        <author>Q Pham</author>
        <author>L Jensen</author>
        <author>N Knudsen</author>
        <author>L Nielsen</author>
        <author>K Ekelund</author>
        <author>T Ruzgas</author>
        <author>J Engblom</author>
        <author>E Sparr</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2016</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Behenic acid is a cholesterol-raising saturated fatty acid in humans</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Cater</author>
        <author>M Denke</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2001</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Nonionic surfactants for stabilization of polymeric nanoparticles for biomedical uses</title>
      <authors>
        <author>H Cortés</author>
        <author>H Hernández-Parra</author>
        <author>S Bernal-Chávez</author>
        <author>M Prado-Audelo</author>
        <author>I Caballero-Florán</author>
        <author>F Borbolla-Jiménez</author>
        <author>M González-Torres</author>
        <author>J Magaña</author>
        <author>G Leyva-G Omez</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2021</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Lipid-induced mechanisms of metabolic syndrome</title>
      <authors>
        <author>Y Denisenko</author>
        <author>O Kytikova</author>
        <author>T Novgorodtseva</author>
        <author>M Antonyuk</author>
        <author>T Gvozdenko</author>
        <author>T Kantur</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Some multifunctional lipid excipients and their pharmaceutical applications</title>
      <authors>
        <author>R Devi</author>
        <author>S Agarwal</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2019</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Lipid nanoparticles as carriers for bioactive delivery</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Dhiman</author>
        <author>A Rajendra</author>
        <author>S Bhupesh</author>
        <author>K Harsha</author>
        <author>G Kulkarni</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2021</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Revealing the correlation between altered skin lipids composition and skin disorders</title>
      <authors>
        <author>K Drakou</author>
        <author>A Tsianni</author>
        <author>F Vrani</author>
        <author>V Kefala</author>
        <author>E Rallis</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2021</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Effects of curcumin on lipid membranes: An EPR spin-label study</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Duda</author>
        <author>K Cygan</author>
        <author>A Wisniewska-Becker</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Effects of monoolein-based cubosome formulations on lipid droplets and mitochondria of HeLa cells</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Falchi</author>
        <author>A Rosa</author>
        <author>A Atzeri</author>
        <author>A Incani</author>
        <author>S Lampis</author>
        <author>V Meli</author>
        <author>C Caltagirone</author>
        <author>S Murgia</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2015</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Nanoparticles in cellular drug delivery</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Faraji</author>
        <author>P Wipf</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2009</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Fatty acids in membranes as homeostatic, metabolic and nutritional biomarkers: Recent advancements in analytics and diagnostics</title>
      <authors>
        <author>C Ferreri</author>
        <author>A Masi</author>
        <author>A Sansone</author>
        <author>G Giacometti</author>
        <author>A Larocca</author>
        <author>G Menounou</author>
        <author>R Scanferlato</author>
        <author>S Tortorella</author>
        <author>D Rota</author>
        <author>M Conti</author>
        <author>S Deplano</author>
        <author>M Louka</author>
        <author>A Maranini</author>
        <author>A Salati</author>
        <author>V Sunda</author>
        <author>C Chatgilialoglu</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2016</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Curcumin as "curecumin": From kitchen to clinic</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Goel</author>
        <author>A Kunnumakkara</author>
        <author>B Aggarwal</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2008</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Resveratrol modifies lipid composition of two cancer cell lines</title>
      <authors>
        <author>L Gomes</author>
        <author>L Viana</author>
        <author>J Silva</author>
        <author>C Mermelstein</author>
        <author>G Atella</author>
        <author>E Fialho</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>The selection and analysis of fatty acid ratios: A new approach for the univariate and multivariate analysis of fatty acid trophic markers in marine pelagic organisms</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Graeve</author>
        <author>M Greenacre</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Preparation, characterization, and in vitro evaluation of curcumin-and resveratrol-loaded solid lipid nanoparticles</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Gumireddy</author>
        <author>R Christman</author>
        <author>D Kumari</author>
        <author>A Tiwari</author>
        <author>E North</author>
        <author>H Chauhan</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2019</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>An allostatic control of membrane lipid composition by SREBP1</title>
      <authors>
        <author>R Hagen</author>
        <author>S Rodriguez-Cuenca</author>
        <author>A Vidal-Puig</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2010</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Encapsulation of oleuropein in nanostructured lipid carriers: Biocompatibility and antioxidant efficacy in lung epithelial cells</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Huguet-Casquero</author>
        <author>M Moreno-Sastre</author>
        <author>T L Opez-Méndez</author>
        <author>E Gainza</author>
        <author>J Pedraz</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>The effect of natural and synthetic fatty acids on membrane structure, microdomain organization, cellular functions and human health</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Ibarguren</author>
        <author>D Escribá</author>
        <author>P</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2014</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Resveratrol modulates desaturase expression and fatty acid composition of cultured hepatocytes</title>
      <authors>
        <author>G Kühn</author>
        <author>K Pallauf</author>
        <author>C Schulz</author>
        <author>M Birringer</author>
        <author>B Diaz-Rica</author>
        <author>S De Pascual-Teresa</author>
        <author>G Rimbach</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2018</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Impact of moderate exercise on fatty acid oxidation in pancreatic β-cells and skeletal muscle</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Langlois</author>
        <author>A Forterre</author>
        <author>M Pinget</author>
        <author>K Bouzakri</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2021</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Cholesterol modulates curcumin partitioning and membrane effects</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Leite</author>
        <author>D Martins</author>
        <author>V Fazani</author>
        <author>M Vieira</author>
        <author>Dos Santos</author>
        <author>M Cabrera</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2018</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Fatty acid transporters in skin development, function and disease</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Lin</author>
        <author>D Khnykin</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2014</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Targeting lipid metabolism of cancer cells: A promising therapeutic strategy for cancer</title>
      <authors>
        <author>Q Liu</author>
        <author>Q Luo</author>
        <author>A Halim</author>
        <author>G Song</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2017</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Fatty acid-related modulations of membrane fluidity in cells: Detection and implications</title>
      <authors>
        <author>G Maulucci</author>
        <author>O Cohen</author>
        <author>B Daniel</author>
        <author>A Sansone</author>
        <author>P Petropoulou</author>
        <author>S Filou</author>
        <author>A Spyridonidis</author>
        <author>G Pani</author>
        <author>M De Spirito</author>
        <author>C Chatgilialoglu</author>
        <author>C Ferreri</author>
        <author>K Kypreos</author>
        <author>S Sasson</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2016</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Solid lipid nanoparticles (SLN) for controlled drug delivery-A review of the state of the art</title>
      <authors>
        <author>R Müller</author>
        <author>K Mäder</author>
        <author>S Gohla</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2000</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Synthesis and potential applications of lipid nanoparticles in medicine</title>
      <authors>
        <author>E Musielak</author>
        <author>A Feliczak-Guzik</author>
        <author>I Nowak</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Antitumor effects of curcumin: A lipid perspective</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Naeini</author>
        <author>A Momtazi</author>
        <author>M Jaafari</author>
        <author>T Johnston</author>
        <author>G Barreto</author>
        <author>M Banach</author>
        <author>A Sahebkar</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2019</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>The effect of nanoparticle uptake on cellular behavior: Disrupting or enabling functions? Nanotechnology</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Panariti</author>
        <author>G Miserocchi</author>
        <author>I Rivolta</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2012</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Cholesterol in the cell membrane-an emerging player in atherogenesis</title>
      <authors>
        <author>K Paukner</author>
        <author>I Králová Lesná</author>
        <author>R Poledne</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Transcutol ® P containing SLNs for improving 8-methoxypsoralen skin delivery</title>
      <authors>
        <author>G Pitzanti</author>
        <author>A Rosa</author>
        <author>M Nieddu</author>
        <author>D Valenti</author>
        <author>R Pireddu</author>
        <author>F Lai</author>
        <author>M Cardia</author>
        <author>A Fadda</author>
        <author>C Sinico</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Influence of surfactant and lipid type on the physicochemical properties and biocompatibility of solid lipid nanoparticles</title>
      <authors>
        <author>C Pizzol</author>
        <author>F Filippin-Monteiro</author>
        <author>J Restrepo</author>
        <author>F Pittella</author>
        <author>A Silva</author>
        <author>P Alves De Souza</author>
        <author>A Machado De Campos</author>
        <author>T Creczynski-Pasa</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2014</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>When polyphenols meet lipids: Challenges in membrane biophysics and opportunities in epithelial lipidomics</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Reis</author>
        <author>V De Freitas</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Enhanced curcumin permeability by SLN formulation: The PAMPA approach</title>
      <authors>
        <author>C Righeschi</author>
        <author>M Bergonzi</author>
        <author>B Isacchi</author>
        <author>C Bazzicalupi</author>
        <author>P Gratteri</author>
        <author>A Bilia</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2016</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>In vitro cytotoxicity evaluation of resveratrol-loaded nanoparticles: Focus on the challenges of in vitro methodologies</title>
      <authors>
        <author>V Rocha</author>
        <author>C Marques</author>
        <author>J Figueiredo</author>
        <author>A Gaio</author>
        <author>P Costa</author>
        <author>J Sousa Lobo</author>
        <author>I Almeida</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2017</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Prenylation preserves antioxidant properties and effect on cell viability of the natural dietary phenol curcumin</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Rosa</author>
        <author>A Atzeri</author>
        <author>M Deiana</author>
        <author>M Melis</author>
        <author>A Incani</author>
        <author>A Minassi</author>
        <author>B Cabboi</author>
        <author>G Appendino</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2014</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Dietary zerumbone from shampoo ginger: New insights into its antioxidant and anticancer activity</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Rosa</author>
        <author>D Caprioglio</author>
        <author>R Isola</author>
        <author>M Nieddu</author>
        <author>G Appendino</author>
        <author>A Falchi</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2019</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>The dietary flavonoid eupatilin attenuates in vitro lipid peroxidation and targets lipid profile in cancer HeLa cells</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Rosa</author>
        <author>R Isola</author>
        <author>F Pollastro</author>
        <author>P Caria</author>
        <author>G Appendino</author>
        <author>M Nieddu</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Monooleinbased cubosomes affect lipid profile in HeLa cells</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Rosa</author>
        <author>S Murgia</author>
        <author>D Putzu</author>
        <author>V Meli</author>
        <author>A Falchi</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2015</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Formulation design, production and characterisation of solid lipid nanoparticles (SLN) and nanostructured lipid carriers (NLC) for the encapsulation of a model hydrophobic active</title>
      <authors>
        <author>G Sakellari</author>
        <author>I Zafeiri</author>
        <author>H Batchelor</author>
        <author>F Spyropoulos</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2021</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Lipid metabolism in cancer</title>
      <authors>
        <author>C Santos</author>
        <author>A Schulze</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2012</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Effect of lipid matrix and size of solid lipid nanoparticles (SLN) on the viability and cytokine production of macrophages</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Schöler</author>
        <author>H Hahn</author>
        <author>R Müller</author>
        <author>O Liesenfeld</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2002</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Solid lipid nanoparticles for drug delivery: Pharmacological and biopharmaceutical aspects</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Scioli Montoto</author>
        <author>G Muraca</author>
        <author>M Ruiz</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Current state-of-art and new trends on lipid nanoparticles (SLN and NLC) for oral drug delivery</title>
      <authors>
        <author>P Severino</author>
        <author>T Andreani</author>
        <author>A Macedo</author>
        <author>J Fangueiro</author>
        <author>M Santana</author>
        <author>A Silva</author>
        <author>E Souto</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2012</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>A review of the nonclinical safety of Transcutol ® , a highly purified form of diethylene glycol monoethyl ether (DEGEE) used as a pharmaceutical excipient</title>
      <authors>
        <author>D Sullivan</author>
        <author>S Gad</author>
        <author>M Julien</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2014</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Solid lipid-polymer hybrid nanoparticles prepared with natural biomaterials: A new platform for oral delivery of lipophilic bioactives</title>
      <authors>
        <author>T Wang</author>
        <author>M Bae</author>
        <author>J Lee</author>
        <author>Y Luo</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2018</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Cytotoxicity of submicron emulsions and solid lipid nanoparticles for dermal application</title>
      <authors>
        <author>W Weyenberg</author>
        <author>P Filev</author>
        <author>D Van Den Plas</author>
        <author>J Vandervoort</author>
        <author>K De Smet</author>
        <author>P Sollie</author>
        <author>A Ludwig</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2007</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Cellular uptake of solid lipid nanoparticles and cytotoxicity of encapsulated paclitaxel in A549 cancer cells</title>
      <authors>
        <author>H Yuan</author>
        <author>J Miao</author>
        <author>Y Du</author>
        <author>J You</author>
        <author>F Hu</author>
        <author>S Zeng</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2008</date>
    </reference>
  </references>
</document>