<document>
  <file>./pdf-files/jmbfs_10916_Sabry.pdf</file>
  <title>IN-VITRO PREPARATION, CHARACTERIZATION AND APPLICATION OF SOLID LIPID NANOPARTICLES AND CHITOSAN NANOPARTICLES EITHER SINGLY OR LOADED WITH CIPROFLOXACIN ANTIBIOTIC AS NANODRUG DELIVERY SYSTEMS</title>
  <date>Unknown</date>
  <authors>
    <author>Sara Sabry</author>
    <author>Mohammed Nagib</author>
    <author>A Hasaneen</author>
    <author>Aya Omer</author>
    <author>Ahmed El-Sayed</author>
    <author>Ahmed Ateya</author>
  </authors>
  <abstract>Unknown</abstract>
  <methods>
    <method>Characterization of CSNPs and SLNPs either singly or loaded with CIP Morphological characterization: The size and shape of the prepared CSNPs and SLNPs either singly or loaded with ciprofloxacin antibiotic were detected by using a JEOL 1010 transmission electron microscope at 80 kV (JEOL, EM unit, Mansoura University). All nanomaterial's solutions were sonicated for two minutes to avoid the aggregation of nanoparticles and for better dispersion of the particles on the carbon-coated grid. One drop of the prepared nanosolutions was put the grid, which was then left to dry aat room temperture nd undergoes TEM examination. Both size and shape of the prepared nanoengineered materials were directly determined from the resulting figures by using an Image-ProPlus 4.5 software (Corradini et al., 2010;Helal et al., 2022 a).</method>
    <method>Chemical characterization: According to the method of Frederick ( 2009), the values of zeta potential of both CSNPs and SLNPs either singly or in-combination with ciprofloxacin antibiotic were measured on zeta-sizer instruments (Malvern Instruments ltd, EM unit, Mansoura University, Mansoura, Egypt). The zeta cell was firstly washed by dist. H2O, ethanol, and then cleaned with dist. H2O again and finally dried with an appropriate stream of nitrogen to remove any residual solvents. The cell was then covered to prevent contamination. By using a syringe, about one cm 3 of each nanosolutions was injected carefully into the cell and three runs were performed for each sample.</method>
    <method>Preparation of different concentrations of ciprofloxacin: Different concentrations of ciprofloxacin dissolved in distilled water were added to both SLNPs emulsion and CSNPs solution with stirring for 6 hours to obtain final antibiotic concentrations 2.0, 0.2, 0.02 and 0.002 mg ml -1 .</method>
    <method>Pre-cultural preparation of Salmonella enteritidis: Bacterial growth suspension was prepared at concentration equivalent to 0.8 mg ml -1 . About 1-2 colonies of Salmonella enteritidis (AC: ON764247) obtained from a culture collection of Microbiology laboratory, Faculty of Veterinary, Mansoura University, were taken by sterile cotton swab to sterilized tube containing 5 cm 3 of sterile distilled water and then shaken.</method>
  </methods>
  <full_text>In recent years, improper use of antibiotics has led to the development of multidrug resistant (MDR) bacteria and the loss of effectiveness of existing antibiotics. Antibiotic-resistant bacteria can be transmitted to human through the food supply chain (Nair et al., 2018). The infection with antibiotic-resistant bacteria can cause serious diseases that can not be treated with regular treatment of conventional antibiotics (Pelyuntha et al., 2022). Salmonella is one of the most commen pathogenic bacteria associated with human. Infection can be associated with the consumption of contaminated food and water. Animals, especially poultry are the primary carriers for these bacterial strain (Obukhovska, 2013). Currently, Salmonella has been reported to be resistant to several antibiotics which can pose a threat to public health and food safety (Wang et al., 2019). Ciprofloxacin is a member of the fluoroquinolone drugs which has been proven to be a strong and broad-spectrum antibiotic with high efficacy against a wide range of bacterial infections, especially Salmonella infection (Brunner and Zeiler, 1988;Jain and Banerjee, 2008). Ciprofloxacin is a poorly water-soluble drug so, its bioavailability can be improved by the nanoformulation of the drug (Savjani et al., 2012). According to the World Health Organization, antimicrobial resistance considerds one of the greatest threats to global health, and the world needs to develop new strategies and tools to overcome this problem (Ling et al., 2018;WHO, 2021). In this context, nanotechnology can offer a real solution to this problem by the development of drug delivery systems which has offered new opportunities to enhance the efficacy of various therapeutic drugs (Qin et al., 2017). Recently, there are a great interest in the development of nanotechnology for drug delivery. Because nanotechnology provides a suitable way to deliver both of drugs with small molecular weight and macromolecules like proteins, peptides and genes to several cells and tissues and protect them from enzymatic degradation (Butowska et al., 2022; Helal et al., 2022 a). Nanoparticles can be used as drug delivery systems because of their unique advantages such as non-toxicity, biodegradability, and sufficent stability to be kept for long periods. One of these developed drug delivery systems, solid lipid nanoparticles (SLNPs) have attacted special attention as promising nanocarriers for controlled drug delivery because they combine between the advantages of polymeric nanoparticles, lipid emulsions, and liposomes simultaneously avoiding some of their negative aspects (Geszke-Moritz and Moritz, 2016; Helal et al., 2022 a, b). Solid lipid nanoparticles are colloidal particles with a submicron size of diameter between 50 and 1000 nm (Ekambaram et al., 2012;Helal et al., 2022 a). They have several advantages of low toxicity, high biocompatibility, high stability, biodegradability and noticeable capacity to bind with both lipophilic and hydrophilic compounds. Additionally, they also can control the release of the incorporated drug and chemically protect the compound and these can be achieved by simple and cheap large-scale production (Bayón-Cordero et al., 2019). Chitosan nanoparticles (CSNPs) have been used as a convenient carrier for drugs and genes to improve their transduction in the cells because of their unique properties, including biodegradability, biocompatibility and low toxicity as reported in different studies (Chopra et al., 2014, Csaba and Alonso, 2014, Helal et al., 2022 a). However, the efficiency of the antimicrobial activity of chitosan nanoparticles depends on the type of targeted microorganism and the antimicrobial activity mechanisms are related to the physicochemical properties of chitosan nanoparticles (Rozman et al., 2019). The antimicrobial activities of CSNPs have been extensively investigated in different in-vitro and in-vivo studies against several microorganisms such as bacteria, fungi, yeasts and algae. In pharmaceutical applications, CSNPs were used as antimicrobial coating to promote wound healing, prevent infections and reduce infectious disease. Besides, CSNPs have also been exhibited significant inhibitory effect on foodborne microorganisms, particularly on fruits and vegetables. It is noteworthy that CSNPs can also be used to deliver antimicrobial drugs, which further enhance the efficiency and stability of the antimicrobial agent Engineered nanomaterials have been used increasingly in the medecinal field to improve drug delivery efficacy in the healthcare field because of their unique physicochemical characteristics. In the current study, chitosan nanoparticles (CSNPs) were synthesized by polymerization of methacrylic acid in chitosan solution. Meanwhile, solid lipid nanoparticles (SLNPs) were synthesized by using the hot homogenization method. Chitosan nanoparticles and solid lipid nanoparticles either singly or loaded with ciprofloxacin (CIP) antibiotic were characterized using morphological, physical, chemical, electrical and biological methods. Both chitosan nanoparticles and solid lipid nanoparticles had spherical shape meanwhile, the size was range from 50.96 nm to 108.42 nm for chitosan nanoparticles and 107 nm for solid lipid nanoparticles, and retained the properties of the drug after loading. The size of both nanomaterials was increased after loading with ciprofloxacin by 145.5% and 49.66 %, respectively. Both prepared nanomaterials offered controlled drug release after 12 hrs Antibacterial activity of solid lipid nanoparticles and chitosan nanoparticles either singly or loaded with ciprofloxacin was evaluated against Salmonella enteritidis as a Gram-ve bacterial strain. The minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) of each prepared nanodrugs against Salmonella enteritidis was determined as 0.0002 mg ml -1 and the antibacterial effect of either nanomaterials, antibiotic singly or loaded with antibiotic as nanodrug delivery systems showed significant variable higher increase in inhibition rate of the pathogen. The following sequence of the treatment: CSNPs-CIP; 2.0 mg ml -1 &gt; SLNPs-CIP; 2.0 mg ml -1 &gt; control (CIP; 2.0 mg ml -1 ) &gt; SLNPs-CIP; 0.2 mg ml -1 &gt; CSNPs-CIP; 0.002 mg ml -1 was displayed with respect to percent change inhibition effect on bacterial pathogen. In conclusion, we recommended an intensive work on the biosafety of using nanomaterials as nanodrug delivery systems for treatment of infectious diseases.

The objective of our study was focused on preparation, characterization and comparing between two different nanoengineered materials; solid lipid nanoparticle and chitosan nanoparticles as nanocarriers for ciprofloxacin antibiotic as an auspicious strategy to overcome or, at least, reduce antibacterial resistance. Under magnetic stirring for 12 hours, chitosan powder (0.2 g) was dissolved in aqueous solution of polymethacrylic acid (0.5 cm 3 ). Potassium persulfate (0.05 g) was then added to the previous solution and then heated to 70 °C while stirring continuously for another one hour until the solution became transparent. The final step is necessary to stop the reaction by cooling the prepared solution in an ice bath. Meanwhile, solid lipid nanoparticles were prepared via hot homogenization method according to Gazi and Krishnasailaja (2018) method. Firstly, about five grams of glycerol monostearate (GMS) lipid was heated in a glass beaker at 70 ℃ untill completely melting Approximately one gram of lipophilic surfactant such as soya lecithin was added to the previous melted lipid. The mixture was mixed well and put in a water bath at 70 ℃ until complete homogeneity to form the lipid phase. Secondly, 1.5 cm 3 of hydrophilic surfactant such as Tween 80 was added in another beaker, and by using distilled water the volume of the mixture was completed to 100 cm 3 and with continuous stirring, the mixture was heated at 70 ℃ for 15 minutes to form aqueous surfactant phase. The lipid phase mixture was added to the aqueous surfactant drop-wisely. Then, the final mixture was homogenized at 15000 rpm for 5 minutes in a graduate highly speed automatic homogenizer and sonicated for 15 minutes by using automatic high-speed sonicator. The prepared solid lipid nanoparticles (SLNPs) emulsion was stored stably at room temperature until use.

The loading of ciprofloxacin on both CSNPs solution and SLNPs emulsion surfaces was performed accorging to the method of Hasaneen et al. (2014,2022). Under magnetic stirring for six hours at room temperature, 20 cm 3 of ciprofloxacin suspension (2.0 mg ml -1 ) was added to 30 cm 3 of each CSNPs solution and SLNPs emulsion.

The size and shape of the prepared CSNPs and SLNPs either singly or loaded with ciprofloxacin antibiotic were detected by using a JEOL 1010 transmission electron microscope at 80 kV (JEOL, EM unit, Mansoura University). All nanomaterial's solutions were sonicated for two minutes to avoid the aggregation of nanoparticles and for better dispersion of the particles on the carbon-coated grid. One drop of the prepared nanosolutions was put the grid, which was then left to dry aat room temperture nd undergoes TEM examination. Both size and shape of the prepared nanoengineered materials were directly determined from the resulting figures by using an Image-ProPlus 4.5 software (Corradini et al., 2010;Helal et al., 2022 a).

According to the method of Frederick ( 2009), the values of zeta potential of both CSNPs and SLNPs either singly or in-combination with ciprofloxacin antibiotic were measured on zeta-sizer instruments (Malvern Instruments ltd, EM unit, Mansoura University, Mansoura, Egypt). The zeta cell was firstly washed by dist. H2O, ethanol, and then cleaned with dist. H2O again and finally dried with an appropriate stream of nitrogen to remove any residual solvents. The cell was then covered to prevent contamination. By using a syringe, about one cm 3 of each nanosolutions was injected carefully into the cell and three runs were performed for each sample.

According to the method of using the method of Trykowski et al. (2010) and Hasaneen et al. (2017), FTIR measurements for the prepared nanomaterials either singly or loaded with ciprofloxacin were performed by using 0.1 g of spectrally pure potassium bromide and approximately three mg of each nanosolution was pressed under vacuum for 10 minutes to form a disc (greyish color) which was analyzed by using a Fourier transform spectrometer (NICOLET IS10 FT-IR instrument) at Faculty of Science, Mansoura University, Mansoura, Egypt.

for ciprofloxacin release from the surface of the prepared nanomaterials were carried out by using the dissolution test. In a beaker containing 50 cm 3 of phosphate buffer solution (pH 6.8), a dialysis bag (redeveloped cellulose membrane; 12-14 KD molecular weight cut-off) containing CIP-based nanomaterials was immersed and the system was maintained under moderate stirring (100 rpm) at 37°C±1. For continuous 12 hours, approximately 5 cm 3 of the release medium was withdrawn every hour and tested for drug release and replaced by 5 cm 3 of preheated fresh phosphate buffer (37°C±1). The cumulative drug levels of ciprofloxacin were calculated by using a UV spectrophotometer at 300 nm via comparing the amount of ciprofloxacin in the extract with the blank. The Cumulative drug of ciprofloxacin was calculated based on a pre-made calibration curve.

Different concentrations of ciprofloxacin dissolved in distilled water were added to both SLNPs emulsion and CSNPs solution with stirring for 6 hours to obtain final antibiotic concentrations 2.0, 0.2, 0.02 and 0.002 mg ml -1 .

Bacterial growth suspension was prepared at concentration equivalent to 0.8 mg ml -1 . About 1-2 colonies of Salmonella enteritidis (AC: ON764247) obtained from a culture collection of Microbiology laboratory, Faculty of Veterinary, Mansoura University, were taken by sterile cotton swab to sterilized tube containing 5 cm 3 of sterile distilled water and then shaken.

The Minimum inhibitory concentration test is used for antimicrobial drug (ciprofloxacin) against Salmonella enteritidis using a several tubes of sterile MacConkey broth with different dilutions of CIP (2.0 to 0.00625 mg/ml) which were specifically inoculated with 100 μl of standardized inoculum. The inoculated tubes were then incubated at 37°C for 24 hours. The lowest ciprofloxacin concentration that did not induce visible growth compared to the control tube was recorded as the MIC (Hassan et al., 2009). Meanwhile, the minimum bacterial concentration (MBC) was determined by preparing MacConkey solid medium that poured into sterilized plates. After medium solidification, 50 μl of standardized bacterial inoculum was inoculated, wells were created using sterile cork poorer (diameter 1cm) and were filled with 100 μl of different CIP dilutions that were prepared. Dilution that produced no single bacterial colony on a solid medium was taken as MBC (Kabir et al., 2005).

According to the method of Balouiri et al. (2016), agar well diffusion method was used to determine the antibacterial activity of each CIP, CSNPs, SLNPs, CSNPs-CIP and SLNPs-CIP. 15 cm 3 of sterile MacConkey agar medium was poured into sterilized petri dishes and allowed to solidify. Approximately 0.1 cm 3 of the bacterial suspension was poured and uniformly spreaded with sterile cotton swab. After the absorption of inoculum by medium, wells were made by a sterile cork poorer (1 cm diameter) and filled with 100 μl of CIP, CSNPs, SLNPs, CSNPs-CIP and SLNPs-CIP. The dishes were kept at room temperature for 45 minutes to allow proper diffusion of the prepared nano-drugs in the medium and then were incubated at 37°C for 24 hours. Inhibition of bacterial growth was measured as inhibition zone diameters (mm)

This research focuses on the development of experimental stuides to explore nanosystems as new strategies for control delivery of the drug based on nanocarriers that premit to ameliorate and maintain the antibiotic effect in drug- Here, it is noteworthy that we succeeded to modify the pervious reported preparation methods and develop a simple synthetic method that allowed us to prepare either chitosan nanoparticles from raw bulk chitosan or solid lipid nanoparticles from tween 80 as the hydrophilic surfactant and soya lecithin as the lipophilic surfactant, easily and inexpensively. Both prepared nanomaterials either singly or loaded with antibiotic were characterized morphologically by using Transmission electron microscop (TEM). It is clearly observed from the TEM micrographs that both CSNPs and SLNPs had a spherical shape. The minimum diameter of the CSNPs is range from 50.96 nm to 108.42 nm (Figure 1A). Meanwhile, the size of SLNPs was approximately 107 nm (Figure 1C). The size of both CSNPs and SLNPs was increased with the addition of ciprofloxacin as antibacterial agent as showed in Figure 1B and 1D, respectively. The maximum percent ratio of increase in the mean diameter was approximately 302 % and 340.81 % with the addition of CIP to each CSNPs solution and SLNPs emulsion, respectively. the preparation of SLNPs can be acheived by the hot homogenization method, at a temperature higher than the melting point of lipid which may be responsible for lowering the size of particles due to the viscosity decreasing of the inner phase. Increasing the number of either cycles or the homogenization pressure often responsible for the increase in particles size due to high kinetic energy of the part. As mentioned above in figure 1 B and 1D, the size of both CSNPs and SLNPs was increased with the addition ciprofloxacin antibiotic. This is due to the presence of much more primary chitosan amino acids and PMAA OH -groups that combined with either other ions or other molecules through ion exchange or simple chelation creating several chemical interaction with these ions, thus increasing the stability of nanomaterials and prevent aggregation

Zeta potential values are significant factor to the physical stability of nanomaterials as the higher value displays better stability of the dispersion. So, to confirm the stability of the prepared SLNPs and CSNPs either singly or loaded with CIP antibiotic, zeta potential (z p ζ) for were measured. Low potential values means that attractive force are greater than repulsive forces and the solution will agglomerate or coagulate due to Van Der-Waal attraction force between particles. But when zeta potential value is high either negative or positive, the solution is electrically stable (Hanaor et al., 2012;Hasaneen et al., 2014). Table 1 showed that SLNPs either singly or in combination with CIP had high negative zeta potential values, meanwhile CSNPs and CSNPs-CIP had highly positively values meaning that both CSNPs and SLNPs either singly or loaded with CIP were highly stable. In general, it is thought of interest to mention that SLNPs either singly or loaded with CIP antibiotic were more stable than the prepared CSNPs either singly or loaded with CIP also. The positive CSNPs zeta potential values either singly or loaded with CIP is due to the cationic characteristics of chitosan. These positive values proved that CSNPs had a positive surface charge, and high values indicating that these nanoparticles were stable. On the other hand, solid lipid nanoparticles exhibited highly negative zeta potential values which indicated that the prepared emulsion whad a negative surface charge and were stable. These negative charge can be attributed to soya lecithin as well as tween 80's hydrogels which can also produce a very small negative charges (Zardini, et al., 2018). The loading of CIP on the surface of both CSNPs and SLNPs change the values of zeta potential due to the loading of additional charges on the surface of both prepared nanomaterials (Hanaor et al., 2012;Hasaneen et al., 2014). Zeta potential of nanocarriers signifcanlty improved as a result of CIP loading on the surface of CSNPs and SLNPs (Table 1).

Determination of the prepared nanomaterials structure was carried out by FTIR analysis to confirm the formation of nanoparticles by examining the presence of functional groups of both CSNPs and SLNPs. The FTIR spectra of the nanosolutions investigated in this study was represented in Figure 2, 3, 4 and 5.

Depending on the procedures of synthesis, CSNPs and SLNPs may contain various functional groups such as -NH4, C=O, N-N,-OH and -COOH. Figure 2 shows that the characteristic peaks of chitosan are NH2 bending vibration at 3571 cm -1 indicating the stretching vibration of the -NH2 and -OH groups and C=O stretching vibration at 1723 cm -1 which indicated that chitosan was ionicaly interacted with poly methacrylic acid (PMAA) to form the nanoparticles. Figure 3  Meanwhile, SLNPs FTIR spectra were presented in Figure 4 which showed the presence of absorption peak at 3314 cm -1 , 2918 cm -1 and 2850 cm -1 that represents -OH, (-CH3) and -(CH2) stretching vibrations, respectively. The peak at approximately 1733 cm -1 was the stretching vibration of the COOH group. In Figure 5, new bands not detected in the FTIr specrum of CIP -SLNPs indicated that there were no any chemical reactions between the lipid and drug. In SLNPs FTIR spectrum, the vibration bands of (-OH) at 3314 cm -1 and (-CH3) at 2918cm     In-vitro drug release study Weng et al. (2020) reported that drug can be released by diffusion which involves swelling of matrix due to water penetration into system then the solid lipid could converted into the rubbery matrix and finally the drug could be diffused from the swollen rubbery matrix. In CSNPs, the acidic pH can promote the electrostatic attraction between NH4 + and water molecules, dissolution of chitosan polymer causes the erosion of nanoparticles matrix and rapid drug release (Kulpreechanan and Sorasitthiyanukarn, 2020). When nanoparticles swelled significantly and even dispersed rapidly, quick drug release can be achieved (Shu and Zhu, 2002).

The cumulative drugs release from CSNPs might indicate that drug was released faster at lower pH (Sabra and Billa, 2020). A promising outcome of the results is the slow and incomplete release of ciprofloxacin. This suggests higher cellular uptake of CSNPs and SLNPs through bacterial cell wall.

Figure 6 Ciprofloxacin release profile from nanosuspensions.

Ciprofloxacin antibacterial activity was compared with those of ciprofloxacin loaded with both CSNPs and SLNPs against Salmonella enteritidis. The different concentrations of CIP showed variable broad activity against the growth of the pathogen. The pathogen was most sensitive at concentration of 0.2 mg ml -1 . This concentration showed optimum antibiotic activity. Both MIC and MBC values were recorded as 0.02 and 0.002 mg ml -1 , respectively as showed in Figure 7. 1; 0.2 mg ml -1 , 2; 0.02 mg ml -1 , 3; 0.002 mg ml -1 , 4; 0.0002 mg ml -1 , 5; 0.00002 mg ml -1 ).

The antibacterial activity of CSNPs and SLNPs and its loaded form with CIP were evaluated against Salmonella enteritidis as Gram-ve bacteria. Administration of ciprofloxacin antibiotic singly or loaded on CSNPs and SLNPs as drug delivery system into the culture media of Salmonella enteritidis induced variable inhibition zones of the growth of the pathogen. Figure 8 and Table 2 showed that the antibacterial activity of CSNPs and SLNPs loaded with ciprofloxacin were increased with the increasing of the absorbed dose for Gram-ve bacterium. The results confirmed that the zone of inhibition with both SLNPs and CSNPs which were free of CIP was lower than those of loaded ones. In relation to the antibacterial activity of CIP, CSNPs and SLNPs, the zone of inhibition of chitosan nanoparticles of Salmonella enteritidis was enhanced with loading of antibiotic by 13.63% for 2.0 mg ml -1 as shown in Table 2 andFigure 8. Meanwhile, the zone of inhibition of SLNPs loaded with ciprofloxacin of Salmonella enteritidis was enhanced to 11.5 mm and increased by the increment of the antibiotic concentration by 4.45% for 2.0 mg ml -1 .

Table 2 Antibacterial activity of chitosan nanoparticles (CSNPs) and solid lipid nanoparticles (SLNPs) either singly or loaded with ciprofloxacin (CIP) against Salmonella enteritidis.

Figure 8 Antibacterial Activity of both chitosan nanoparticles and solid lipid nanoparticles either singly or loaded with ciprofloxacin (1; 0.2 mg ml -1 , 2; 0.02 mg ml -1 , 3; 0.002 mg ml -1 , S; 2.0 mg ml -1 , A; SLNPs, B; CSNPs).

The valuable and new data obtained in the present study (Figure 8 and Table 2) showed that the administration of CSNPs and SLNPS loaded with ciprofloxacin antibacterial as nano-drug delivery systems led to variable increases and decreases in its activity by a ratio of 13.63 % and 4.45%, respectively. Thus, CSNPs loaded with CIP is might be considered as an influential nanodrug delivery system for inhibition of the growth of Salmonella enteritidis pathogenic bacteria. The decreasing in MIC levels may be attributed to the inhibition of bacterial growth which resulted from more penetration of drug loaded on nanocarriers into the bacterial cell. For this connection, Hasaneen et al. (2022) reported that nanoformulations can be used as a controlled release system prolonging the half-life of the antibiotic payload, reducing the antibiotics toxicity, improving their pharmacokinetics, reducing the period of administration and increasing the therapeutic index.

The antibacterial activity of CSNPs singly against Gram-ve strain exhibited low activity, this might be due to the inhibitory effect of chitosan nanoparticles at high doses so the increased antibacterial activity of ciprofloxacin loaded on CSNPs, could not be due to the antimicrobial effect of CSNPs alone. The negative charge of the cell wall of Salmonella leading to more CSNPs-CIP adsorbed and higher inhibitory effect against the pathogenic bacteria ( 9.0 -18.18% CIP 0.02 mg ml -1 ) 6.5 -40.90% CIP (0.002 mg ml -1 ) 3.0 -72.72% SLNPs singly 3.0 -72.72% CSNPs singly 4.0 -63.63% CSNPs-CIP (2.0 mg ml -1 ) 12.5 13.63% CSNPs-CIP (0.2 mg ml -1 ) 9.5 -13.63% CSNPs-CIP (0.02 mg ml -1 ) 6.0 -45.45 % CSNPs-CIP (0.002 mg ml -1 ) 10.0 -9.09% SLNPs-CIP (2.0 mg ml -1 ) 11.5 4.45% SLNPs-CIP (0.2 mg ml -1 ) 10.5 -4.45% SLNPs-CIP (0.02 mg ml -1 ) 7.25 -31.81% SLNPs-CIP (0.002 mg ml -1 ) 8.5 -22.72%

of CSNPs. The most widely known mechanism of antimicrobial activity is the electrostatic interaction between the bacterial negatively charged cell membranes and the positively charged amino groups of glucosamine of chitosan nanoparticles. This interaction initiates a widespread change on the cell surface and causes a modification in the permeability of bacterial membrane which sequentially induce osmotic imbalance and efflux of intracellular substances that finally result in cell death (Raafat et al., 2008). Solid lipid nanoparticles are considered an auspicious nanocarrier for controlled delivery of drug and being a good alternative to liposomes. They have many special properties such as low toxicity, high biodegradability, stability, biocompatibility and the notable potential to combine with both hydrophilic and lipophilic compounds. Furthermore, they can control the release of the incorporated drugs and chemically protects them. This suggests a high cellular uptake of SLNPs through the bacterial cell wall. This approach can lead to a significant reduction in the CIP dose and therefore reduction of all dosedependent side effects

The promising results of our study: in-vitro preparation and characterization of solid lipid nanoparticles and chitosan nanoparticles either singly or loaded with ciprofloxacin antibiotic, optimization of drug, evaluation of the activity of nanodrug delivery systems, could pave the way for developing effective treatment for the diseases induced by Salmonella enteritidis and suggest promising useful insights into novel nanodrug delivery systems represented by nanochitosanciprofloxacin drug delivery system and nano-solid lipid-ciprofloxacin drug delivery system. This fact was confirmed by further studies including molecular, biochemical and pathological good need of further studies of application in-vivo.</full_text>
  <references>
    <reference>
      <title>Preparation, characterization and antibacterial properties of cyanoethyl chitosan/cellulose acetate polymer blended films</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Abou-Zeid</author>
        <author>A Waly</author>
        <author>N Kandile</author>
        <author>A Rushdy</author>
        <author>M El-Sheikh</author>
        <author>H Ibrahim</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2011</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Enhancement of ciprofloxacin activity by incorporating it in solid lipid nanoparticles</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Alarifi</author>
        <author>S Massadeh</author>
        <author>M Al-Agamy</author>
        <author>M Al Aamery</author>
        <author>A Al Bekairy</author>
        <author>A Yassin</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Diethylmethyl chitosan as an antimicrobial agent: synthesis, characterization and antibacterial effects</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Avadi</author>
        <author>A Sadeghi</author>
        <author>A Tahzibi</author>
        <author>K Bayati</author>
        <author>M Pouladzadeh</author>
        <author>M Zohuriaan-Mehr</author>
        <author>M Rafiee-Tehrani</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2004</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Methods for in vitro evaluating antimicrobial activity: A review</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Balouiri</author>
        <author>M Sadiki</author>
        <author>S Ibnsouda</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2016</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Application of solid lipid nanoparticles to improve the efficiency of anticancer drugs</title>
      <authors>
        <author>L Bayón-Cordero</author>
        <author>I Alkorta</author>
        <author>L Arana</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2019</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Oral ciprofloxacin treatment for Salmonella typhimurium infection of normal and immunocompromised mice</title>
      <authors>
        <author>H Brunner</author>
        <author>H Zeiler</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1988</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Doxorubicin-conjugated siRNA lipid nanoparticles for combination cancer therapy</title>
      <authors>
        <author>K Butowska</author>
        <author>X Han</author>
        <author>N Gong</author>
        <author>R El-Mayta</author>
        <author>R Haley</author>
        <author>L Xu</author>
        <author>W Zhong</author>
        <author>W Guo</author>
        <author>K Wang</author>
        <author>M Mitchell</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Box-Behnken Designed Fluconazole Loaded Chitosan Nanoparticles for Ocular Delivery</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Chopra</author>
        <author>R Marwaha</author>
        <author>D Kaushik</author>
        <author>H Dureja</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2014</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>A preliminary study of the incorporation of NPK fertilizer into chitosan nanoparticles</title>
      <authors>
        <author>E Corradini</author>
        <author>M Demoura</author>
        <author>L Mattoso</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2010</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Biodegradable polymer nanoparticles as protein delivery systems</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Csaba</author>
        <author>M Alonso</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2014</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Preparation of chitosan nanoparticles using methacrylic acid</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Demoura</author>
        <author>F Aouda</author>
        <author>L Mattoso</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2008</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Effect of molecular weight and ionic strength on the formation of polyelectrolyte complexes based on poly (methacrylic acid) and chitosan</title>
      <authors>
        <author>C Devasconcelos</author>
        <author>P Bezerril</author>
        <author>D Dos-Santos</author>
        <author>T Dantas</author>
        <author>M Pereira</author>
        <author>J Fonseca</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2006</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Solid lipid nanoparticles: a review</title>
      <authors>
        <author>P Ekambaram</author>
        <author>A Sathali</author>
        <author>K Priyanka</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2012</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Measuring zeta potential of nanoparticles</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Frederick</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2009</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Preparation &amp; evaluation of paracetamol solid lipid nanoparticles by hot homogenization method</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Gazi</author>
        <author>A Krishnasailaja</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2018</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Solid lipid nanoparticles as attractive drug vehicles: Composition, properties and therapeutic strategies</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Geszke-Moritz</author>
        <author>M Moritz</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2016</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>The effects of carboxylic acids on the aqueous dispersion and electrophoretic deposition of ZrO2</title>
      <authors>
        <author>D Hanaor</author>
        <author>M Michelazzi</author>
        <author>C Leonelli</author>
        <author>C Sorrell</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2012</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Preparation, optimization, characterization and antimicrobial activity of chitosan and calcium nanoparticles loaded with Streptomyces rimosus extracted compounds as drug delivery systems</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Hasaneen</author>
        <author>M Abou-Dobara</author>
        <author>S Nabih</author>
        <author>M Mousa</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Preparation of chitosan nanoparticles for loading with NPK fertilizer</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Hasaneen</author>
        <author>H Abdel-Aziz</author>
        <author>D El-Bialy</author>
        <author>A Omer</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2014</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Evaluation of the P-glycoprotein (Abcb1) affinity status of a series of morphine analogs: Comparative study with meperidine analogs to identify opioids with minimal P-glycoprotein interactions</title>
      <authors>
        <author>H Hassan</author>
        <author>S Mercer</author>
        <author>C Cunningham</author>
        <author>A Coop</author>
        <author>N Eddington</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2009</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Preparation, characterization and properties of three different nanomaterials either alone or loaded with nystatin or fluconazole antifungals</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Helal</author>
        <author>H Abdel-Aziz</author>
        <author>M El-Zayat</author>
        <author>M Hasaneen</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>In vitro efficacy of antifungal activities either singly or loaded on nanomaterials, as new and novel drug delivery systems on the growth of Alternaria alternata and Botrytis fabae fungal pathogens</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Helal</author>
        <author>H Abdel-Aziz</author>
        <author>M El-Zayat</author>
        <author>M Hasaneen</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Comparison of ciprofloxacin hydrochloride-loaded protein, lipid, and chitosan nanoparticles for drug delivery</title>
      <authors>
        <author>D Jain</author>
        <author>R Banerjee</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2008</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Molecular evidence supporting the portal theory: a causative link between visceral adiposity and hepatic insulin resistance</title>
      <authors>
        <author>M Kabir</author>
        <author>K Catalano</author>
        <author>S Ananthnarayan</author>
        <author>S Kim</author>
        <author>G Van Citters</author>
        <author>M Dea</author>
        <author>R Bergman</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2005</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Degradable controlled-release polymers and polymeric nanoparticles: mechanisms of controlling drug release</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Kamaly</author>
        <author>B Yameen</author>
        <author>J Wu</author>
        <author>O Farokhzad</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2016</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>New surfacemodified solid lipid nanoparticles using N-glutaryl phosphatidylethanolamine as the outer shell</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Kashanian</author>
        <author>A Azandaryani</author>
        <author>K Derakhshandeh</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2011</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors />
      <date>Unknown</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Recent advances in non-conventional antimicrobial approaches for chronic wound biofilms: have we found the 'chink in the armor'?</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Kaushik</author>
        <author>S Kadam</author>
        <author>S Shai</author>
        <author>A Shahane</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2019</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Evaluation of in-vitro release kinetics of capsaicin-loaded chitosan nanoparticles using DDsolver</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Kulpreechanan</author>
        <author>F Sorasitthiyanukarn</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Effects of monocarboxylic acids and potassium persulfate on preparation of chitosan nanoparticles</title>
      <authors>
        <author>E Kusrini</author>
        <author>N Shiong</author>
        <author>Y Harahap</author>
        <author>Y Yulizar</author>
        <author>R Arbianti</author>
        <author>A Pudjiastuti</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2015</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Tilmicosinand florfenicol-loaded hydrogenated castor oil-solid lipid nanoparticles to pigs: Combined antibacterial activities and pharmacokinetics</title>
      <authors>
        <author>Z Ling</author>
        <author>L Yonghong</author>
        <author>L Junfeng</author>
        <author>Z Li</author>
        <author>L Xianqiang</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2018</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>A prospective comparison of octyl cyanoacrylate tissue adhesive and suture for the closure of head and neck incisions</title>
      <authors>
        <author>J Maw</author>
        <author>J Quinn</author>
        <author>G Wells</author>
        <author>Y Ducic</author>
        <author>P Odell</author>
        <author>A Lamothe</author>
        <author>P Brownrigg</author>
        <author>T Sutcliffe</author>
        <author>J Otolaryngol</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1997</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Nanoemulsion: A novel drug delivery tool</title>
      <authors>
        <author>R Mishra</author>
        <author>G Soni</author>
        <author>R Mishra</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2014</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Potential of chitin/chitosan-bearing materials for uranium recovery: an interdisciplinary review</title>
      <authors>
        <author>R Muzzarelli</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2011</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Antibiotic-resistant Salmonella in the food supply and the potential role of antibiotic alternatives for control</title>
      <authors>
        <author>D Nair</author>
        <author>K Venkitanarayanan</author>
        <author>J Kollanoor</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2018</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>The natural reservoirs of Salmonella Enteritidis in populations of wild birds</title>
      <authors>
        <author>O Obukhovska</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2013</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Broad lytic spectrum of novel Salmonella phages on ciprofloxacin-resistant Salmonella contaminated in the broiler production chain</title>
      <authors>
        <author>W Pelyuntha</author>
        <author>A Sanguankiat</author>
        <author>A Kovitvadhi</author>
        <author>K Vongkamjan</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2022</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Drug selfdelivery systems for cancer therapy</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Qin</author>
        <author>A Zhang</author>
        <author>S Cheng</author>
        <author>L Rong</author>
        <author>X Zhang</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2017</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Insights into the mode of action of chitosan as an antibacterial compound</title>
      <authors>
        <author>D Raafat</author>
        <author>K Vonbargen</author>
        <author>A Haas</author>
        <author>H Sahl</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2008</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Nanoemulsion: A novel approach for lipophilic drugs -a review</title>
      <authors>
        <author>B Reddy</author>
        <author>S Debnath</author>
        <author>M Babu</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2013</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Potential Antimicrobial Applications of Chitosan Nanoparticles (ChNP)</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Rozman</author>
        <author>W Tong</author>
        <author>C Leong</author>
        <author>W Tan</author>
        <author>M Hasanolbasori</author>
        <author>S Abdullah</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2019</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Gastrointestinal delivery of APIs from chitosan nanoparticles</title>
      <authors>
        <author>R Sabra</author>
        <author>N Billa</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Physico-chemical characterization of interactions between erythromycin and various film polymers</title>
      <authors>
        <author>N Sarisuta</author>
        <author>M Kumpugdee</author>
        <author>B Muller</author>
        <author>S Puttipipatkhachorn</author>
      </authors>
      <date>1999</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Drug solubility: importance and enhancement techniques</title>
      <authors>
        <author>K Savjani</author>
        <author>A Gajjar</author>
        <author>J Savjani</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2012</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Polyethylene glycol functionalized carbon nanotubes/gelatin-chitosan nanocomposite: An approach for significant drug release</title>
      <authors>
        <author>S Sharmeen</author>
        <author>M Rahman</author>
        <author>M M Lubna</author>
        <author>Salem</author>
        <author>S Kh</author>
        <author>R Islam</author>
        <author>M A Khan</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2018</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Adsorption of selected volatile organic vapors on multiwall carbon nanotubes</title>
      <authors>
        <author>Y Shih</author>
        <author>M Li</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2008</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>The influence of multivalent phosphate structure on the properties of ionically cross-linked chitosan films for controlled drug release</title>
      <authors>
        <author>X Shu</author>
        <author>K Zhu</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2002</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Nanoparticles of chitosan loaded ciprofloxacin: fabrication and antimicrobial activity</title>
      <authors>
        <author>Z Sobhani</author>
        <author>S Samani</author>
        <author>H Montaseri</author>
        <author>E Khezri</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2017</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Preliminary investigations into the purification and functionalization of multiwall carbon nanotubes</title>
      <authors>
        <author>G Trykowski</author>
        <author>S Biniak</author>
        <author>L Stobinski</author>
        <author>B Lesiak</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2010</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>The antimicrobial activity of nanoparticles: present situation and prospects for the future</title>
      <authors>
        <author>L Wang</author>
        <author>C Hub</author>
        <author>L Shao</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2017</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Unknown</title>
      <authors />
      <date>Unknown</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Antibiotic resistance in Salmonella typhimurium isolates recovered from the food chain through national antimicrobial resistance monitoring system between 1996 and 2016</title>
      <authors>
        <author>X Wang</author>
        <author>S Biswas</author>
        <author>N Paudyal</author>
        <author>H Pan</author>
        <author>X Li</author>
        <author>W Fang</author>
        <author>M Yue</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2019</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>In-vitro release study of the polymeric drug nanoparticles: development and validation of a novel method</title>
      <authors>
        <author>J Weng</author>
        <author>H Tong</author>
        <author>S Chow</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2020</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Antibiotic Resistance</title>
      <authors />
      <date>2021</date>
    </reference>
    <reference>
      <title>Production and characterization of nanostructured lipid carriers and solid lipid nanoparticles containing lycopene for food fortification</title>
      <authors>
        <author>A Zardini</author>
        <author>M Mohebbi</author>
        <author>R Farhoosh</author>
        <author>S Bolurian</author>
      </authors>
      <date>2018</date>
    </reference>
  </references>
</document>