<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Liposome-Mediated calcium phosphate formation in metastable solutions.pdf</file>
	<title>Liposome-Mediated Calcium Phosphate Formation in Metastable Solutions</title>
	<date>Unknown</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Liposome-Mediated calcium phosphate formation in metastable solutions.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>E Eanes</author>
		<author>A Hailer</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>Anionic liposomes were prepared as previously described [4] by dispersing dried films of 7:2:1 molar mixtures of phosphatidylcholine (PC), dicetyl phosphate (DCP), and cholesterol (chol) (Avanti Polar-lipids, Inc., Birmingham, AL) in PIPES (piperazine-N,N'-bis[2-ethane-sulfonic acid], Sigma Chemical Co., St.</abstract>
	<methods/>
	<full_text>Summary. The present study examined the effect of anionic liposomes on precipitate formation in supersaturated calcium phosphate solutions. The liposomes were prepared by dispersing 7:2:1 molar mixtures of phosphatidylcholine, dicetyl phosphate, and cholesterol in buffered aqueous solutions containing 0 or 50 mM inorganic phosphate (PI). Unencapsulated PI was removed by gel filtration. The liposomes were then suspended in reaction solutions containing 2.25 mM Ca 2+ and either 0, 1.0, or 1.5 mM Pt. All experiments were carried out at 22~ pH 7.4, and 240 mOsm. External solution Ca 2+ and PI losses were found to be appreciable only when the membranes of liposomes containing entrapped PI were made permeable to Ca 2 + with the addition to the suspension of the ionophore X-537A. The Ca 2+ losses, moreover, were up to 3 times as great (1.5 vs 0.5 mM) when accompanied by external PI losses than in Prfree external solutions where Ca 2+ alone was involved. Previous studies showed that in this latter situation, decline in external Ca 2+ concentration was the result of precipitate formation in the aqueous interiors of the liposomes. The present findings suggest that when the external solution phase was metastable, the apparent coupling of large additional Ca 2+ losses with intraliposomal precipitation was due to secondary precipitation brought about by the seeding action of intraliposomal crystals penetrating into the external solution. The results may explain in part the origin of extravesicular mineral deposits in matrix vesicle calcification.

Mineral deposition in matrix vesicles appears to be an early stage in the extracellular calcification of many vertebrate hard tissues [1][2][3]. However, the precise mechanism by which these extracellular, membrane-enclosed bodies initiate mineralization in vivo is not fully understood. In a recent synthetic chemical study [4], an effort was made to investigate some of the possible physicochemical aspects of this calcification process by employing artificial phospholipid vesicles (liposomes) as models for native matrix vesicles. It proved possible to carry out de novo precipitation reactions within the aqueous interiors of these liposomes by first filling the interior spaces with buffered inorganic orthophosphate (PI) solutions and then making the enclosing membranes permeable to external Ca 2+ ions with the addition of the lipophilic ion carrier, lasalocid acid (X-537A). The ensuing precipitation was found to proceed in two stages: with the formation of amorphous calcium phosphate (ACP) occurring initially, followed by the hydrolysis of the ACP and its replacement with crystalline apatitelike phases.

The formation of mineral phases in the intraliposomal spaces led also to a disruption in the integrity of the normally stable enclosing membranes. The experiments described in the present report show that when the Ca 2 +-loading of Pi-containing liposomes was carried out in metastable Ca-P I solutions, this breakdown in membrane unity induced by intraspace precipitation resulted in additional precipitation in the surrounding exterior solution space as well.

Louis, MO)--buffered solutions (50 mM, pH 7.4) containing either 0 or 50 mM KH2PO 4. The liposome suspensions (15 txmol lipid/ml) were aged undisturbed at 22~ for 20 h, then unencapsulated solution was removed on Sephadex G-50C (Pharmacia Fine Chemicals, Piscataway, N J) using HEPES (N-2-hydroxyethylpiperazine-N'-2-ethane-sulfonic acid, Sigma Chemical Co., St. Louis, MO)--buffered (10 mM, pH 7.4) NaCI as the eluting medium.

Eluted fractions richest in liposomes (6 txmol lipid/ml, average) were pooled, then mixed with a sufficient volume (0.04 or 0.06 ml/ml) of the KH2PO4-PIPES solution used in the encapsulation procedure to bring the inorganic phosphate (Pt) concentration in the external medium to either 2.0 or 3.0 raM. The liposome suspensions were next mixed with equal volumes of a 50 mM HEPES-buffered NaCI solution (pH 7.4) containing 4.5 mM CaCl 2. At this stage, the Ca 2+ , PI, and total buffer concentrations in the external suspension medium were 2.25, 1.0-1.5, and 31 mM respectively. In Pl-free control experiments, a KC1-PIPES solution was added to the suspending medium instead of KH2PO4-PIPES. In other experiments, the suspending medium was also made 0.8 mM'in MgC12 and/or 0.02 mM in Na4P207 by adding the appropriate amounts of these salts to the CaCI 2-HEPES and KH2PO4-PIPES solutions, respectively, before mixing the latter solutions with the pooled liposome fractions. All solutions were adjusted to 240 mOrns with either KC1 (KH2PO4-PIPES solution) or NaCI before using.

Calcium-liposome interactions were initiated by injecting into the liposomal suspension 15 M/ml of a 0.6 mM ethanolic solution of the carboxylic ionophore X-537A (lasalocid acid, Na salt, Aldrich Chemical Co., Milwaukee, WI). The final ionophore/lipid molar ratio was 0.003. In ionophore-free control experiments, 15 ~1 of ethanol alone was added to each ml of suspension. In some reactions the KH2PO4-PIPES was added to an initially Pl-free suspending medium at 2 and 24 h after the injection of the X-537A. All reactions were carried out in sealed 5 ml polypropylene tubes incubated at 22 -+ 0.1~ At regular intervals after injection of the ionophore, portions of the suspension were filtered through 0.22 Ixm Millex-GS filter assemblies (Millipore Corp., Bedford, MA). Filtrates were analyzed for Ca 2+ by atomic absorption spectrophotometry and for inorganic phosphate by the UV spectrophotometric method of Murphy and Riley [5]. Although both filtrate Ca 2+ and P[ were measured, the Ca 2+ values were used as the primary indicators of reaction-induced changes in the external suspension medium. The PI values were less reliable for this purpose because of the concomitant leakage of encapsulated P~ into the suspension medium during ionophore-mediated Ca 2+ loading of the liposomes [4].

Liposome-free reaction solutions identical in electrolyte makeup to the external suspension medium were prepared by mixing the reactants in the same manner as described above but in appropriate volumes of the NaC1 eluting buffer alone. In some solutions, only enough CaC12 was employed to bring the final Ca 2+ concentration to 1.5 mM, Seeded reactions were initiated in these latter solutions by adding to each ml of solution 0.04 ml of a 24 h-old apatite suspension (1.4 mg crystals/ml) prepared by spontaneous precipitation [4].

The data in Fig. 1A show that aqueous solutions equivalent in Ca 2 + and Pt to the most concentrated external suspension medium used in the liposome experiments were stable toward unseeded precipitation for at least 48 h. On the other hand, some loss of filterable Ca 2+ from the external medium was observed in all liposome suspensions studied over this time period. The smallest losses occurred in suspensions in which the X-537A-primed liposomes contained no encapsulated P[, even in cases where the external suspension medium contained the maximum P1 concentration employed (1.5 raM) (Fig. 1B). Filterable Ca 2+ losses were similarly small in suspensions where the liposomes also contained entrapped PI but to which no ionophore was added (Fig. 1C). For the most part, these external solution Ca 2+ changes (0.1-0.2 raM) could be attributable to the binding of Ca 2 + to liposome membrane surfaces [4]. The one possible exception was the slight additional Ca 2+ loss observed in the ionophore-free liposomes at 48 h. Appreciably greater Ca 2+ losses from the external solution phase occurred when Pi-encapsulated liposomes were inoculated with X-537A (Figs. 1D-F). In suspensions containing no external PI, the Ca 2+ losses stabilized after 5 h at about 0.5 mM (Fig. 1D). As reported previously [4], Ca 2+ losses in this situation were largely due to calcium phos-    ,F) until at 48 h the maximum measured Ca 2+ loss was 3 times that observed in the PFfree suspension. However, commensurate Ca 2+ decreases could be achieved in this latter suspension by adding P~ to the external me-dium as late as 24 h after priming with X-537A (Fig. 2). These delayed losses appear not to have resulted from extraneous precipitation induced directly by the Pl addition itself. Adding in a similar fashion the PI after the Ca 2+ to an equivalent suspension containing no encapsulated PI did not result in measurable Ca 2+ changes. The data in Table 1 show that external solution PI, if present initially, also appeared to decline in concentration after priming Pi-encapsulated liposomes with X-537A. However, the leakage of encapsulated Pl (Table 1, Po column) into the external solution phase makes quantitation of this loss less precise than that for Ca 2+ .

Adding Mg 2+ and pyrophosphate ions to X-537Aprimed liposome suspensions containing both encapsulated and external PI greatly decreased the rate at which filterable Ca 2 + was removed (Fig. 3). These ions, however, did not affect the amount of Ca 2+ taken up by the Pi-liposomes in suspensions that contained no external PI. The addition of 0.8 mM Mg 2+ slowed the Ca 2+ loss from external solutions containing 1.5 mM P~ to a rate comparable to that observed in solutions with only 1.0 mM P~. As little as 0.02 mM pyrophosphate anions, on the other hand, totally inhibited further Ca 2+ removal after 2 h. The data curves in Fig. 4 show that similar inhibiting effects could be achieved with Mg 2+ and pyrophosphate ions when added to stable liposomefree supersaturated solutions seeded with apatite crystals.

The data presented show that anionic 7PC: 2DCP:lchol liposomes have a much stronger destabilizing influence on solutions containing both Ca 2+ and PI than on solutions containing Ca 2+ alone. This difference in reactivity was evident, however, only when the aqueous interiors of the liposomes both contained PI and were made permeable to Ca 2 + influx with X-537A, the two conditions previously found to be necessary for intraliposomal calcium phosphate formation [4]. When either X-537A or encapsulated PI, or both, was excluded from the experimental protocol, the Ca 2+ change in the external aqueous solution was the same whether or not this solution was rendered metastable with P[. These findings suggest that the additional Ca 2+ losses observed in metastable external solutions were tied to calcium phosphate formation inside the liposomes. The further finding that these additional losses were readily induced even when the external PI was added as late as 24 h after intraliposomal Ca 2--loading commenced suggests that these losses were secondary to intraliposomal precipitate formation.

Since decreases in external solution PI accompanied the secondary solution Ca 2+ losses, the inference can be drawn that these changes were the result of additional calcium phosphate formation. It is unlikely, however, that this additional precipitation occurred inside the liposomes proper. Rather, the combined effects of low intrinsic membrane permeability to Pi and high intraliposomal PI concentrations most probably restricted the precipitate to the extraliposomal fluid space. The anionic liposomes used in this study are normally quite resistant to transmembrane Px movement, even when primed with X-537A [4]. Therefore, only negligible external PI would be expected to accompany X-537A-mediated Ca 2+ transport per se across intact membranes into the aqueous interiors of the liposomes. But even an increase in P1 permeability, such as observed during intraliposomal precipitate development [4], would not necessarily result in a net uptake of external Pl by the liposome. To the contrary, the large initial PI(encapsulated)/Pi(external) ratio (/&gt;33) would favor a net efflux of PI from the liposomal interior and an elevation in external P~ concentration. In fact, results previously reported [4] on the leakage of encapsulated P1 into an initially Pvfree external solution phase during intraliposomal precipitation showed that the amount of PI released was appreciable, approaching nearly 1/2 of that initially entrapped. In the present experiments, PI released in this way could have raised the external solution PI concentration in the metastable solutions by as much as 0.4 mM (Table 1).

In itself, the elevation in external PI brought about by encapsulated PI leakage during intraspace precipitation was probably not sufficient to induce extraliposomal precipitation in the metastable solutions used in the present study, although this leakage may have contributed to subsequent mineral development. In reactions where 1.0 mM Pi was initially present in the external solution, the increase in PI concentration was still well below the stability limit for the solutions used in this study. Also, as shown previously [4], most of the P[ leakage occurred after the intraliposomal solids had formed so that, even where 1.5 mM P1 was present initially in the external solution, the decline in external Ca 2+ associated with intraliposomal precipitation would probably offset the destabilizing effect of the PI leakage.

On the other hand, leakage of encapsulated PI suggests that intraliposomal precipitation may have disrupted the integrity of the liposomal membranes [4]. Such breakdown in membrane structure could have resulted in exposure of the internally formed solids to the external solution. Once penetrated, the solids could become substrates for seeding the external solution. Additional evidence that the intraliposomal precipitate induced external precipitation was the finding that the retarding effects of Mg 2+ and P207 on the kinetics of the secondary Ca 2+ losses were similar to those observed in metastable solutions seeded with apatite crystals.

Several studies [6][7][8] indicate that the first apatite crystals seen in association with matrix vesicles originate in the aqueous interiors of these cell-derived bodies. However, the bulk of the apatite crystals which subsequently form occur outside the vesicles. These extravesicular crystals appear to cluster initially in the fluid space immediately adjacent to the vesicle surface, but later they proliferate outward to form coalescing, nodular crystalline masses [9-I1]. This progressive spherulitic growth away from the matrix vesicles suggests that the outer surface of the vesicle membrane provided sites for the initial nucleation of these crystal clusters. The formation of phospholipid-Ca-P l complexes, which are capable of inducing precipitation in metastable solutions in vitro [12,13], may be one way by which such sites could be activated. An alternative possibility [3] is that it is the mineral already present inside the vesicles that initiates extravesicular mineral formation. Our results support this latter hypothesis and suggest further that one way by which these crystals could fulfill this function is to physically breach the bilayer membrane and then either continue to grow or seed directly new crystals in the surrounding fluid space.</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Pathol Annu</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Anderson</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1980</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Clin Orthop Rel Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Boskey</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1981</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>The role of calcium in biological systems</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Wuthier</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1982</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif Tissue lnt</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Eanes</author>
				<author>A Hailer</author>
				<author>J Costa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1984</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Anal Chim Acta</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Murphy</author>
				<author>J Riley</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1962</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Cell Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Anderson</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1969</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Z Zelleforsch Mikrosk Anat</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Bonucci</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1970</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Am J Pathol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Anderson</author>
				<author>R Cecil</author>
				<author>S Sajdera</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1975</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Matrix vesicles</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Bonucci</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1981</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Dent Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Bernard</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1969</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Dentin and dentinogenesis</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Jones</author>
				<author>A Boyde</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1983</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Metab Bone Dis</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Boskey</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1978</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif Tissue Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Boskey</author>
				<author>A Posner</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
</document>
