<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Liposome directed growth of calcium phosphate nanoshells.pdf</file>
	<title>Unknown</title>
	<date>Unknown</date>
	<doi_number/>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Liposome directed growth of calcium phosphate nanoshells.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors/>
	<abstract>In conclusion, a well-ordered mesoporous silica/gold nanocomposite was synthesized using a liquid phase self-assembly method. The silica matrix was highly crystalline with mesopores extending throughout the structure and pore volume and surface area were comparable with mesoporous silicate materials. Gold nanoparticles, 60 nm in diameter were preprepared and acted as seeds for the growth of the mesoporous silica shell. Therefore quantum size effects were controlled independently of the silica mesopore geometry. Work on the encapsulation of other nanoparticles, including, Fe, Pt, Ti, and cadmium(II) selenide materials is currently being undertaken.</abstract>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>Experimental</heading>
			<text>Preparation: 25 mg of lyophilized 1,2-dioleoyl-SN-glycero-3-phosphate (Avanti Lipids No. 840875) DOPA (Avanti) was added to 5 mL of deionized and degassed water to make a 6.9 mM solution. Stock solutions of 0.24 M diammoniumphosphate tetrahydrate (Fisher) and 0.29 M calcium nitrate (Fisher) were prepared in deionized and degassed water. The reaction apparatus was a four-necked 250 mL round-bottom pyrex flask. Extending from the top of the flask were two 10 mL addition burettes controlled by throttling valves. The reaction was monitored by an Orion (420 A) ATC pH probe. A nitrogen gas atmosphere was maintained in the flask by purging N 2 through the remaining two necks. The reaction was stirred magnetically. All manipulations were performed at RT. A standard sample of calcium phosphate (Fisher) was prepared for comparison by adding 0.5 g in 10 mL of deionized water. It was prepared in the same manner as the nanoshell suspension for characterization.

Synthesis: The liposomes were made using sonication in a Fisher (FS30) bath sonicator. The liposome solution was allowed to sit for 20 min before the reaction was initiated. In the addition burettes 10 mL of water was added to 150 lL of 0.29 M calcium nitrate and 105 lL of 0.24 M diammonium phosphate. The reaction flask was filled with 50 mL of water and 2.5 mL of liposome solution was added. Ammonia was slowly added to bring the solution pH up to 11.5 under gentle stirring. The first 400 lL portion of calcium nitrate solution was added and allowed to stir slowly for 10 min followed by the first 400 lL of phosphate. The suspension was allowed to stir for 10 min. Addition continued in this manner for 2 more additions each before stirring was increased to maximum. Once rapid stirring was achieved the time between additions was decreased from ten to 2 min. These additions continued for as long as desired but is recommended that at least 10 additions be added to ensure complete coverage, yielding a shell thickness about 3 nm. Following the last addition the solution was stirred for an additional 15 min. Before characterization the suspension is allowed to age for 3 days at RT without stirring. The same procedure was followed without the DOPA to produce calcium phosphate nanocrystals for comparison using this recipe.

Characterization: Conventional transmission electron microscopy was performed on a 100 kV Hitachi H-600 TEM operated at 75 kV. Undiluted drops of the suspension were deposited on 300-mesh, formvar-coated carbon grids (Ted Pella). A contact time of 1 min was used and the excess suspension blotted off with filter paper. No staining was used. Most grids were covered and allowed to air-dry overnight before viewing. To observe the effect the TEM electron beam had on the shell's core region the samples were air dried for only three hours only before analysis. EDS measurements were performed on a Hitachi H8100 TEM with a (PGT eXcalibur) EDS detector at Northwestern's EPIC facility. There is a clear resemblance between the two above figures, and a sharp contrast between the morphology of the crystals and that of the nanoshells in Figure 1.

By Ari H. O. Kärkkäinen,* Juha T. Rantala, Arto Maaninen, Ghassan E. Jabbour, and Michael R. Descour Various application fields, such as telecommunications, data storage, information displays, sensing, and imaging systems, are moving towards integrated electronic and photonic systems. This trend has created growing demands for miniaturization of conventional optical systems as well as for development of novel materials and manufacturing technologies to fabricate and integrate micro-optical systems as part of electronic devices. In addition, simple packaging and assembly are critical to achieve productive and cost-effective integratedsystems manufacturing. The novel materials and manufacturing technologies have to be able to satisfy all or some of the following requirements: 1) capability to form thick structures (e.g., greater than 100 lm), 2) variable optical properties (e.g., tunable index of refraction, low dispersion, and high transmission), 3) photoimageability, 4) no etch transfer of the structures, 5) compatibility with wafer scale integration, 6) lowtemperature processing, 7) use of the same material in optical, mechanical, and structural roles, 8) high surface quality, 9) high thermal stability, and 10) low cost.

Several processing and manufacturing techniques as well as material categories have been introduced for micro-optics fabrication. Conventionally, the fabrication of micro-optical structures is performed by a multistep process. This process includes patterning of a deposited photoresist film using ªmask lithographyº (UV or X-ray) or ªscanning lithographyº (electronbeam or laser-beam scanning). [1] In ªmask lithographyº, binary and/or grayscale photomasks are used to produce the desired images in photoresist films. Reflow techniques can be applied to further modify the shape of the photoresist structures. The resulting patterned resist surfaces can then be etched directly into the underlying substrate by using wet or dry etch transfer or used to produce tools suitable for replication. [1±3] Conventional etch transfer processes are typically applied to materials that require high deposition temperatures, limiting the selection of the substrate materials. Replication of micro-optical structures can be performed by embossing, casting, UV-reaction molding, injection and compression molding using polymer-, glass-, or sol-gel-derived materials. [1,4±7] The LIGA and diamond-turning techniques have also been applied in replication tool fabrication. [8±10] Laser micromachining of optical structures into substrate materials can also be used in micro-optics fabrication. [11] More recently, non-lithographic techniques such as ink-jet printing of optical structures using polymers and sol-gel derived materials have been investigated. [12±14] Etch transfer techniques are well-established methods for the fabrication of optical structures but they are usually time-consuming and expensive, especially if large etch depths are required. Because of these constraints, etch transfer techniques are most suitable for the fabrication of diffractive and refractive optical structures when etch depths of less than 20 lm are sufficient.

Plastic and glass molding techniques are also widely applied in micro-optics fabrication. By using molding techniques, large structure heights can be achieved. However, the mechanical machining and molding technologies are not always well suited for use with electronic components that are complex and relatively brittle. Molding techniques, especially glass and ceramic molding, require the use of high temperatures during fabrication, which may eliminate various integration options. Furthermore, a disadvantage in the use of pure polymers in micro-optics fabrication is their lack of thermal stability and high optical loss at specific telecommunication wavelengths.

In this communication we describe the fabrication of microoptical and opto-mechanical structures by applying photoim-</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>The self-assembly of organized nanoscopic structures has been the subject of much interest in both colloidal and materials science. Recent work has shown that nanoscale liposomes can be used as a nanoscale template for the deposition of silica, to create a hollow silica nanoshell. [1,2] These silicate materials have been used to encapsulate fluorescent dyes, [3] enzymes, [4] polymer particles, [5] and liquids. [6] There is a possi-± [*] Prof. A. E. Ostafin, H. T. Schmidt  Chemical Engineering, University of Notre Dame Notre Dame, IN 46556-5637 (USA) E-mail: aostafin@nd.edu bility that these materials could be used as drug delivery devices but they suffer from biocompatibility problems. An ideal material would be one that is both non-cytotoxic and biodegradable. Calcium phosphate is a mineral that is native to the body and is the major mineral component of bones and teeth.

Here, a novel method is described to produce nanoscale shells composed of calcium phosphate. The method is inspired by the work of Dominicus in that it uses a liposome to provide a template for shell formation. Calcium and phosphate are precipitated on the exterior of the liposome forming the completed shell with a liposome/solvent core. This method can be altered to produce shells of 45 nm to greater than 100 nm in diameter, with thicknesses ranging from 2 nm to greater than 10 nm.

To date, solid calcium phosphate [Ca x (PO 4 ) y OH z ] particles have been produced using a variety of methods. The most widely used method is solution precipitation under different pH, compositions, and temperatures to produce calcium phosphate with different sizes and stoichiometric ratios of calcium, phosphate, and hydroxide. [7,8] A more advanced technique is the inverse emulsion technique, in which a water-in-oil emulsion is used to produce ultra-fine hydroxyapatite [Ca 10 -(PO 4 ) 6 OH 2 ] powders. [9±11] Mineralization of calcium and phosphate on the interior of a liposome produces micrometer scale spheres of hydroxyapatite. [12] Calcium phosphate ceramics are well known for their uses in biotechnology. [13±15] Hydroxyapatite is being investigated as a biocompatible barrier between titanium and aluminum bone implants. [16,17] Hydroxyapatite's osteoconductive properties allow it to be used in, orthopaedics, maxillofacial surgery and in periodontics to regrow decayed or lost bone. [18±20] In the future, hydroxyapatite may be used for artificial teeth and bone implants. Solid particles of hydroxyapatite are also being explored for use in drug delivery. [21,22] Calcium phosphate nanoshells have not yet been synthesized.

The synthesis of nanoshells of calcium phosphate uses a sequential addition approach, in which the calcium and phosphate are added in alternating aliquots. This is done in order to minimize undesired side reactions from occurring and improve liposome stability. Liposome stability is sensitive to ionic strength and this synthesis keeps the number of free ions in solution to a minimum. Throughout the process two reactions will be competing, one will be the deposition of calcium phosphate onto the liposomal nucleation site and the other will be the reaction of calcium and phosphate ions in solution, forming solid calcium phosphate particles and crystals. In our procedure, the calcium source (such as CaNO 3 ) is first added in proportion to the surface area of the liposome to provide a monolayer that covers the periphery of the liposome. When the phosphate source is added, the much larger, Ca 2+ coated liposome is the preferred reaction site for precipitation, leading to the formation of a nanoshell. To avoid a large excess of Ca 2+ that will affect the liposomes phase stability, only a monolayer amount of Ca 2+ was added initially to the suspension to prime the liposome for shell growth. A monolayer was approximated by assuming that the entire amount of lipid in solution formed unilamellar, bilayered liposomes and hence only half of the total phosphate head groups are available for binding. Since this approximation does not take into account the micellar fraction or potential multilamellarity of the liposomes, there are expected deviations in this work, which can explain the observation of small amounts of calcium phosphate crystals in the suspension.

The lipid chosen for synthesizing the nanoshell is the phosphatidic acid 1,2-dioleoyl-SN-glycero-3-phosphate (DOPA; Avanti Lipids No. 840875). The calcium and phosphate salts used were calcium nitrate and ammonium phosphate tetrahydrate. The synthesis was carried out in deionized and degassed water, and kept at a solution pH above 11 using NH 4 OH. A monolayer of the prepared calcium nitrate sufficient to coat the perimeter of the liposome was added under gentle stirring conditions at room temperature (RT) and allowed to react for 10 min with the liposome suspension. A DLS measurement was performed to ensure that the size of the liposome remained constant and did not rupture during this step. After the 10 min incubation, a monolayer of phosphate was added to the solution and allowed to stir for an additional 10 min.

Gentle stirring was used initially to preserve the spherical shape of the bare, pliable liposome. After the fourth addition, a sufficient amount of calcium phosphate was present to rigidify the liposome, therefore, the stirring speed was increased and the time between additions shortened. The addition of calcium and phosphate was then repeated 10 times to obtain a »3 nm thick shell of calcium phosphate. The process could be continued to obtain thicker shells. After following this procedure, a suspension was formed containing monodisperse and aggregated nanoshells as well as some nanocrystallites of calcium phosphate. The aggregates were a mixture of larger size shells around 100 nm and solid calcium phosphate crystals. The supernatant had a very high percentage of smaller shells on the order of 30±50 nm that were stable in suspension. These shells are seen in Figure 1. Fig. 1. A typical TEM image showing hollow calcium phosphate nanoshells viewed at 100kX (scale bar: 100 nm). The inset is a shell viewed at 300kX (scale bar: 33 nm). An area similar to this was analyzed using EDS, and revealed calcium, phosphate, and oxygen peaks in contrast to the areas of the grid without particles.

The obtained suspension aged for three days at RT and analyzed using transmission electron microscopy (TEM) to obtain the size, shape, and appearance of the particles. Dynamic light scattering (DLS) used to obtain an approximate size distribution of the liposomes before shell formation. Electron dispersive spectroscopy (EDS) was used to ascertain the chemical identity of the calcium phosphate nanoshell sample. EDS was chosen over X-ray diffraction (XRD) by virtue of the apparent amorphous properties of the synthesized material. Experiments using XRD showed weak peaks in the calcium phosphate region, approximately 24±34 2h.

From Figure 2 we can conclude that a solution prepared from the described synthesis is very different from a suspension prepared in the same way without the addition of the liposome template. This suspension, prepared without the DOPA, is identical to the suspension of standard calcium phosphate crystals. All the samples in Figure 1 were air-dried for 24 h before being studied in the TEM. The presence of a lipid/water core was inferred from the effect of TEM exposure on the samples. Initially the shells appeared circular and solid but the core region became lighter the longer the sample was exposed to the transmission electron beam. The effect occurred more rapidly on shells possessing a thin coating of calcium phosphate.

To confirm the presence of calcium and phosphate in the shells, the TEM grid was analyzed using an EDS detector on regions of the grid with and without sample. The blank portion of the grid showed no evidence of calcium or phosphorus whereas the sample area showed definitive phosphorus, oxygen, and calcium peaks, confirming the presence of a calcium phosphate material in the sample. All evidence obtained shows that the successful synthesis of calcium phosphate shells using liposomes as templates is possible. These nanoshells can be visualized using TEM without staining or additional grid preparations. The calcium phosphate coating can range in size from 2 nm to greater than 10 nm depending on how many additions are added during the reaction.

Solid hydroxyapatite particles have shown to be effective in the sustained delivery of antibiotics and proteins such as human serum albumin. [21] By utilizing calcium phosphate hollow shells as sustained delivery vehicles, there lies a potential for much longer release times, as a greater reservoir of drug can be carried in the hollow interior of the shell. The porous calcium phosphate barrier could be tailored to control the release or, if desired, retention of the material in the core term systemic complications. Here, we have demonstrated a method for synthesizing a calcium phosphate nanoshell possessing a liposome/water core. In light of the osteoconductve properties of calcium phosphate ceramics already being exploited in oral surgery to encourage bone regrowth, these calcium phosphate shells are also promising candidates for use in bone reconstruction, antibiotic filled porous coatings for implants, and perhaps may find utility in creating artificial bones.

Preparation: 25 mg of lyophilized 1,2-dioleoyl-SN-glycero-3-phosphate (Avanti Lipids No. 840875) DOPA (Avanti) was added to 5 mL of deionized and degassed water to make a 6.9 mM solution. Stock solutions of 0.24 M diammoniumphosphate tetrahydrate (Fisher) and 0.29 M calcium nitrate (Fisher) were prepared in deionized and degassed water. The reaction apparatus was a four-necked 250 mL round-bottom pyrex flask. Extending from the top of the flask were two 10 mL addition burettes controlled by throttling valves. The reaction was monitored by an Orion (420 A) ATC pH probe. A nitrogen gas atmosphere was maintained in the flask by purging N 2 through the remaining two necks. The reaction was stirred magnetically. All manipulations were performed at RT. A standard sample of calcium phosphate (Fisher) was prepared for comparison by adding 0.5 g in 10 mL of deionized water. It was prepared in the same manner as the nanoshell suspension for characterization.

Synthesis: The liposomes were made using sonication in a Fisher (FS30) bath sonicator. The liposome solution was allowed to sit for 20 min before the reaction was initiated. In the addition burettes 10 mL of water was added to 150 lL of 0.29 M calcium nitrate and 105 lL of 0.24 M diammonium phosphate. The reaction flask was filled with 50 mL of water and 2.5 mL of liposome solution was added. Ammonia was slowly added to bring the solution pH up to 11.5 under gentle stirring. The first 400 lL portion of calcium nitrate solution was added and allowed to stir slowly for 10 min followed by the first 400 lL of phosphate. The suspension was allowed to stir for 10 min. Addition continued in this manner for 2 more additions each before stirring was increased to maximum. Once rapid stirring was achieved the time between additions was decreased from ten to 2 min. These additions continued for as long as desired but is recommended that at least 10 additions be added to ensure complete coverage, yielding a shell thickness about 3 nm. Following the last addition the solution was stirred for an additional 15 min. Before characterization the suspension is allowed to age for 3 days at RT without stirring. The same procedure was followed without the DOPA to produce calcium phosphate nanocrystals for comparison using this recipe.

Characterization: Conventional transmission electron microscopy was performed on a 100 kV Hitachi H-600 TEM operated at 75 kV. Undiluted drops of the suspension were deposited on 300-mesh, formvar-coated carbon grids (Ted Pella). A contact time of 1 min was used and the excess suspension blotted off with filter paper. No staining was used. Most grids were covered and allowed to air-dry overnight before viewing. To observe the effect the TEM electron beam had on the shell's core region the samples were air dried for only three hours only before analysis. EDS measurements were performed on a Hitachi H8100 TEM with a (PGT eXcalibur) EDS detector at Northwestern's EPIC facility. There is a clear resemblance between the two above figures, and a sharp contrast between the morphology of the crystals and that of the nanoshells in Figure 1.

By Ari H. O. Kärkkäinen,* Juha T. Rantala, Arto Maaninen, Ghassan E. Jabbour, and Michael R. Descour Various application fields, such as telecommunications, data storage, information displays, sensing, and imaging systems, are moving towards integrated electronic and photonic systems. This trend has created growing demands for miniaturization of conventional optical systems as well as for development of novel materials and manufacturing technologies to fabricate and integrate micro-optical systems as part of electronic devices. In addition, simple packaging and assembly are critical to achieve productive and cost-effective integratedsystems manufacturing. The novel materials and manufacturing technologies have to be able to satisfy all or some of the following requirements: 1) capability to form thick structures (e.g., greater than 100 lm), 2) variable optical properties (e.g., tunable index of refraction, low dispersion, and high transmission), 3) photoimageability, 4) no etch transfer of the structures, 5) compatibility with wafer scale integration, 6) lowtemperature processing, 7) use of the same material in optical, mechanical, and structural roles, 8) high surface quality, 9) high thermal stability, and 10) low cost.

Several processing and manufacturing techniques as well as material categories have been introduced for micro-optics fabrication. Conventionally, the fabrication of micro-optical structures is performed by a multistep process. This process includes patterning of a deposited photoresist film using ªmask lithographyº (UV or X-ray) or ªscanning lithographyº (electronbeam or laser-beam scanning). [1] In ªmask lithographyº, binary and/or grayscale photomasks are used to produce the desired images in photoresist films. Reflow techniques can be applied to further modify the shape of the photoresist structures. The resulting patterned resist surfaces can then be etched directly into the underlying substrate by using wet or dry etch transfer or used to produce tools suitable for replication. [1±3] Conventional etch transfer processes are typically applied to materials that require high deposition temperatures, limiting the selection of the substrate materials. Replication of micro-optical structures can be performed by embossing, casting, UV-reaction molding, injection and compression molding using polymer-, glass-, or sol-gel-derived materials. [1,4±7] The LIGA and diamond-turning techniques have also been applied in replication tool fabrication. [8±10] Laser micromachining of optical structures into substrate materials can also be used in micro-optics fabrication. [11] More recently, non-lithographic techniques such as ink-jet printing of optical structures using polymers and sol-gel derived materials have been investigated. [12±14] Etch transfer techniques are well-established methods for the fabrication of optical structures but they are usually time-consuming and expensive, especially if large etch depths are required. Because of these constraints, etch transfer techniques are most suitable for the fabrication of diffractive and refractive optical structures when etch depths of less than 20 lm are sufficient.

Plastic and glass molding techniques are also widely applied in micro-optics fabrication. By using molding techniques, large structure heights can be achieved. However, the mechanical machining and molding technologies are not always well suited for use with electronic components that are complex and relatively brittle. Molding techniques, especially glass and ceramic molding, require the use of high temperatures during fabrication, which may eliminate various integration options. Furthermore, a disadvantage in the use of pure polymers in micro-optics fabrication is their lack of thermal stability and high optical loss at specific telecommunication wavelengths.

In this communication we describe the fabrication of microoptical and opto-mechanical structures by applying photoim-

15214095, 2002, 7, Downloaded from https://advanced.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/1521-4095(20020404)14:7&lt;532::AID-ADMA532&gt;3.0.CO;2-4 by Riga Technical University, Wiley Online Library on [06/04/2026]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Q Huo</author>
				<author>J Feng</author>
				<author>F Schuth</author>
				<author>G Stucky</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adv. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Ozin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Supramolecular Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Büchel</author>
				<author>M Grün</author>
				<author>K Unger</author>
				<author>A Matsumoto</author>
				<author>K Tsutsumi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1998</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B Aronson</author>
				<author>C Blanford</author>
				<author>A Stein</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adv. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Parala</author>
				<author>H Winkler</author>
				<author>M Kolbe</author>
				<author>A Wohlfart</author>
				<author>R Fischer</author>
				<author>R Schmechel</author>
				<author>H Seggern</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Mulukurtla</author>
				<author>K Asakura</author>
				<author>T Kogure</author>
				<author>S Namba</author>
				<author>Y Iwasawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Appl. Phys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Cai</author>
				<author>H Zhong</author>
				<author>L Zhang</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1998</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>PhysChemComm</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Mukherjee</author>
				<author>C Patra</author>
				<author>R Kumar</author>
				<author>M Sastry</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2001</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Langmuir</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Liz-Marzan</author>
				<author>M Giersig</author>
				<author>P Mulvaney</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1996</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adv. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Fowler</author>
				<author>D Khushalani</author>
				<author>B Lebeau</author>
				<author>S Mann</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2001</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Q Cai</author>
				<author>Z Luo</author>
				<author>W Pang</author>
				<author>Y Fan</author>
				<author>X Chen</author>
				<author>F Cui</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2001</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Microporous Mesoporous Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Grün</author>
				<author>K Unger</author>
				<author>A Matsumoto</author>
				<author>K Tsutsumi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Stöber</author>
				<author>A Fink</author>
				<author>E Bohn</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1968</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nature</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Kresge</author>
				<author>M Leonowicz</author>
				<author>W Roth</author>
				<author>J Vartuli</author>
				<author>J Beck</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Nature</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Lu</author>
				<author>H Fan</author>
				<author>A Stump</author>
				<author>T Ward</author>
				<author>T Rieker</author>
				<author>C Brinker</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Brown</author>
				<author>D Walter</author>
				<author>M Natan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Science</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Monnier</author>
				<author>F Schüth</author>
				<author>Q Huo</author>
				<author>N Kumar</author>
				<author>D Margolese</author>
				<author>R Maxwell</author>
				<author>G Stucky</author>
				<author>M Krishnamurty</author>
				<author>P Petroff</author>
				<author>A Firouzi</author>
				<author>M Janicke</author>
				<author>B Chmelka</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1299</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloid Polym. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Fontell</author>
				<author>A Khan</author>
				<author>B Lindstrom</author>
				<author>D Maciejewska</author>
				<author>S Puang-Ngern</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1991</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Pure Appl. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Sing</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1985</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Chem. Soc., Chem. Commun</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Branton</author>
				<author>K Sing</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1993</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Schmidt</author>
				<author>E Hansen</author>
				<author>M Stocker</author>
				<author>D Akporiaye</author>
				<author>O Ellestad</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1995</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Int. J. Thermophys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Maddox</author>
				<author>K Gubbins</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1994</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Discuss. Faraday Soc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Turkevich</author>
				<author>P Stevenson</author>
				<author>J Hiller</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1951</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adv. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Dominicus</author>
				<author>J Martin</author>
				<author>P Frederick</author>
				<author>P Bomans</author>
				<author>J Meuldijk</author>
				<author>A German</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adv. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Dominicus</author>
				<author>J Martin</author>
				<author>A German</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1291</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Phys Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>O Makarova</author>
				<author>A Ostafin</author>
				<author>D Meisel</author>
				<author>J Norris</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Proc. SPIEÐInt. Soc. Opt. Eng</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Q Wang</author>
				<author>X Chen</author>
				<author>D Meisel</author>
				<author>A Ostafin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2001</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title/>
			<authors>
				<author>C Mckelvey</author>
				<author>E Zadinski</author>
				<author>J Coldren</author>
				<author>B Jung</author>
				<author>H Jung</author>
				<author>Langmuir</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids and Surf</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Goller</author>
				<author>B Vincent</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1998</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Luo</author>
				<author>T Nieh</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1996</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Phys. Chem. B</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Onuma</author>
				<author>A Oyane</author>
				<author>K Tsutsui</author>
				<author>K Tanaka</author>
				<author>G Trebea</author>
				<author>N Kanzaki</author>
				<author>A Ito</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Mater. Letter</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Lim</author>
				<author>J Wang</author>
				<author>S Ng</author>
				<author>L Gan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1996</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Lim</author>
				<author>J Wang</author>
				<author>S Ng</author>
				<author>C Chew</author>
				<author>L Gan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Langmuir</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Hirai</author>
				<author>M Hodono</author>
				<author>I Komasawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Proc. Mater. Res. Soc. Symp</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Cui</author>
				<author>Y Zhang</author>
				<author>Q Cai</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Am. Ceram. Soc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Hench</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1991</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Bioceramics of Calcium Phosphates</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K De Groot</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1980</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Ceram. Ind</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Barnes</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1987</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Biomed. Mater. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Wei</author>
				<author>A Ruys</author>
				<author>B Milthorpe</author>
				<author>C Sorell</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Biomed. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Jiang</author>
				<author>D Shi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1998</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Mater. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Doremus</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Orthopedics</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Thomas</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1994</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomaterials</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Fabbri</author>
				<author>G Cellotti</author>
				<author>A Ravaglioli</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1995</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Mater. Sci: Mater. in Medic</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Paul</author>
				<author>C Sharma</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Biomed. Mater. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Yamamura</author>
				<author>H Iwata</author>
				<author>T</author>
				<author>Yotsuyanagi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1992</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Siloxane-Based Hybrid Glass Materials for Binary and Grayscale Mask Photoimaging</title>
			<authors/>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>VTT Electronics Kaitoväylä 1, FIN-90570</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Kärkkäinen</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>GuideOptics Oy PO Box</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J T Dr</author>
				<author>Dr Rantala</author>
				<author>Maaninen</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>This research was also supported in part by the US National Science Foundation grants</title>
			<authors/>
			<date/>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>The authors thank Veeco Metrology Group</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M</author>
			</authors>
			<date/>
		</reference>
	</references>
</document>
