<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/One-pot synthesis of amorphous calcium phosphate and Fe3O4 composites and the application in the removal of cadmium.pdf</file>
	<title>One-pot synthesis of amorphous calcium phosphate/Fe3O4 composites and the application in the removal of cadmium</title>
	<date>2020</date>
	<doi_number>10.1016/j.jece.2020.103653</doi_number>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/One-pot synthesis of amorphous calcium phosphate and Fe3O4 composites and the application in the removal of cadmium.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>Trang Thuy Thuy Le Hoang</author>
		<author>Fuangfa Unob</author>
		<author>Soontorn Suvokhiaw</author>
		<author>Nipaka Sukpirom</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>Amorphous calcium phosphate (ACP) is a promising material for cadmium removal due to its irregular surface structure. Nevertheless, the preparation of ACP has not been trivial owing to the facile transformation of the meta-stable state of ACP into the crystalline phase of hydroxyapatite (Hap). Herein we report a new preparation, by which ACP can be synthesized at ease through a one-pot synthesis. The utility of citric acid, together with, preformed Fe 3 O 4 renders the formation of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 magnetic composites, hampering the aggregation of calcium phosphates and hence hindering the transformation of ACP into undesired Hap. The well-controlled syntheses are illustrated and proved to be pH-dependent. The cadmium adsorption of the ACP/Fe 3 O 4 composite is well-fitted with Langmuir isotherm giving a maximum capacity of 454.5 mg g -1 and shows a pseudo-second order kinetic behavior. The superior cadmium adsorption capacity of the composite is top ranked among previously reported adsorbents. The thorough investigation underpins the adsorption mechanism, whereby the specific replacement of Ca 2+ ions in ACP network by Cd 2+ is highly selective over other M(II) ions such as Co 2+ and Ni 2+ . Furthermore, the superparamagnetic nature of the composites allows a convenient separation of the materials after use.</abstract>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>Synthesis of magnetite particles and calcium phosphates</heading>
			<text>Fe 3 O 4 particles were synthesized based on the method of Suvokhiaw et al. [36] with some modifications. Under an inert atmosphere of nitrogen, 25 mL of 1.38 M Fe 2+ (aq) and 25 mL of 2.76 M Fe 3+ (aq) were mixed together to get the Fe 2+ : Fe 3+ molar ratio of 1:2. Concentrated ammonia solution was added to the mixed solution until the pH of solution reached 10.0. After stirring the mixture for 1 h, the black precipitates were separated using an external magnet and washed three times with deionized water. The as-synthesized Fe 3 O 4 was dried at 60 °C under vacuum for 12 h.

The bulk calcium phosphates were synthesized by precipitation method. 20 mL of 2.10 M Ca(NO 3 ) 2 .4H 2 O and 20 mL of 1.26 M NH 4 H 2 PO 4 (atomic Ca/P ratio of 1.67) were mixed together in aqueous solution. Then, concentrated ammonia solution was added until the pH of the suspension reached 10.5. After stirring the mixture for 1 h, the white precipitates were recovered by centrifugation and washed twice with deionized water. Finally, the received precipitates were dried at 90 °C for 12 h.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>One-pot synthesis of CPs/Fe 3 O 4 composites</heading>
			<text>The molar ratio of citric acid to Ca 2+ and Fe 3+ to Ca 2+ were fixed at 0.25:1 and 0.22:1, respectively, throughout the experiments. Firstly, Fe 3 O 4 particles were formed, using the same method as described in section 2.2 without collecting and washing steps. In the second step, 4 mL of 0.53 M citric acid was added into the preformed Fe 3 O 4 mixture. At this step, the pH of the solution was adjusted from 10.0-2.3, 4.0, 6.0, 6.7, 7.9 or 9.5 using 2 M HNO 3 . After continuous stirring for 20 min, 4 mL of 2.10 M Ca 2+ and 4 mL of 1.26 M H 2 PO 4 -(Ca/P = 1.67) were added, as the third step. The pH of the suspension was adjusted to 10.5 using a concentrated ammonia solution. After stirring for 1 h, the obtained brown precipitates were collected using an external magnet and washed twice by deionized water and dried at 90 °C. The effect of an initial Ca/P ratio was also studied. By maintaining the constant amount of Ca(NO 3 ) 2 .4H 2 O and varying the amount of NH 4 H 2 PO 4 , the composites with three ratios of Ca/P (1.5, 1.67 and 2) were synthesized using the above-mentioned method. The pH of the reaction mixture in the second step was fixed at 6.0.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Material characterization</heading>
			<text>The crystalline phases of the products were identified by XRD using a Rigaku, Dmax-2200 Ultima + diffractometer equipped with a monochromater and a Cu Kα radiation source. The surface area of the samples was measured by N 2 adsorption-desorption method using a BEL Japan BELSORP-mini 28SP instrument. The FTIR spectra were recorded as KBr pellets with a Thermo Scientific Nicolet 6700 FTIR spectrophotometer. Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) images were obtained using a Philips TECNAI 20 electron microscope. The surface morphology of the materials was monitored by SEM using a JSM-5800 LV scanning electron microscopy (Oxford Instrument Link ISIS series 300). A LECO CHNS-628 elemental analyzer was used to determine the percentage of carbon element in the final products in order to estimate the amount of citrate ions existing in the products. The magnetic hysteresis loops were recorded using an in-house developed VSM system [37], calibrated by nickel sphere from Lake Shore, model 730908. DSC results were recorded using a DSC1 Mettler Toledo. The measurements were performed by heating samples from 30 °C to 450 °C at a heating rate of 10 °C min -1 in air.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Adsorption experiments</heading>
			<text>The removal of Cd 2+ by CPs/Fe 3 O 4 composites was evaluated using batch experiments. The bottles containing 10 mg of sorbents and 10.0 mL of Cd 2+ each were shaken at 30 rpm. The sample solutions were collected by separating the solid through 0.45 μm syringe filters.

The effect of solution pH on cadmium adsorption (Cd 2+ initial concentration of 250 mg L -1 ) was studied in the initial pH range of 2-7. The pH of the initial solution of Cd 2+ was adjusted to desire values using 0.01 M HNO 3 or 0.01 M NaOH.

To study the effect of ionic strength, 0.003-0.5 mol L -1 of NaNO 3 was added to Cd 2+ solutions (350 mg L -1 ). The pH of the initial solution of Cd 2+ was adjusted to 5.0. The suspensions were shaken at 25 °C for 15 h.

To investigate the selectivity of the composites, the binary metal solutions of Cd 2+ with Co 2+ , Ni 2+ and Pb 2+ were prepared. The initial pH of all metals solutions was 5.0. The initial concentrations of each metal ions were kept approximately at 3 M. The suspensions were shaken at 25 °C for 15 h.

The experiments of sorption isotherms investigated under Cd 2+ initial concentration in a range from 0-778 mg L -1 shaken for 24 h and sorption kinetics evaluated at various sorption times (5-420 min) were performed.

The initial and equilibrium concentration of Cd 2+ was determined by an inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrometer (ICP-OES) model iCAP 6500 series (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The capacity of the material in cadmium adsorption (q t (mg g -1 )) was calculated by Eq. 1;

where C 0 and C t are the initial concentration and the concentration at given time t (mg L -1 ) of Cd 2+ , respectively. V is the volume of solution (L), and m is the weight of sorbents (g).</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Preparation and characterization of the materials</heading>
			<text>To prepare CPs/Fe 3 O 4 composites, the one-pot synthesis was conducted in three consecutive steps: (1) the formation of Fe 3 O 4 nanoparticles (MNPs), ( 2) the complexation of citrate ions on MNPs surface, and (3) the precipitation of CPs/Fe 3 O 4 composites. The effect of various parameters on the formation of CPs/Fe 3 O 4 composites was investigated.</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Magnetic properties of the materials</heading>
			<text>The magnetic properties of Hap/Fe 3 O 4 and ACP/Fe 3 O 4 were compared with that of Fe 3 O 4 (Fig. 4). All hysteresis curves exhibited nearly zero values of magnetic remanence and coercivity, showing their superparamagnetic property [28,41]. The saturation magnetization parameter (M s ) of Fe 3 O 4 was 61.4 emu g -1 , while those of Hap/Fe 3 O 4 (consisting of 15.8 wt% Fe 3 O 4 ) and ACP/Fe 3 O 4 (consisting of 15.9 wt% Fe 3 O 4 ) were 8.94 emu g -1 and 7.80 emu g -1 , respectively. The nonmagnetic phase of ACP or Hap may cause the lower saturation magnetization of the composites owing to the feasible separation of each magnetite particles. The observation replicates the phenomenon, of which under an external magnetic field the magnetic induction among different magnetic domains was interrupted by a non-magnetic phase [36,42,43].</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Mechanism of the synthesis process</heading>
			<text>The schematic illustration of the formation of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 and Hap/ Fe 3 O 4 is shown in Fig. 5. There were two types of the formation of magnetic calcium phosphates (i.e. Hap and ACP) depending on the pH of the reaction mixture when citric acid was added to the preformed magnetic particles (step (2)).

In the pH range lower than the pK a3 of citric acid (less than 6.4), Fe 3 O 4 particle had positive surface charge [44,45]. There would be the electrostatic interaction between the negative charge of the partly-deprotonated species of citric acid (H 2 C 6 H 5 O 7

-and HC 6 H 5 O 7 2-) and the positive charge on Fe 3 O 4 surface. Therefore, the anions were coated on the surface of Fe 3 O 4 and acted as steric stabilizer of magnetite particles. After that, when Ca 2+ and PO 4 3 were added, another end of the citrate anions would bind with Ca 2+ , linking Ca 2+ to the surface of magnetite particles. As a result, the Ca 2+ ions were attached on the surface of magnetite, and the meta-stable phase of amorphous calcium phosphate was formed and maintained on the particle surface. On the other hand, the synthesis of calcium phosphates with only magnetite or citric acid under similar conditions always yielded the Hap phase. The cooperation of magnetite and citrate species was therefore needed for stabilizing ACP. In the range of pH higher than the pK a3 of citric acid (6.7-9.5), the charge on the surface of magnetite particles became negative or less positive [44,45]. Therefore, the interaction between fully-deprotonated citrate ion (C 6 H 5 O 7</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>The contamination of toxic species in water sources has long been recognized as one of the most serious problems worldwide. The development of adsorbents to remove those species with effective cost, convenient process, high selectivity, high removal capacity and environmental benign is interesting due to the awareness on environmental issue [1]. The adsorbents could be categorized into low-cost pristine materials such as activated carbons [2], metal oxide nanoparticles [3], porous materials with high adsorption capacity such as zeolite [4], metal open-framework materials [5], surface-modified materials such as modified clays [6] and chitosan [7], composites with the combination of desired properties such as magnetic metal oxide nanoparticles and polymer nanocomposites [8], and conjugate nanomaterials exhibiting both selective adsorption and visual response [9,10]. Owing to the environmental benign properties and the high accessible surface areas of calcium phosphates (CPs), the materials have received plethora amount of attention in the field of water treatment and toxic removal among previously stated materials [11][12][13][14][15][16][17][18]. This work presents the composites with the combination of irregular surface of amorphous calcium phosphate network and a magnetic behavior of Fe 3 O 4 , aiming to obtain the adsorbents with high adsorption capacity, high selectivity and ease of separation.

Two types of CPs, including hydroxyapatite-based [11][12][13][14][15][16][17] and amorphous calcium phosphates [18] have been known for their potential applications in the removal of heavy metals, especially cadmium. It has been found that higher removal capacities of heavy metals were achieved from hydroxyapatite (Hap) with lower crystallinity and higher specific surface area [17]. Considering the correlation between crystallinity and removal capacity, amorphous calcium phosphate (ACP) could be a more promising sorbent than Hap.

ACP has various Ca/P ratios depending on the condition of the synthesis [19,20]. ACP precipitates normally contain a large amount of water including bound water (10-20 %) and water molecules in the space between the calcium phosphate clusters, called the Posner's clusters. The specific surface area of ACP was therefore surprising low due to the obstruction of these water molecules [19]. Moreover, ACP is a meta-stable species, formed as a precursor of Hap in a basic condition. From a saturated calcium phosphate solution, ACP precipitates as an initial solid phase, then readily transforms to the stable crystalline materials, Hap [18,19,[21][22][23][24][25][26]. Thus, the uses of special techniques, such as spray drying method [19], phosphorus-containing biomolecules as starting materials [18,25] or deep eutectic solvents [24] were necessary to prevent the transformation from ACP to Hap. Even though the potential of ACP as sorbents for toxic removal is realized, the use of ACP in this field has thus far been in their infancy majorly owing to their complicated preparations. Therefore, more facile syntheses of ACP are requisite to broaden the investigation and use of potent ACP in toxic removal avenues.

The use of CPs materials to remove heavy metals normally faces some difficulty in adsorbent separation [13,27,28]. A development of adsorbents that can be conveniently recovered is hence needed. The magnetic separation of materials from media is well known as an efficient, economic, and non-contaminated technology. Various magnetic composites used for metal ion adsorption including magnetic Hap were prepared and their easy separation using an external magnetic field was demonstrated [13,27,28]. However, the studies exploring the possibility of using magnetic ACP for heavy metals removal are scarce. ACP/ CoFe 2 O 4 composites were synthesized by co-precipitation method using block copolymer pluronic P123 as a template [29]. ACP/iron oxide composites were prepared using Na 2 ATP as a stabilizer [30]. These magnetic ACP materials were used for biochemical applications. In this work, ACP/Fe 3 O 4 composites were synthesized via a one-pot synthesis for cadmium removal. A one-pot synthesis has advantages including less time consuming and cost saving. Here we first report the preparation of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 composites via a facile one-pot synthesis procedure.

Citric acid was applied in the one-pot synthesis of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 composites. It is a weak organic tricarboxylic acid (pK a1 = 3.1, pK a2 = 4.8 and pK a3 = 6.4) [31], known as an inhibitor ceasing the transformation of ACP to Hap [22]. The acid and its anionic forms have a strong chelating ability to calcium ions depending strongly on the pH of the solution [32][33][34]. Moreover, citric acid could also stabilize the magnetite particles by using one carboxylate group to bind with magnetite surface, leaving other two carboxylates to prevent the aggregation or to provide the active sites for further surface modification [35]. The effect of factors related to the formation of ACP was studied and the mechanism of ACP formation was subsequently proposed. The cadmium removal behavior of these composites was also investigated.  O), standard solution (1000 mg L -1 ) of cadmium, lead, cobalt and nickel were analytical grade and used as received.

Fe 3 O 4 particles were synthesized based on the method of Suvokhiaw et al. [36] with some modifications. Under an inert atmosphere of nitrogen, 25 mL of 1.38 M Fe 2+ (aq) and 25 mL of 2.76 M Fe 3+ (aq) were mixed together to get the Fe 2+ : Fe 3+ molar ratio of 1:2. Concentrated ammonia solution was added to the mixed solution until the pH of solution reached 10.0. After stirring the mixture for 1 h, the black precipitates were separated using an external magnet and washed three times with deionized water. The as-synthesized Fe 3 O 4 was dried at 60 °C under vacuum for 12 h.

The bulk calcium phosphates were synthesized by precipitation method. 20 mL of 2.10 M Ca(NO 3 ) 2 .4H 2 O and 20 mL of 1.26 M NH 4 H 2 PO 4 (atomic Ca/P ratio of 1.67) were mixed together in aqueous solution. Then, concentrated ammonia solution was added until the pH of the suspension reached 10.5. After stirring the mixture for 1 h, the white precipitates were recovered by centrifugation and washed twice with deionized water. Finally, the received precipitates were dried at 90 °C for 12 h.

The molar ratio of citric acid to Ca 2+ and Fe 3+ to Ca 2+ were fixed at 0.25:1 and 0.22:1, respectively, throughout the experiments. Firstly, Fe 3 O 4 particles were formed, using the same method as described in section 2.2 without collecting and washing steps. In the second step, 4 mL of 0.53 M citric acid was added into the preformed Fe 3 O 4 mixture. At this step, the pH of the solution was adjusted from 10.0-2.3, 4.0, 6.0, 6.7, 7.9 or 9.5 using 2 M HNO 3 . After continuous stirring for 20 min, 4 mL of 2.10 M Ca 2+ and 4 mL of 1.26 M H 2 PO 4 -(Ca/P = 1.67) were added, as the third step. The pH of the suspension was adjusted to 10.5 using a concentrated ammonia solution. After stirring for 1 h, the obtained brown precipitates were collected using an external magnet and washed twice by deionized water and dried at 90 °C. The effect of an initial Ca/P ratio was also studied. By maintaining the constant amount of Ca(NO 3 ) 2 .4H 2 O and varying the amount of NH 4 H 2 PO 4 , the composites with three ratios of Ca/P (1.5, 1.67 and 2) were synthesized using the above-mentioned method. The pH of the reaction mixture in the second step was fixed at 6.0.

The crystalline phases of the products were identified by XRD using a Rigaku, Dmax-2200 Ultima + diffractometer equipped with a monochromater and a Cu Kα radiation source. The surface area of the samples was measured by N 2 adsorption-desorption method using a BEL Japan BELSORP-mini 28SP instrument. The FTIR spectra were recorded as KBr pellets with a Thermo Scientific Nicolet 6700 FTIR spectrophotometer. Transmission electron microscopy (TEM) images were obtained using a Philips TECNAI 20 electron microscope. The surface morphology of the materials was monitored by SEM using a JSM-5800 LV scanning electron microscopy (Oxford Instrument Link ISIS series 300). A LECO CHNS-628 elemental analyzer was used to determine the percentage of carbon element in the final products in order to estimate the amount of citrate ions existing in the products. The magnetic hysteresis loops were recorded using an in-house developed VSM system [37], calibrated by nickel sphere from Lake Shore, model 730908. DSC results were recorded using a DSC1 Mettler Toledo. The measurements were performed by heating samples from 30 °C to 450 °C at a heating rate of 10 °C min -1 in air.

The removal of Cd 2+ by CPs/Fe 3 O 4 composites was evaluated using batch experiments. The bottles containing 10 mg of sorbents and 10.0 mL of Cd 2+ each were shaken at 30 rpm. The sample solutions were collected by separating the solid through 0.45 μm syringe filters.

The effect of solution pH on cadmium adsorption (Cd 2+ initial concentration of 250 mg L -1 ) was studied in the initial pH range of 2-7. The pH of the initial solution of Cd 2+ was adjusted to desire values using 0.01 M HNO 3 or 0.01 M NaOH.

To study the effect of ionic strength, 0.003-0.5 mol L -1 of NaNO 3 was added to Cd 2+ solutions (350 mg L -1 ). The pH of the initial solution of Cd 2+ was adjusted to 5.0. The suspensions were shaken at 25 °C for 15 h.

To investigate the selectivity of the composites, the binary metal solutions of Cd 2+ with Co 2+ , Ni 2+ and Pb 2+ were prepared. The initial pH of all metals solutions was 5.0. The initial concentrations of each metal ions were kept approximately at 3 M. The suspensions were shaken at 25 °C for 15 h.

The experiments of sorption isotherms investigated under Cd 2+ initial concentration in a range from 0-778 mg L -1 shaken for 24 h and sorption kinetics evaluated at various sorption times (5-420 min) were performed.

The initial and equilibrium concentration of Cd 2+ was determined by an inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrometer (ICP-OES) model iCAP 6500 series (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The capacity of the material in cadmium adsorption (q t (mg g -1 )) was calculated by Eq. 1;

where C 0 and C t are the initial concentration and the concentration at given time t (mg L -1 ) of Cd 2+ , respectively. V is the volume of solution (L), and m is the weight of sorbents (g).

To prepare CPs/Fe 3 O 4 composites, the one-pot synthesis was conducted in three consecutive steps: (1) the formation of Fe 3 O 4 nanoparticles (MNPs), ( 2) the complexation of citrate ions on MNPs surface, and (3) the precipitation of CPs/Fe 3 O 4 composites. The effect of various parameters on the formation of CPs/Fe 3 O 4 composites was investigated.

In previous studies, citric acid has been utilized in the modification of the magnetite surface as well as the formation of complexes with calcium phosphates [22,[32][33][34][35]. In this work, citric acid was added into the mixture during step (2) of the one-pot synthesis and the pH of the mixture solution was varied to observe its effect on the formation of calcium phosphates. The XRD patterns of CPs/Fe 3 O 4 composites derived at various pH are shown in Fig. 1. The characteristic peaks of Fe 3 O 4 (PDF 86-1361) appear in all patterns. The detailed investigation using XRD provided the evidence of Hap in composites prepared at the pH higher than the pK a3 of citric acid (6.7-9.5). In a stark contrast, no Hap was marked in any composite derived at the pH lower than the pK a3 of citric acid (2.3-6.0). This observation could imply the successful synthesis of ACPs/Fe 3 O 4 under the optimal acidic conditions.

TEM and SEM images of the bare Fe 3 O 4 (Fig. 2 (a) and (b)) show the agglomeration of nano-sized particles. For the composites, ACP/Fe 3 O 4 (pH 6.0) and Hap/Fe 3 O 4 (pH 9.5) were chosen as the representatives of the composites containing ACP and Hap, respectively. The TEM image of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 (Fig. 2(c)) suggests the particle aggregation. Fe 3 O 4 particles were covered and linked by the irregular shape of ACP phase, resulting to the mossy surface as seen in the SEM image (Fig. 2(d)). On the other hand, the needle-shaped particles of Hap and the nano-sized Fe 3 O 4 aggregate together in Hap/Fe 3 O 4 (Fig. 2(e) and 2(f)).

To determine the content of calcium phosphates and magnetite in the materials, samples were digested in acid and the concentrations of calcium, phosphorus, and iron were measured by ICP-OES. The content of citrate represented by carbon content was observed using elemental analysis technique. The elemental content results are shown in Table 1. According to the weight percentages of iron detected, the content of MNPs was in a range from 9.8-19.9 wt% of composites depending on the pH during the synthesis. The average amount of MNPs in the ACP/ Fe 3 O 4 composites was higher than those in Hap/Fe 3 O 4 . According to the percentages of carbon detected, 11.9 wt% -16.7 wt% citrate ions were retained in the prepared composites. The presence of citrate ions in the final products were confirmed by FTIR (Fig. S1). The bands at 1633 cm -1 and 1430 cm -1 could be assigned as n asym (COO -) and n sym (COO -) of citrate ions, respectively [31,34]. These citrate ions in the composites would help maintaining the structure of the materials as discussed in the synthesis mechanism. The weight percentages of calcium and phosphorus indicating the amount phosphate were found to be in a range of 18.1-25.0 wt% and 8.9-11.8 wt%, respectively. The calcium and phosphorus contents slightly increased when the pH in the step (2) increased from 2.3-9.5. This is in line with the previous observation, whereby a higher pH condition could induce the formation of calcium phosphates better than that obtained at lower pH [38].

The specific surface area and the capacity of the materials in cadmium adsorption are shown in Table 1. Among all the parameters presented in this table, the capacity of the materials in cadmium adsorption depended strongly on the phase of calcium phosphates. ACP/ Fe 3 O 4 composites possessed higher adsorption capacities than Hap/ Fe 3 O 4 composites although they had lower surface area. The large difference in adsorption capacities between ACP composites and Hap composites pointed to the effect of crystallinity on the adsorption efficiency. In the amorphous phase (ACP), Ca 2+ would be substituted by Cd 2+ easier than those in a crystalline phase (Hap) due to the presence of defects and dangling bonds normally found in amorphous materials [39,40]. The mechanism of cadmium adsorption will be discussed hereafter. The unanticipated correlation between the surface area and cadmium removal ability could be explained by the different interaction of the water-containing ACP-based materials on the N 2 adsorption and on the Cd 2+ adsorption. For the determination of the specific surface area of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 , the physical adsorption occurred between the solid and nitrogen gas molecules. Therefore, the tightly bound interspace water in the ACP/Fe 3 O 4 materials would obstruct the adsorption of nitrogen molecules and thus reduce the measured specific surface area (Fig. S2) [19]. In the cadmium adsorption process, sorbents were suspended into the Cd 2+ solution. The metal ions would diffuse inside the pore easily through the water inside the structure of ACP-based materials that acted as the medium for the mass transfer in the sorption process. The cadmium adsorption capacities of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 composites synthesized at pH 6.0 and pH 4.0 were not significantly different, and they were higher than that of the composite synthesized at pH 2.3. Therefore, pH of 6.0 was chosen for the preparation of the materials for further investigation.

As previously reported, ACP existed in the wide range of Ca/P ratios [19]. To synthesize the magnetic ACP in this study, the Ca/P ratio was varied in the range of 1.5 -2.0. The XRD patterns of materials with different Ca/P ratios are illustrated in Fig. 3. Only Fe 3 O 4 phase appeared in all XRD patterns, indicating that the calcium phosphate of all three Ca/P ratios was an amorphous phase. The irregular shape of ACP particles linking together and becoming random network that covered the Fe 3 O 4 particles could be clearly perceived in the TEM image of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 (Fig. S3). Furthermore, all three ACP/Fe 3 O 4 composites possessed closed values of specific surface areas and cadmium  adsorption capacities, as summarized in Table 2. Therefore, the Ca/P ratios in this range show negligible effect either on the phase formation or the cadmium adsorption.

The magnetic properties of Hap/Fe 3 O 4 and ACP/Fe 3 O 4 were compared with that of Fe 3 O 4 (Fig. 4). All hysteresis curves exhibited nearly zero values of magnetic remanence and coercivity, showing their superparamagnetic property [28,41]. The saturation magnetization parameter (M s ) of Fe 3 O 4 was 61.4 emu g -1 , while those of Hap/Fe 3 O 4 (consisting of 15.8 wt% Fe 3 O 4 ) and ACP/Fe 3 O 4 (consisting of 15.9 wt% Fe 3 O 4 ) were 8.94 emu g -1 and 7.80 emu g -1 , respectively. The nonmagnetic phase of ACP or Hap may cause the lower saturation magnetization of the composites owing to the feasible separation of each magnetite particles. The observation replicates the phenomenon, of which under an external magnetic field the magnetic induction among different magnetic domains was interrupted by a non-magnetic phase [36,42,43].

The schematic illustration of the formation of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 and Hap/ Fe 3 O 4 is shown in Fig. 5. There were two types of the formation of magnetic calcium phosphates (i.e. Hap and ACP) depending on the pH of the reaction mixture when citric acid was added to the preformed magnetic particles (step (2)).

In the pH range lower than the pK a3 of citric acid (less than 6.4), Fe 3 O 4 particle had positive surface charge [44,45]. There would be the electrostatic interaction between the negative charge of the partly-deprotonated species of citric acid (H 2 C 6 H 5 O 7

-and HC 6 H 5 O 7 2-) and the positive charge on Fe 3 O 4 surface. Therefore, the anions were coated on the surface of Fe 3 O 4 and acted as steric stabilizer of magnetite particles. After that, when Ca 2+ and PO 4 3 were added, another end of the citrate anions would bind with Ca 2+ , linking Ca 2+ to the surface of magnetite particles. As a result, the Ca 2+ ions were attached on the surface of magnetite, and the meta-stable phase of amorphous calcium phosphate was formed and maintained on the particle surface. On the other hand, the synthesis of calcium phosphates with only magnetite or citric acid under similar conditions always yielded the Hap phase. The cooperation of magnetite and citrate species was therefore needed for stabilizing ACP. In the range of pH higher than the pK a3 of citric acid (6.7-9.5), the charge on the surface of magnetite particles became negative or less positive [44,45]. Therefore, the interaction between fully-deprotonated citrate ion (C 6 H 5 O 7

) and magnetite surface became weaker. While citrate ions bound and chelated strongly with Ca 2+ ions, and the crystalline phase of Hap particles would form and further deposit or aggregate with magnetite particles. The hypothesis of stronger chelation between citrate and Ca 2+ at higher pH was supported with the reported binding constants of citrate ion and Ca 2+ (K = 7.4 × 10 3 at the pH greater than 6.4, and K = 832 or K = 28.2 at the pH less than 6.4) [32].

In order to understand how citrate ions bonded in the materials, the thermal stability of the materials synthesized with and without citric acid were evaluated and compared by DSC technique (Fig. 6). Hap and Hap/Fe 3 O 4 samples synthesized without citric acid were thermally stable up to 450 °C as no peak was observed in the DSC results. On the other hand, for the analysis of the other samples containing citrate ions, the endothermic peaks appeared in range of 143 °C -167 °C corresponding to the melting temperature of citrate ions [46]. The shift of melting temperature of citrate in DSC results could predict the bonding strength of citrate ion with its surroundings. The degree of shifting to lower melting point was as follows: ACP/Fe 3 O 4 (with citric acid) &gt; Hap/Fe 3 O 4 (with citric acid) &gt; Hap (with citric acid). This might be explained that citrate ions could bind with crystalline phase of Hap in more ordered fashion, as compared with the composites. With the same reason, the random arrangement of amorphous phase would shift the melting point of citrate ions to the lowest temperature.

As mentioned in Section 3.1 (Table 1), the high cadmium adsorption capacity relies mainly on the amorphous phase of calcium phosphate; therefore, ACP/Fe 3 O 4 (Ca/P = 1.5, obtained at pH of 6.0) was selected as the sorbent for sorption study. The adsorption properties of the sorbent including adsorption kinetics and adsorption behavior at equilibrium were studied. The adsorption mechanism was also investigated.

The effect of solution pH on cadmium adsorption was studied in the initial pH range of 2-7. As shown in Fig. 7 from pH 3-7, the cadmium adsorption capacity remained constant, indicating that the solution pH has no effect on the adsorption process. The dramatic drop of the capacity at the pH lower than 3 was due to the dissolution of ACP in strong acidic solution.

It should be noted that starting with the initial solution pH of 3-7, the pH at equilibrium of these solutions was ca.6 (5.69-6.15) despite the different initial pH values owning to the basic nature of calcium phosphates. At lower pH, sparingly soluble calcium phosphates become slightly soluble, increasing the pH of solution as a result [47,48]. It is  c Samples were digested and the concentration of calcium, phosphorus and iron were measured by ICP-OES. d The adsorption condition: 10 mg of sorbents, 10 mL of 390 mg L -1 Cd 2+ , pH of 5.0. The concentration of Cd 2+ was measured by ICP-OES.

likely that at this pH range, the active sites for Cd 2+ adsorption on ACP exhibited the same nature and hence the uptake of Cd 2+ was not affected. The initial pH of 5 was adopted in further adsorption experiments.

The adsorption of Cd 2+ by the material was observed at different contact time varied from 5 min to 7 h (Fig. 8a). The adsorption occurred rapidly in the first 40 min and reached the equilibrium after 2 h. In order to determine the rate of the adsorption, the pseudo-first order model (Eq.2) and pseudo-second order model (Eq.3) [27] were applied to the experimental kinetics data. The adsorption capacities (mg g -1 ) observed at contact time t, and at equilibrium are presented by the variables q t and q e , respectively. The pseudo-first order rate constant (k 1 ) and pseudo-second order rate constant (k 2 ) were determined by linear plotting of the experimental data. It was observed that the kinetics data were fitted with the pseudo-second order model (R 2 = 0.999) (Fig. 8b) better than the pseudo-first order model (R 2 = 0.925) (Fig. S4). The pseudo-second order rate constant (k 2 ) was 3.6 × 10 -4 g mg -1 min -1 . The adsorption capacity at equilibrium calculated using pseudo-second order model (q e,cal ) was 312.5 mg g -1 , which was close to the experimental value (q e,exp ) of 294.1 mg g -1 , indicating a good fit of the model to the experimental data. Using the k 2 value, the initial rate (h = k 2 q e 2 ) of cadmium adsorption on ACP/Fe 3 O 4 was calculated to be 0.112 mg g -1 min -1 .

To understand the adsorption nature of the sorbent, the effect of ionic strength on the adsorption of cadmium was studied using NaNO 3 solution. The results in Fig. 9 indicate that there was no statistically significant difference in removal efficiencies when the solution contained NaNO 3 in the range of 0 -0.5 M (one way ANOVA, P = 0.07) at 95 % confident interval (α = 0.05.). The result could imply that the main factor of adsorption mechanism was not a simply coulombic interaction [49].

The presence of competitive cations such as Co 2+ , Ni 2+ , and Pb 2+ could affect the adsorption performance of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 for the selective removal of Cd 2+ ions. Fig. 10 shows the removal percentage of Cd 2+ from a solution containing single metal ions and those containing binary metal (2+) ions. In the case of Cd 2+ -Co 2+ and Cd 2+ -Ni 2+ solutions, ACP/Fe 3 O 4 could adsorb a certain amount of other cations; however, the ratios of removal percentages were 0.25 and 0.05 for Co 2+ and Ni 2+ respectively, when compared with that of Cd 2+ . The  reason is due to the size compatibility of Cd 2+ at the adsorption site. The ionic radius of Cd 2+ (95 pm) is comparable to that of Ca 2+ (100 pm); however, is much larger than that of Co 2+ (74 pm) and Ni 2+ (69 pm). The solution of Cd 2+ -Pb 2+ , on the other hand, exhibited the significantly lower adsorption of Cd 2+ by 50 %, with the disappearance of Pb 2+ in the solution. The explanation could be that lead ions disrupted the calcium phosphate network and precipitated as Pb 10 (PO 4 ) 6 (OH) 2 , as revealed by the XRD pattern of used ACP/Fe 3 O 4 (Fig. S5). These results along with the results from the effect of solution ionic strength indicate that ACP/Fe 3 O 4 exhibited high selectivity towards Cd 2+ adsorption attributed to the size of the adsorption site in the material.

To investigate the adsorption behavior at equilibrium, the adsorption isotherms experiments were performed. The effect of cadmium concentration on the capacity of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 in cadmium adsorption is demonstrated in Fig. 11a. The cadmium adsorption capacity increased with the increasing cadmium initial concentration. The Langmuir (Eq.4) and Freundlich (Eq.5) isotherm models [14,27] were applied to analyze the adsorption behavior of this material. The Langmuir constant related to energy of adsorption (b), the adsorbent maximum adsorption capacity (q m ), the Freundlich constant (n) and a constant related to adsorption capacity (K f ) could be calculated from the linear equation obtained from experimental data plots. According to the results, the Langmuir model fitted with the obtained adsorption data (R 2 = 0.993, Fig. 11b) better than the Freundlich model (R 2 = 0.978, Fig. S6). The Langmuir constant was 0.04 L mg -1 and the maximum adsorption capacity was 454.5 mg g -1 .

(4)

By obtaining a good fitting of the Langmuir model to the adsorption isotherms, it confirms the monolayer coverage of Cd 2+ ions onto ACP/ Fe 3 O 4 [50]. The reaction of the sorbent and sorbate only took place on the active sites (Ca 2+ ) on the surface of material. In order to confirm the adsorption mechanism, the release of Ca 2+ from materials into the solutions during the adsorption of Cd 2+ was monitored. The relationship between the amount of Ca 2+ released and the amount of Cd 2+ adsorbed was investigated (Fig. S7). The results indicated that the amount of Cd 2+ adsorbed on the materials was directly proportional to that of Ca 2+ released from the materials. The ratio of the amount of Cd 2+ adsorbed (mmol g -1 ) to the amount of Ca 2+ released (mmol g -1 ) was found in a range from 0.77 to 1.15 which was close to unity. Furthermore, the structure of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 before and after the adsorption process was examined by XRD (Fig. S5). The XRD pattern of the material after being used in cadmium adsorption was similar to that of the pristine materials. This result indicated that the structure of magnetic amorphous calcium phosphate remained intact through the sorption process. With the unchanged structure and the direct ration of Cd 2+ and Ca 2+ in agreement with other studies [14,51], this work confirmed the ion exchange mechanism between Ca 2+ in the ACP and Cd 2+ in the solution as shown in equation ( 6).

[ACP-Ca 2+ + Cd 2+ → ACP-Cd 2+ + Ca 2+ ] (6) Based on this mechanism, the solution ionic strength would have no influence on the adsorption, since the Cd 2+ adsorption took place by networking with phosphate rather than by coulombic interaction at the outer surface. In addition, the adsorption selectivity is achieved as Cd 2+ possesses the matching size to Ca 2+ ; therefore, the removal of Cd 2+ is more favorable compared to the smaller cations such as Co 2+ and Ni 2+ .

The capacity of the ACP/Fe 3 O 4 in Cd 2+ ions adsorption is compared with precedently reported materials (Table 3). Among all of these materials, the ACP/Fe 3 O 4 composite obtained by the proposed one-pot synthesis method shows intrinsically high adsorption capacity. When compared to crystalline Hap, the ACP provided higher adsorption capacity. In amorphous materials, there were defects and dangling bonds [39,40,52,53] and Ca 2+ ions might be released and replaced by Cd 2+ ions easier than those in a crystalline phase. Therefore, the materials having lower crystallinity would exhibit higher Cd 2+ adsorption capacity. This evidence makes ACP an interesting material in respect to its ion exchange ability. Moreover, in the presence of the magnetic particles, the ACP/Fe 3 O 4 composites in this work have also facilitated the convenient adsorbent separation.

To investigate the reuse of ACP/Fe 3 O 4 , the desorption of Cd 2+ from the used material was performed using either 0.05 M Ca(NO 3 ) 2 or 0.05 M Ca(NO 3 ) 2 in 0.09 M thiourea (Fig. 12). The desorption of Cd 2+ ions by replacing with the excess of Ca 2+ ions alone and with the cooperation of thiourea resulted to the desorption percentage of 13.6 and 22.0 respectively. Due to the adsorption mechanism of Cd 2+ on ACP/ Fe 3 O 4 that went through the replacement of Ca 2+ on the network of calcium phosphate, the complete desorption of Cd 2+ ions and hence the reusibility of the sorbent at its full-potential would be unattainable. The recovered adsorbent from the Ca(NO 3 ) 2 /thiourea solution showed a   Cd 2+ removal percentage of 36.4 %, compared to 77.6 % performed by the freshly prepared ACP/Fe 3 O 4 . However, the recovered sorbents could adsorb the amount of Ca 2+ exceeding the desorption capacity. This is possible due to the availability of the remaining Ca 2+ in the calcium phosphate sorbent for the replacement with Cd 2+ .

The amorphous calcium phosphate/Fe 3 O 4 composite was successfully prepared via a simple precipitation method. Fe 3 O 4 could prevent the aggregation of calcium phosphate nuclei, and citric acid was found to inhibit the transformation of amorphous calcium phosphate into hydroxyapatite. The degree of transformation of ACP to Hap was totally pH-dependent and directly involved the forms of citric acid during the synthesis, namely the fully-deprotonated citrate ions promoted the formation of Hap, while the partly deprotonated species encouraged the production of ACP.

Higher cadmium adsorption capacity was achieved from the magnetic composites of ACP. The isotherms and kinetics of Cd 2+ adsorption were fitted with Langmuir model and pseudo-second order model, respectively. The maximum capacity achieved from the Langmuir model was 454.5 mg g -1 . This composite is a promising material having many advantages, such as having simple preparation, low cost, high Cd 2+ removal capacity, high selectivity and convenient separation.

b from CHN elemental analysis. c Samples were digested in acid and the concentration of calcium, phosphorus, and iron were measured by ICP-OES.d The adsorption condition: 10 mg of sorbents, 10 mL of 390 mg L -1 Cd 2+ , pH of 5.0. The concentration of Cd 2+ was measured by ICP-OES.

b from CHN elemental analysis. c Samples were digested in acid and the concentration of calcium, phosphorus, and iron were measured by ICP-OES.d

b from CHN elemental analysis. c Samples were digested in acid and the concentration of calcium, phosphorus, and iron were measured by ICP-OES.

a from N 2 isotherm using the BET model. b from CHN elemental analysis.

* calculated from the published paper.

T.T.T.L. Hoang, et al. Journal of Environmental Chemical Engineering 8 (2020) 103653

Journal of Environmental Chemical Engineering 8 (2020) 103653</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Environ. Technol. Inno</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Singh</author>
				<author>G Nagpal</author>
				<author>S Agrawal</author>
				<author>Rachna</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2018</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Eng. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Kyzas</author>
				<author>G Bomis</author>
				<author>R Kosheleva</author>
				<author>E Efthimiadou</author>
				<author>E Favvas</author>
				<author>M Kostoglou</author>
				<author>A Mitropoulos</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2019</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Eng. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Lingamdinne</author>
				<author>Y Chang</author>
				<author>J Yang</author>
				<author>J Singh</author>
				<author>E Choi</author>
				<author>M Shiratani</author>
				<author>J Koduru</author>
				<author>P Attri</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Eng. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Hong</author>
				<author>L Yu</author>
				<author>Y Wang</author>
				<author>J Zhang</author>
				<author>Z Chen</author>
				<author>L Dong</author>
				<author>Q Zan</author>
				<author>R Li</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2019</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Eng. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Lv</author>
				<author>J Liu</author>
				<author>C Li</author>
				<author>N Zhao</author>
				<author>Z Wang</author>
				<author>S Wang</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2019</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Appl. Clay Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Phothitontimongkol</author>
				<author>K Sanuwong</author>
				<author>N Siebers</author>
				<author>N Sukpirom</author>
				<author>F Unob</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>React. Funct. Polym</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Borsagli</author>
				<author>A Mansur</author>
				<author>P Chagas</author>
				<author>L Oliveira</author>
				<author>H Mansur</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2015</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Environ. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>X Hu</author>
				<author>Y Hu</author>
				<author>G Xu</author>
				<author>M Li</author>
				<author>Y Zhu</author>
				<author>L Jiang</author>
				<author>Y Tu</author>
				<author>X Zhu</author>
				<author>X Xie</author>
				<author>A Li</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2019</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Eng. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Awual</author>
				<author>M Hasan</author>
				<author>G Eldesoky</author>
				<author>M Khaleque</author>
				<author>M Rahman</author>
				<author>M Naushad</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Eng. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Awual</author>
				<author>M Ismael</author>
				<author>T Yaita</author>
				<author>S El-Safty</author>
				<author>H Shiwaku</author>
				<author>Y Okamoto</author>
				<author>S Suzuki</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interf. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Corami</author>
				<author>S Mignardi</author>
				<author>V Ferrini</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2008</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Hazard. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B Sandrine</author>
				<author>N Ange</author>
				<author>B Didier</author>
				<author>C Eric</author>
				<author>S Patrick</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2007</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Eng. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Feng</author>
				<author>J Gong</author>
				<author>G Zeng</author>
				<author>Q Niu</author>
				<author>H.-Y Zhang</author>
				<author>C.-G Niu</author>
				<author>J Deng</author>
				<author>M Yan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2010</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Catal. Today</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Zhu</author>
				<author>R Yu</author>
				<author>J Yao</author>
				<author>D Mao</author>
				<author>C Xing</author>
				<author>D Wang</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2008</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Mater. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Ozawa</author>
				<author>S Kanahara</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2005</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Mater. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Qi</author>
				<author>J Shen</author>
				<author>Q Jiang</author>
				<author>B Jin</author>
				<author>J Chen</author>
				<author>X Zhang</author>
				<author>J Su</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids Surf. B Biointerfaces</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Stötzel</author>
				<author>F Müller</author>
				<author>F Reinert</author>
				<author>F Niederdraenk</author>
				<author>J Barralet</author>
				<author>U Gbureck</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2009</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>RSC Adv</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Ding</author>
				<author>Y Zhu</author>
				<author>C Qi</author>
				<author>T Sun</author>
				<author>J Wu</author>
				<author>F Chen</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2015</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Acta Biomater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Combes</author>
				<author>C Rey</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2010</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Thermochim. Acta</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Maciejewski</author>
				<author>T Brunner</author>
				<author>S Loher</author>
				<author>W Stark</author>
				<author>A Baiker</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2008</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Solid State Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Somrani</author>
				<author>M Banu</author>
				<author>M Jemal</author>
				<author>C Rey</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2005</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochem. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Williams</author>
				<author>J Sallis</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1979</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Cryst. Growth Des</title>
			<authors>
				<author>L Du</author>
				<author>S Bian</author>
				<author>B Gou</author>
				<author>Y Jiang</author>
				<author>J Huang</author>
				<author>Y Gao</author>
				<author>Y Zhao</author>
				<author>W Wen</author>
				<author>T Zhang</author>
				<author>K Wang</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Non-Cryst. Solids</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Karimi</author>
				<author>S Hesaraki</author>
				<author>M Alizadeh</author>
				<author>A Kazemzadeh</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interf. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Ding</author>
				<author>Y Zhu</author>
				<author>C Qi</author>
				<author>B Lu</author>
				<author>J Wu</author>
				<author>F Chen</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2015</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Mater. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>O Clarkin</author>
				<author>M Towler</author>
				<author>G Insley</author>
				<author>M Murphy</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2007</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Alloys. Compd</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Zhuang</author>
				<author>R Tan</author>
				<author>W Shen</author>
				<author>X Zhang</author>
				<author>W Xu</author>
				<author>W Song</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2015</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interf. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Yang</author>
				<author>S Masse</author>
				<author>H Zhang</author>
				<author>C Hélary</author>
				<author>L Li</author>
				<author>T Coradin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2014</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Dalton Trans</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Rout</author>
				<author>B Behera</author>
				<author>T Maiti</author>
				<author>S Mohapatra</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2012</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Asian J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B Lu</author>
				<author>Y Zhu</author>
				<author>F Chen</author>
				<author>C Qi</author>
				<author>X Zhao</author>
				<author>J Zhao</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2014</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids Surface A</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Saoiabi</author>
				<author>K Achelhi</author>
				<author>S Masse</author>
				<author>A Saoiabi</author>
				<author>A Laghzizil</author>
				<author>T Coradin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Pharm. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Goss</author>
				<author>J Prushko</author>
				<author>R Bogner</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2010</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Hu</author>
				<author>X Liu</author>
				<author>X Ma</author>
				<author>A Rawal</author>
				<author>T Prozorov</author>
				<author>M Akinc</author>
				<author>S Mallapragada</author>
				<author>K Schmidt-Rohr</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2011</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Dalton Trans</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Achelhi</author>
				<author>S Masse</author>
				<author>G Laurent</author>
				<author>A Saoiabi</author>
				<author>A Laghzizil</author>
				<author>T Coradin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2010</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Phys. Chem. C</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M De Sousa</author>
				<author>M Fernández Van Raap</author>
				<author>P Rivas</author>
				<author>P Mendoza Zélis</author>
				<author>P Girardin</author>
				<author>G Pasquevich</author>
				<author>J Alessandrini</author>
				<author>D Muraca</author>
				<author>F Sánchez</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Sep. Sci. Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Suvokhiaw</author>
				<author>A Imyim</author>
				<author>N Sukpirom</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Rare Metal Mat. Eng</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Jantaratana</author>
				<author>J Noodam</author>
				<author>C Sirisathitkul</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Ceram. Process. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Recillas</author>
				<author>V Lugo</author>
				<author>M Montero</author>
				<author>S Viquez</author>
				<author>L Hernandez</author>
				<author>V Castaño</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2012</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Materials</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Z Stachurski</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2011</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Surf. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Cai</author>
				<author>P Storer</author>
				<author>A Kheifets</author>
				<author>I Mccarthy</author>
				<author>E Weigold</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1996</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>ACS Appl. Mater. Interfaces</title>
			<authors>
				<author>V Patsula</author>
				<author>L Kosinová</author>
				<author>M Lovrić</author>
				<author>L Ferhatovic</author>
				<author>M Hamzić</author>
				<author>R Rabyk</author>
				<author>A Konefal</author>
				<author>M Paruzel</author>
				<author>V Šlouf</author>
				<author>S Herynek</author>
				<author>D Gajović</author>
				<author>Horák</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Appl. Surf. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Hong</author>
				<author>J Li</author>
				<author>S Zhang</author>
				<author>H Li</author>
				<author>Y Zheng</author>
				<author>J Ding</author>
				<author>D Wei</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2009</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Eng. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Pan</author>
				<author>L Xu</author>
				<author>J Dai</author>
				<author>X Li</author>
				<author>H Hang</author>
				<author>P Huo</author>
				<author>C Li</author>
				<author>Y Yan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2011</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Radioanal. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Milonjić</author>
				<author>M Kopečni</author>
				<author>Z Ilić</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1983</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Colloid Interf. Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Rajput</author>
				<author>C Pittman</author>
				<author>D Mohan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Therm. Anal. Calorim</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Wyrzykowski</author>
				<author>E Hebanowska</author>
				<author>G Nowak-Wiczk</author>
				<author>M Makowski</author>
				<author>L Chmurzyński</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2011</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Intracellular Delivery: Fundamentals and Applications</title>
			<authors>
				<author>O Pinto</author>
				<author>A Tabaković</author>
				<author>T Goff</author>
				<author>Y Liu</author>
				<author>J Adair</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2011</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Monogr. Oral Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Lc</author>
				<author>E Eanes</author>
				<author>O Phosplrate</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2001</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Water Supply Res. T</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Sharma</author>
				<author>C Sebwato</author>
				<author>B Petrusevski</author>
				<author>J Schippers</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2002</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Hazard. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Awual</author>
				<author>T Yaita</author>
				<author>T Taguchi</author>
				<author>H Shiwaku</author>
				<author>S Suzuki</author>
				<author>Y Okamoto</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2014</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Hazard. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>I Smičiklas</author>
				<author>A Onjia</author>
				<author>S Raičević</author>
				<author>Đ Janaćković</author>
				<author>M Mitrić</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2008</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Non-Cryst. Solids</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Fehr</author>
				<author>A Schnegg</author>
				<author>B Rech</author>
				<author>K Lips</author>
				<author>O Astakhov</author>
				<author>F Finger</author>
				<author>C Freysoldt</author>
				<author>R Bittl</author>
				<author>C Teutloff</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2012</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Non-Cryst. Solids</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Freysoldt</author>
				<author>G Pfanner</author>
				<author>J Neugebauer</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2012</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Environ. Chem. Eng</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2019</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Bioresource Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>O Karnitz</author>
				<author>L Gurgel</author>
				<author>J De Melo</author>
				<author>V Botaro</author>
				<author>T Melo</author>
				<author>R De Freitas Gil</author>
				<author>L Gil</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2007</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Hazard. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Benaïssa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2006</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
	<reference_dois>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.eti.2018.05.006</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2018.09.019</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2016.08.067</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2018.11.087</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2019.122111</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.clay.2013.06.002</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.reactfunctpolym.2015.10.005</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2016.01.038</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2013.02.042</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2007.09.075</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2006.02.039</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2010.05.049</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cattod.2008.08.011</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s10853-005-6529-9</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s10853-015-9573-0</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.colsurfb.2009.06.031</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.actbio.2010.02.017</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.tca.2007.11.022</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jssc.2004.11.029</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1042/bj1840181</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/cg400498j</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jnoncrysol.2016.04.026</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2014.12.004</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s10853-006-0783-3</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jallcom.2015.02.216</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2013.11.031</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1039/c2dt30984j</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1002/asia.201402319</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.colsurfa.2012.12.005</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1002/jps.22131</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/cm200355n</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1039/c0dt00251h</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/jp311556b</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/01496395.2016.1231206</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S1875-5372(13)60030-2</number>
		<number>DOI-10.3390/ma4091564</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0039-6028(96)00193-8</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/acsami.5b12720</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.apsusc.2008.09.071</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2011.08.046</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/BF02519745</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2015.12.008</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s10973-010-1015-2</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/978-94-007-1248-5_23</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1159/000061650</number>
		<number>DOI-10.2166/aqua.2002.0017</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2014.06.011</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2007.07.056</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jnoncrysol.2011.12.105</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jnoncrysol.2011.12.090</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jece.2019.103378</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.biortech.2006.05.013</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2005.07.085</number>
	</reference_dois>
</document>
