<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Regeneration of insulating mineral oil by carbonated amorphous calcium phosphate-chitosan adsorbent.pdf</file>
	<title>Regeneration of Insulating Mineral Oil by Carbonated Amorphous Calcium Phosphate–Chitosan Adsorbent</title>
	<date>2007</date>
	<doi_number>10.1205/psep06057</doi_number>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Regeneration of insulating mineral oil by carbonated amorphous calcium phosphate-chitosan adsorbent.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>A.C. Laurentino</author>
		<author>A.L. Parize</author>
		<author>M.C.M. Laranjeira</author>
		<author>A.R. Martins</author>
		<author>N.M. Mayer</author>
		<author>V.T. De Fávere</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>In this study carbonated amorphous calcium phosphate (CACP) microparticles were prepared for use as an alternative adsorbent to replace bauxite in the removal of polar compounds present in mineral oil previously used in transformers. Chitosan was used to bind the adsorbent CACP microparticles together. This material showed a better performance than bauxite in relation to the colour and interfacial tension (IT) of regenerated oil. Also, this adsorbent may offer an interesting alternative environmentally since, after extraction of the residual oil with an organic solvent it could be disposed of in soil providing macronutrients such as calcium, carbon, nitrogen and phosphorous.</abstract>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>EXPERIMENTAL</heading>
			<text>Chitosan (CHS) was obtained from Purifarma (Brazil). The insulating mineral oil was collected from a transformer of CELESC (Santa Catarina Central Electric Company) with the following characteristics: interfacial tension (IT) 15.4 dine cm 21 , neutralization index (NI) of 0.197 mg KOH per gram of oil, colour 3 and water content 26.9 mg L 21 .

The CACP was prepared by a wet method according to Lee et al. (2001), in which two solutions were mixed under stirring. Solution A was prepared from the dissolution of 55 g of Na 2 HPO 4 . 7H 2 O, 50 g of NaOH, 30 g of NaHCO 3 and 2 g of Na 4 P 2 PO 7 . 10H 2 O in 1.3 litres of distilled water. Solution B was prepared from the dissolution of 43 g of Ca(NO 3 ) 2 . 4H 2 O and 1 g of MgCl 2 . 6H 2 O. The addition of Na 4 P 2 PO 7 . 10H 2 O and MgCl 2 is known to retard the development of crystallinity in amorphous calcium phosphate. The precipitated CACP was washed with distilled water until pH 8.0 and dried at 708C (Tadic et al., 2002).

The microparticles of CACP-CHS were obtained from a 3.0% (w/v) solution of polymer in 5% (w/v) acetic acid containing different percentages of CACP. The mixture formed an emulsion which was precipitated in a 2.0 mol L 21 sodium hydroxide solution. The gelified particles were washed with distilled water until neutral pH and dried at 608C (Rorrer et al., 1993). The particles, after drying, were ground to a powder to increase the area of contact with the insulating mineral oil. Samples of material CACP-CHS were sieved to characterize the particle. The particle size distribution were obtained in three size ranges: 60% (0.500 -0.250 mm) 20% (0.250-0.149 mm) and 20% (below 0.149 mm).

The insulating oil recovery was carried out by the percolating method using three interconected columns filled with microparticles of CACP-CHS, each column having 20 cm length and 2.0 cm internal diameter, simulating the treatment used in the CELESC regeneration plant. The oil was percolated by gravity and aliquots were taken for the determination of color, interfacial tension and neutralization index.</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>Insulating mineral oil is of considerable importance because of its insulation and refrigeration characteristics in transformers. The existence of impurities (metals, cellulose) and products of the oxidative degradation of the oil contribute to decreasing the useful life of the transformers (Lishtein and Shakhnovich, 1970).

The regeneration of the oil is carried out using the adsorption process, which consists of the removal of the acid components, water and oxidation products with an adsorbent. The decision to apply a process of regeneration instead of a simple substitution is basically economic, when the following factors are considered: equipment, operational, maintenance, transport and storage costs, along with the quality of the new oil versus regenerated oil, and the cost of used mineral oil disposal as waste (Al-Zahrani and Daous, 2000).

Currently, activated bauxite is used as an adsorbent for the recovery of aged oil through the contact or percolation method in order to regenerate the oil, maintaining the properties of new oil with low cost. One of the problems of the regeneration process with bauxite is the great volume of organo-mineral waste that is discarded in landfill sites. Research on alternative methods and materials is thus necessary to discover raw materials from renewable sources that possess adsorbent properties for removing impurities in the treatment of insulating oil without causing damage to the environment (Al-Zahrani and Daous, 2000).

Chitosan (CHS) is a biopolymer obtained from the partial deacetylation of chitin which is found naturally in the exoskeletons of insects, crustaceous shells and fungal cell walls. Chitosan has been found to be a promising polymeric material of great scientific interest due to its properties and wide range of applications (Kumar, 2000). Special attention has been given to the physical properties of chitosan to prepare fibres, films, gels, membranes, nanoparticles and microspheres. Chitosan has been widely used as an adsorbent for the removal of pollutants such as metal ions (Juang and Shao, 2002;Ng et al., 2002;Varma et al., 2004;Guibal, 2004;Ngah et al., 2005), dyes and phenols (Wu et al., 2000;Chiu et al., 2004;Wong et al., 2004;Ngah and Fatinathan, 2006).

Calcium phosphate has demonstrated a capacity for the removal of toxic metal ions by ionic exchange due to its large surface area. Carbonated apatite has a preponderant role in bone metabolism due to its capacity to adsorb proteins, peptides, amino acids and other organic molecules, for example, citrates (Bihi et al., 2002).

The binder polymers such as polyvinyl alcohol and emulsions of some acrylic polymers have successfully been used to cement the adsorbing particles together through the formation of an interfacial alloy (Kro ´l et al., 2005). In this study, the role of the polymer layer is to bind particles of carbonated amorphous calcium phosphate (CACP) together when the material is subject to coacervation of particles using chitosan as a binder.

Thus, the use of this material for removal of polar compounds from aged insulating mineral oil could offer an alternative solution to the environmental problems generated by the use of bauxite, given that the phosphorous and calcium from CACP, and the nitrogen and carbon from CHS, are constituents of fertilizers and could be disposed of in landfill sites.

Chitosan (CHS) was obtained from Purifarma (Brazil). The insulating mineral oil was collected from a transformer of CELESC (Santa Catarina Central Electric Company) with the following characteristics: interfacial tension (IT) 15.4 dine cm 21 , neutralization index (NI) of 0.197 mg KOH per gram of oil, colour 3 and water content 26.9 mg L 21 .

The CACP was prepared by a wet method according to Lee et al. (2001), in which two solutions were mixed under stirring. Solution A was prepared from the dissolution of 55 g of Na 2 HPO 4 . 7H 2 O, 50 g of NaOH, 30 g of NaHCO 3 and 2 g of Na 4 P 2 PO 7 . 10H 2 O in 1.3 litres of distilled water. Solution B was prepared from the dissolution of 43 g of Ca(NO 3 ) 2 . 4H 2 O and 1 g of MgCl 2 . 6H 2 O. The addition of Na 4 P 2 PO 7 . 10H 2 O and MgCl 2 is known to retard the development of crystallinity in amorphous calcium phosphate. The precipitated CACP was washed with distilled water until pH 8.0 and dried at 708C (Tadic et al., 2002).

The microparticles of CACP-CHS were obtained from a 3.0% (w/v) solution of polymer in 5% (w/v) acetic acid containing different percentages of CACP. The mixture formed an emulsion which was precipitated in a 2.0 mol L 21 sodium hydroxide solution. The gelified particles were washed with distilled water until neutral pH and dried at 608C (Rorrer et al., 1993). The particles, after drying, were ground to a powder to increase the area of contact with the insulating mineral oil. Samples of material CACP-CHS were sieved to characterize the particle. The particle size distribution were obtained in three size ranges: 60% (0.500 -0.250 mm) 20% (0.250-0.149 mm) and 20% (below 0.149 mm).

The insulating oil recovery was carried out by the percolating method using three interconected columns filled with microparticles of CACP-CHS, each column having 20 cm length and 2.0 cm internal diameter, simulating the treatment used in the CELESC regeneration plant. The oil was percolated by gravity and aliquots were taken for the determination of color, interfacial tension and neutralization index.

The samples of CHS, CACP and CACP-CHS particles were characterized by infrared spectroscopy using a spectrophotometer with Fourier Transform System, FTIR-Perkin Elmer 16PC and the respective spectra a are shown in Figure 1.

The main characteristic groups of the CHS are the NH 2 of the primary amine, OH of the primary alcohol and a little C5 5O from the chitin. Figure 1(a) shows a band at 1650 cm 21 characteristic of the secondary amide C5 5O bond contributed by the remaining acetamido groups. The band at 3397 cm 21 corresponds to the stretching of the OH bond of the hydroxyl group of the polymer and water. The contribution of the OH bond of the primary alcohol appears at 1075 cm 21 , while at 1594 cm 21 the bending of the NH 2 group of the primary amine and at 2872 cm 21 the stretching of the C-H bond appear (Brugnerotto et al., 2001).

Figure 1(b) shows the spectrum of CACP, where the bands at 3446 and 1640 cm 21 are attributed to structural water molecule bands or adsorbed water. The bands at 1035 cm 21 are attributed to the stretching of the PO 4 3-, while the bands at 604 cm 21 and 566 cm 21 are attributed to the bending vibrations of PO 4 3-. The spectrum also shows bands at 873, 1418 and 1467 cm 21 which correspond to the vibration modes of carbonate (Donadel et al., 2005).

Figure 1(c) shows the spectrum of CACP-CHS. The bands that appear in the spectrum are practically the same as those of the CACP, in view of the small amount of CHS in the material.

Thermogravimetric analysis (TGA) of the samples was carried out with a TGA-50 Shimadzu instrument, with a heating rate of 108C min 21 , under a nitrogen atmosphere. The TGA curve (Figure 2) for the chitosan shows a thermal degradation at 3278C, with a polymer mass loss of 66.7%. This value was determined by derived TGA curves (Tadic et al., 2002). This characterization was important to determine the decomposition temperature of chitosan in order to dry the CACP-CHS particles in the process of adsorbent reuse. The characterization of the CACP sample was carried out by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrometry (ICP-AES Varian Vista Pro Axial) for calcium and phosphorous content and elemental analysis for carbon and hydrogen (Perkin Elmer CHN Analyzer 2400). The phosphorous, hydrogen and carbon were converted into phosphate, carbonate and water (Table 1).

For the regeneration tests, aged mineral oil with an interfacial tension of 15.4 dine cm 21 was employed using a digital tensiometer Kruss K10. A minimum interfacial tension value around of 40 dine cm 21 was adopted as being indicative of the end of the regeneration, since this value interfacial tension is tipical of the new oil.

Initial tests of the oil regeneration were carried out with CHS microparticles in order to verify the possible interactions of this binder with the polar compounds of the aged oil. This polymer is considered as a polybase due to the high percentage of amino groups distributed in the polymeric chain, it being capable of neutralizing acid and forming Schiff bases with aldehydes and ketones in aqueous medium. Thus, CHS is an excellent adsorbent material for polar compounds.

However, in non-aqueous medium, CHS showed a very low interaction with these compounds, being inefficient for the removal of polar compounds from the aged oil. Thus, the role of chitosan here is only as a binder.

Figure 3 shows the variation in the interfacial tension as a function of the CACP composition in the microparticles. The regeneration treatment was carried out in a column packed with 30 g of microparticles and 50 mL of oil was percolated. An interfacial tension of 45.0 dine cm 21 was obtained for a CACP composition of 95%, while the chitosan showed a tension of 20 dine cm 21 , which is a value close to that of used oil without treatment. Thus, the CACP-CHS adsorbent with 95% CACP composition was the most efficient in the removal of polar compounds from the oil, such as the corrosive carboxylic acid.

The CACP powder was found to be an excellent adsorbent, since it increased the interfacial tension of the aged oil to 46 dine cm 21 . However, this material was found not to be a viable option because of the prolonged time required for the oil to percolated through the column due to the packing with microparticles. This experiment demonstrated that the role of chitosan in the microparticles was as binder in order to agglutinate the inorganic interface, thus obtaining a particulate material with adsorbent characteriscs.

Another experiment was carried out passing oil through a column packed with CACP-CHS calcinated at 10008C, converting to hydroxyapatite in a single phase. The hydroxyapatite was not efficient in the removal of acid compounds from the insulating mineral oil.   The material with the optimum composition (CACP 95%) determined in a previous experiment, was employed to pack three columns, simulating the operational conditions of the CELESC regeneration plant.

Figure 4 shows the interfacial tension values as a function of the volume of regenerated oil percolated, using bauxite and the CACP-CHS microparticles. It was observed that the interfacial tension (IT) curves have the same profile with an increase in the oil volume. However, the IT curve of the bauxite adsorbent had a more accentuated decrease than that of the CACP-CHS, over the whole range studied.

For the first 100 mL of percolated oil the CACP-CHS adsorbent maintained an IT value of 48 dine cm 21 , while the bauxite had a significant decrease from 45 dine cm 21 to 37 dine cm 21 .

The performance of the new adsorbent was better than that of the bauxite over the whole range studied with a difference of around 10 dine cm 21 for each aliquot collected and analysed.

To reach the value of 40 dine cm 21 , which is the value indicative of the end of the regeneration process, 525 mL of oil were needed, using CACP-CHS, and 200 mL using bauxite, using the same procedure. Thus, CACP-CHS was 2.6 times more efficient than bauxite.

Figure 4 shows that a sample of aged oil was percolated through the three three interconected columns containing the CACP-CHS or bauxite. The determination of the interfacial tension (IT) and neutralization index (NI) values and a semi-quantitative analysis of the carbonyl content (CT) were carried out for the samples using a Bomem Hartmann &amp; Braun MB-series instrument and the results are given in Table 2.

The results shown in the above table confirm that CACP-CHS was more efficient than bauxite, according to the IT, NI and CT values. The table also shows that the carbonyl content remains high. This is attributed to the fact that both the CACP-CHS and bauxite remove only the carboxylic acid, while the other polar compounds containing carbonyl groups are not removed, which is also confirmed by the neutralization index values. Both the CACP-CHS and the bauxite caused a loss of colour in the regenerated oil, due to the removal of the carboxylic acids, which are the compounds responsible for the dark colour of aged oil. After the treatment with the adsorbents the colour of the oil becomes light yellow.

The contamination of the oil by the CACP-CHS adsorbent could affect the electric properties of the insulating oil by solubilization of chitosan or CACP. Physical and chemical changes of new oil such as colour, NI and IT can indicate this solubilization. In order to evaluate this possible contamination tests for the compatibility of this adsorbent and the oil were carried out following a methodology proposed by the American Society for Testing and Materials (ASTM, 1995) and these results were compared with the reference values. It was verified that CACP-CHS passed the compatibility test.

In order to reuse the adsorbent material two methods of CACP-CHS recovery were tested. In recovery A, the residual oil of the adsorbent was eliminated by percolating petroleum ether through the column until an aliquot of the solvent was colorless and the CACP-CHS was then heated to 2008C to effect its activation. In recovery B the residual oil was extracted in a Soxhlet extractor using petroleum ether as the solvent and the adsorbent was then dried at 608C. After the recovery of the adsorbent by methods A and B, the material was used in the regeneration of the aged oil.

Table 3 shows the results obtained with the reuse of the CACP-CHS adsorbent in the regeneration of the aged oil. In recovery process A, the adsorbent can be used four times to regenerate the insulating mineral oil, maintaining an IT value close to 40.0 dine cm 21 . The recovered material showed a regeneration power similar to the original CACP-CHS. However, in recovery process B a good efficiency was not achieved, since the reactivation power of the adsorbent is strongly dependent on the temperature used to eliminate the adsorbed compounds.

The CACP-CHS adsorbent containing 95% (w/w) of calcium phosphate used in the regeneration of the aged insulating mineral oil showed a better performance than bauxite in relation to the colour and interfacial tension (IT) of regenerated oil, and it also represents a good alternative from the environmental point of view, since the waste organo-mineral adsorbent is rich in nitrogen, carbon, phosphorous and calcium, and can thus be converted into a soil fertilizer after removal of the adsorbed residual oil.

Trans IChemE, Part B, Process Safety and Environmental Protection, 2007, 85(B4): 327-331</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Process Saf Environ Prot</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Al-Zahrani</author>
				<author>M Daous</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Standard test methods for compatibility of construction material with electrical insulating oil of petroleum origin</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Astm D</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1995</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Ann Chim Sci Mat</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Bihi</author>
				<author>M Bennani-Ziatini</author>
				<author>A Taitai</author>
				<author>A Lebugle</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2002</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Polymer</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Brugnerotto</author>
				<author>J Lizardi</author>
				<author>F Goycoolea</author>
				<author>W Arguelles-Monal</author>
				<author>J Desbrie `res</author>
				<author>M Rinaudo</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2001</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Dyes Pigm</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Chiu</author>
				<author>P Ho</author>
				<author>H Li</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2004</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Am Ceram Soc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Donadel</author>
				<author>M Laranjeira</author>
				<author>V Gonc ¸alves</author>
				<author>V Fa ´vere</author>
				<author>J Lima</author>
				<author>L Prates</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2005</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Sep Purif Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Guibal</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2004</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Water Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Juang</author>
				<author>H Shao</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2002</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids and Surf. A: Physicochem Eng Aspects</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Kro ´l</author>
				<author>B Kro ´l</author>
				<author>S Pikus</author>
				<author>K Skrzypiec</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2005</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>React Funct Polym</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Kumar</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>US Patent</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Lee</author>
				<author>C Rey</author>
				<author>M Ailova</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2001</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Transformer Oil</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Lishtein</author>
				<author>M Shakhnovich</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1970</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Ng</author>
				<author>W Cheung</author>
				<author>G Mckay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2002</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Bioresour Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Ngah</author>
				<author>S Ghani</author>
				<author>A Kamari</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2005</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids Surf A: Physicochem Eng Aspect</title>
			<authors>
				<author>W Ngah</author>
				<author>S Fatinathan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2006</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Ind Eng Chem Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Rorrer</author>
				<author>T Hsien</author>
				<author>J Way</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1993</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomaterials</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Tadic</author>
				<author>F Peters</author>
				<author>M Epple</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2002</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Carbohydr Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Varma</author>
				<author>S Deshpande</author>
				<author>J Kennedy</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2004</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Process Biochem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Wong</author>
				<author>Y Szeto</author>
				<author>W Cheung</author>
				<author>G Mckay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2004</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Hazard Mater, B</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Wu</author>
				<author>R Tseng</author>
				<author>R Juang</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
	<reference_dois>
		<number>DOI-10.1205/095758200530682</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0151-9107(02)80033-2</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0032-3861(00)00713-8</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0143-7208(03)00140-2</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1111/j.1551-2916.2005.00433.x</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.seppur.2003.10.004</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0043-1354(01)00537-1</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.colsurfa.2005.01.032</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S1381-5148(00)00038-9</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1006/jcis.2002.8664</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.biortech.2004.05.022</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.colsurfa.2005.11.093</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/ie00021a042</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0142-9612(01)00390-8</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.carbpol.2003.08.005</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0032-9592(03)00152-3</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0304-3894(99)00168-5</number>
	</reference_dois>
</document>
