<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/sara,+26577-70379-1-SM.pdf</file>
	<title>Dye and its removal from aqueous solution by adsorption: A review</title>
	<date>2014</date>
	<doi_number>10.1016/j.cis.2014.04.002</doi_number>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/sara,+26577-70379-1-SM.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>Mustafa T. Yagub</author>
		<author>Tushar Kanti Sen</author>
		<author>Sharmeen Afroze</author>
		<author>H.M. Ang</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>Calcium phosphate tricalcic apatitic (CaPT-Ap) was synthesized by co-precipitation at low temperature and basic medium. The potential of CaPT-Ap as an adsorbent was investigated in a batch reactor under different experimental conditions for removing dye Eriochrome Black T (EBT) from aqueous solutions. The used adsorbent was characterized by X-ray diffraction (XRD), infrared spectroscopy (FTIR) and chemical analysis indicate that this calcium phosphate is a CaPT-Ap. The effect of particle sizes , mass of the adsorbent, contact time ,temperature and the concentration of the dye on the adsorption were determined. The kinetic study showed that the pseudo-secondorder model gives a better description of the kinetics of the adsorption reaction than the pseudo-first-order model. Analysis of adsorption isotherms showed that adsorption governed by the isotherms of Freundlich. Thermodynamic parameters such as ΔG°, ΔS° and ΔH° were calculated. It was found that EBT dye adsorption was spontaneous and endothermic.</abstract>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>Synthesis and Characterization of the adsorbent material</heading>
			<text>The adsorption tests were conducted on a calcium phosphate: calcium phosphate tricalcic apatitic (CaPT-Ap) Ca9 (PO4)5 (HPO4) (OH) [25]. Its powder was prepared at room temperature by an aqueous double decomposition method of the salts of calcium and phosphate [26]; so to have nanoparticles and a large area, the solution A was quickly poured at room temperature [27] into a stirred reactor containing the solution B, stirring quickly for a few minutes and the precipitate was filtered under vacuum pump on a Buchner's funnel, washed with distilled water containing ammonia and finally dried in the oven at 120°C for 24 h. The adsorbent is crushed and sieved to obtain different particle sizes. The solution A: to 47 g of calcium nitrate Ca(NO3)2•4H2O (Reidel-de haen,97%) prepared in 550 ml of distilled water, 20 ml of ammonia solution(d = 0.91) was added. The solution B: to 26 g of di-ammonium hydrogen phosphate (NH4)2HPO4 (Reidel-de haen 99%) prepared in 1300 ml of distilled water, 20 ml ammonia solution (d = 0.91) was added. The calcium and the phosphate ion content in the powder were determined respectively by complexometry with EDTA and by spectrophotometry after the formation of the blue phosphomolybdate complex (λmax = 880 nm). The constitution and phase purity of the synthesized powders were checked by X-ray diffractometry using a Bruker D8 Advance apparatus. The presence of functional groups was also investigated by the Fourier transform infrared (FTIR) spectroscopy. A mixture of synthesized powder and spectroscopic grade KBr was ground in an agate mortar and was pressed to obtain a thin transparent pellet. IR spectra were collected by a Shimadzu IR Affinity-1S FTIR spectrometer in the spectral range 4000-400 cm -1 .</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Adsorption experiment</heading>
			<text>In this part, we have studied the effect of dyes concentrations, mass of adsorbent, duration time and the particle sizes on the adsorption of EBT by CaPT-Ap. The batch adsorption experiments were carried out at ambient temperature in conical flasks at a constant agitation speed of 500 rpm by varying the adsorbent dosage from 0 to 4.0 g.L -1 ; the duration time is about 4h; the initial dyes concentrations were from 5 to 100 mg.L -1 , the particle sizes were from 0 to1mm and the temperature range 7 to 60°C. The pH was about 6.10. Different amount of CaPT-Ap nanoparticles was added to EBT solution (previously known concentration); the mixing operation was done for adsorption in multiple shakers. After each adsorption experiment, the samples were centrifuged at 4000 rpm for 10 min to separate the solid phase from the liquid one. The supernatants were analyzed for residual dye concentrations by a T60 UV/Vis spectrophotometer. The quantity of dye adsorbed and percentage removal were calculated by the following expressions ( 1) and ( 2):

(

(2)

were the m is the mass of adsorbent (g), V the volume of the solution (L),C0 the initial concentration of adsorbate (mg.L -1 ), Ce is the equilibrium adsorbate concentration (mg.L -1 ), and qe is the amount of adsorbate adsorbed per unit mass of adsorbent (mol.g -1 ) at equilibrium (mg of EBT per g of adsorbent CaPT-Ap) .</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>The world has seen a raw development in technology to meet the needs of the world, especially in the textile field with the increase of demand for textiles which in turn increases the demand for textile dyes. This pushes us to make the treatment of wastewater our environmental priority. Adsorption techniques are widely used to remove dyes from wastewater [1]- [3]. It is currently known that a great part of natural calcium phosphates adopts a crystalline structure similar to that of synthetic hydroxyapatite Ca10(PO4)6(OH)2 [4]- [8] The composition of natural phosphates is very complex. Indeed, the lattice allows various anionic and cationic substitutions [5], [9]- [12]. Despite their low cost and their availability in the market, the use and application of apatite as adsorbents is still a subject of relatively scarce investigations, chromium [13] nickel [14] dyes [15] industrial gas [16] Proteins [17] fluoride [18]- [21] phenolic substances [22] pharmaceutical contaminant [23]. In addition, several studies have shown that this material can be efficient matrices of water purification [20] [24]. However, as far as we know, it is the first time that in the present work, we studied the use of calcium phosphate tricalcic apatitic (CaPT-Ap) prepared by co-precipitation at ambient temperature and basic medium as adsorbent to remove dye Eriochrome Black T (EBT) in aqueous solution. The synthesized CaPT-Ap was characterized using several experimental techniques such as X-ray diffraction, FT-IR spectroscopy and chemical analysis.

The adsorption tests were conducted on a calcium phosphate: calcium phosphate tricalcic apatitic (CaPT-Ap) Ca9 (PO4)5 (HPO4) (OH) [25]. Its powder was prepared at room temperature by an aqueous double decomposition method of the salts of calcium and phosphate [26]; so to have nanoparticles and a large area, the solution A was quickly poured at room temperature [27] into a stirred reactor containing the solution B, stirring quickly for a few minutes and the precipitate was filtered under vacuum pump on a Buchner's funnel, washed with distilled water containing ammonia and finally dried in the oven at 120°C for 24 h. The adsorbent is crushed and sieved to obtain different particle sizes. The solution A: to 47 g of calcium nitrate Ca(NO3)2•4H2O (Reidel-de haen,97%) prepared in 550 ml of distilled water, 20 ml of ammonia solution(d = 0.91) was added. The solution B: to 26 g of di-ammonium hydrogen phosphate (NH4)2HPO4 (Reidel-de haen 99%) prepared in 1300 ml of distilled water, 20 ml ammonia solution (d = 0.91) was added. The calcium and the phosphate ion content in the powder were determined respectively by complexometry with EDTA and by spectrophotometry after the formation of the blue phosphomolybdate complex (λmax = 880 nm). The constitution and phase purity of the synthesized powders were checked by X-ray diffractometry using a Bruker D8 Advance apparatus. The presence of functional groups was also investigated by the Fourier transform infrared (FTIR) spectroscopy. A mixture of synthesized powder and spectroscopic grade KBr was ground in an agate mortar and was pressed to obtain a thin transparent pellet. IR spectra were collected by a Shimadzu IR Affinity-1S FTIR spectrometer in the spectral range 4000-400 cm -1 .

The physical characteristics of Eriochrome Black T (EBT) which is an acidic synthetic dye are given in Table 1. It was provided by &quot;Labochemie&quot;.

In this part, we have studied the effect of dyes concentrations, mass of adsorbent, duration time and the particle sizes on the adsorption of EBT by CaPT-Ap. The batch adsorption experiments were carried out at ambient temperature in conical flasks at a constant agitation speed of 500 rpm by varying the adsorbent dosage from 0 to 4.0 g.L -1 ; the duration time is about 4h; the initial dyes concentrations were from 5 to 100 mg.L -1 , the particle sizes were from 0 to1mm and the temperature range 7 to 60°C. The pH was about 6.10. Different amount of CaPT-Ap nanoparticles was added to EBT solution (previously known concentration); the mixing operation was done for adsorption in multiple shakers. After each adsorption experiment, the samples were centrifuged at 4000 rpm for 10 min to separate the solid phase from the liquid one. The supernatants were analyzed for residual dye concentrations by a T60 UV/Vis spectrophotometer. The quantity of dye adsorbed and percentage removal were calculated by the following expressions ( 1) and ( 2):

(

(2)

were the m is the mass of adsorbent (g), V the volume of the solution (L),C0 the initial concentration of adsorbate (mg.L -1 ), Ce is the equilibrium adsorbate concentration (mg.L -1 ), and qe is the amount of adsorbate adsorbed per unit mass of adsorbent (mol.g -1 ) at equilibrium (mg of EBT per g of adsorbent CaPT-Ap) .

The contact time is one of the important parameters for the successful application of adsorption procedures to understand in details the exact dynamics mechanism of the adsorption process, three general kinetics models, namely, pseudo-first-order, pseudo-second-order and second-order were applied to the experimental data [28].

The linear forms of these models are given in equation ( 3), ( 4) and ( 5) respectively:

Pseudo first order equation:

(

Pseudo second order equation:

Second order equation: (5) Where; qt and qe are the adsorption capacities at time t and equilibrium, respectively (mg.g -1 ), t is the contact time (min). k1 is the rate constant of pseudo-first-order adsorption (min -1 ), k2 is the rate constant of pseudo-second-order adsorption (g min -1 mg -1 ) and k3 is the rate constant of second-order adsorption (g min -1 mg -1 ).

To plot log (qe-qt) versus t gives a linear relationship from which k1 and qe can be determined from the slope.

The plot of t/qt versus t shows a linear relationship and allows us to calculate k2 and qe. From the plot of 1/(qe-qt) versus t, we can calculate k3 and qe.

Experimental data were simulated with linear forms of Langmuir [29] and Freundlich [30] models, recommended for dye adsorption. The linearized form of Langmuir (6) and Freundlich (7) equations are expressed as follows:

Where qe is the amount of BET adsorbed per unit mass of adsorbent (mg.g -1 ); Ce is the equilibrium concentration of BET solution (mg.L -1 ); qmax the maximum quantity adsorbed. The constants KF, KL and n of the model can be determinate from the slop of the plot of Ce/qe versus Ce and the plot of log qe versus log Ce. Langmuir isotherm assumes the homogenous nature of adsorption with equal energy of the entire active adsorption sites [31] and

Freundlich isotherm applies to heterogeneous surfaces [32].

Temperature is an important factor in the adsorption process and the adsorbent's performance at equilibrium. The adsorption phenomenon is always accompanied by a thermal process which can be either exothermic (ΔH°&lt; 0) or endothermic (ΔH°&gt; 0) and the measurement of the heat of adsorption ΔH is the main criterion that differentiates the process of chemisorption from physisorption. To evaluate the effect of temperature on adsorption process of BET onto the adsorbent powder, thermodynamic parameters such as standard Gibbs free energy change (ΔG°), enthalpy change (ΔH°) and entropy change (ΔS°) are determined according to the equations:

(10) (11) Were; K is the distribution coefficient, ΔG° is the Gibbs free energy change (J.mol -1 ), ΔH° is the enthalpy change (J.mol -1 ), ΔS° is the entropy change (J.mol -1 .K -1 ), T is the absolute temperature in Kelvin (°K), R is the universal gas constant (8.31 J.K -1 .mol -1 ), Ce the equilibrium adsorbate concentration in the aqueous phase (mg.l -1 ),qe the amount of EBT adsorbed per unit mass of adsorbent (mg.g -1 ) .Plotting the linear transform of Ln (K) versus (1 / T) gives a straight line with slope and intercept equal to -ΔH°/R and ΔS°/R.This allows us to determinate by identification with the equations, the enthalpy ΔH° and entropy ΔS° of adsorption and deduces the Gibbs free energy ΔG ° at different temperatures.

The IR spectrum of the sample is presented in Figure 1, the bands appearing at 1097 and 1035, 961, 603 and 564 and 471 cm -1 are assigned respectively to the ν3 (P-O) asymmetric stretching mode, ν1 (P-O) symmetric stretching mode, ν4

(O-P-O) bending mode and ν2 (O-P-O) bending mode [33]. Broadbands appearing at around 3446 and 1645 cm -1 could be linked to adsorbed water [34]. A sharp peak at 3569 cm -1 is associated with OH -stretching mode and a peak appearing at 632 cm -1 is also related to bending mode [35]- [39]. There is also a low-intensity band at 875cm -1 which could be ascribed to the structural HPO4 2-entities [40], [41]. The presence of HPO4 2-and OH -ions confirms that this calcium phosphate prepared by co-precipitation in the basic medium at ambient temperature is a CaPT-Ap [42] [43].

Our results are following the literature in which the authors reported the same calcium phosphate [13], [15], [44].

4000 3600 3200 2800 2400 2000 1600 1200 800 400

Wavenumber (cm -1 )

Figure 2 shows the X-ray diffraction pattern for the dried calcium phosphate. The XRD pattern shows a broad peak indicating that the powder is poorly crystalline and CaPT-Ap, without the presence of impurity phases. Our XRD data were found to be consistent with literature [13], [15], [20], [42], [45].

From chemical analysis, our adsorbent was found to have an average Ca/P ratio of 1.49 ( 28.1 % wt P; 14.6 % wt Ca) which allow us to confirm that this calcium phosphate tricalcic apatitic CaPT-Ap [26][27].

The effect of adsorbent's particles size was studied in the range of 0-1mm (0-255µm, 255-450µm, 450µm -1mm) for checking the maximum adsorption of EBT at ambient temperature and pH = 6.10. The smallest mesh particles (0-255µm) presents a larger surface area that was shown to be the best for adsorption (Figure 3).

The effect of adsorbent dose was investigated, by varying the mass CaPT-Ap (0-255µm) from 0 to 4 g.L -1 which was added to EBT whose initial concentration was 10 mg.L -1 . The others parameters were kept constants. Figure 4 shows that the efficiency capacity of removal EBT dye increased and reached its maximum (85%) at the addition of adsorbent dose 1g.L -1 .In addition, the adsorption capacity decreased with the increase of adsorbent dosage. We suggest that these results can be explained that at high doses of adsorbent added, the available sites decreased.  Qads (mg/g) Figure 5. Effect of contact time on the percentage of removal of EBT and the quantity adsorbed of EBT

Figure 6 shows that the capacity of adsorption decreases from 92% to 74% when the dye concentration increased from 10 to 100 mg.L -1 . This result can be explained by the fact that available active sites are insufficient when the initial dye concentration is high.

Figure 8 presents the plot of the linear transforms of the three kinetic models. The linear variation of t/qt with the time suggests that the pseudo-second-order model describes well the kinetic behaviour of the EBT adsorption on CaPT-Ap (R 2 =0.987). The experimental adsorption Qe,exp (7 mg.g -1 ) is very close to the obtained (Qe,cal ) by the pseudo-second-order (Table 2). According to this latter model, we can state that the adsorption of EBT on CaPT-Ap involves the chemisorption process in addition to the physisorption [46].

Figure 9 presents the plot of the linear transforms of the two adsorptions isotherms models Langmuir and Freundlich.

The linear variation of Ln(Qe) versus Ln(Ce) suggests that the Freundlich model fits well the experimental values (R 2 = 0.965) (Table 3). According to this later model, we can conclude that the EBT adsorption by CaPT-Ap is done on a heterogeneous surface [32].

The observed increase in the capacity adsorption of dye on adsorbent with the increase in temperature is indicative of the fact that the adsorption process is endothermic in nature.

The observed increase in the capacity adsorption of dye on adsorbent with the increase in temperature is indicative of the fact that the adsorption process is endothermic in nature. Figure 10 presents the plot of linear transform of Ln (K)

versus (1 / T) Table 4 shows the results obtained for the thermodynamic adsorption parameters. The positive value of the enthalpy ΔH° indicates that the adsorption process of NET on CaPT-Ap is endothermic in nature (by increasing T we promote adsorption) [47]. The positive value of the entropy ΔS° means that the adsorption is accompanied by a disorder of the medium thus showing that the molecules of the dye adsorbed on the surface of the adsorbent are organized randomly.

Likewise, the negative values of the Gibbs free energy ΔG ° at each temperature, confirm that the adsorption of the dye on the surface of the adsorbent is a spontaneous process [48][49].

Generally, the method used to prepare the CaPT-Ap was efficient and successful, as shown by the characterization analysis. In the present work, we tested the adsorption of EBT on CaPT-Ap prepared by co-precipitation at ambient temperature in a basic medium. The results show that the adsorption kinetic of EBT is well described by the pseudosecond-order model. The adsorptions isotherms satisfactorily by the Freundlich model and the thermodynamic study indicates that the adsorption process is a spontaneous, disordered and endothermic physisorption.

All characteristics indicate that CaPT-Ap could be used as an efficient and low-cost adsorbent for water treatment.

B Figure 9. Plots of (A) Langmuir model and (B) Freundlich model Figure 10. Linear plot of ln (K) versus (1/T) for the adsorption of BET dye onto the adsorbent</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Adv. Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Yagub</author>
				<author>T Sen</author>
				<author>S Afroze</author>
				<author>H Ang</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2014</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Moroccan J. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Tcheka</author>
				<author>D Abia</author>
				<author>D Iya-Sou</author>
				<author>A Tamgue</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Moroccan J. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Hassan</author>
				<author>A Shahat</author>
				<author>A El-Didamony</author>
				<author>M El-Desouky</author>
				<author>A El-Bindary</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2020</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Materials</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Dorozhkin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2009</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif. Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>G Penel</author>
				<author>G Leroy</author>
				<author>C Rey</author>
				<author>E Bres</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1998</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Biomed. Mater. Res. -Part B Appl. Biomater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Ogose</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2005</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Rev. Mater</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Sossa</author>
				<author>B Giraldo</author>
				<author>B Garcia</author>
				<author>E Parra</author>
				<author>P Arango</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2018</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomaterials</title>
			<authors>
				<author>D Tadic</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2003</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomaterials</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Antonakos</author>
				<author>E Liarokapis</author>
				<author>T Leventouri</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2007</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Thermochim. Acta</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Yahia</author>
				<author>M</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2010</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Eur. Ceram. Soc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>I Cacciotti</author>
				<author>A Bianco</author>
				<author>M Lombardi</author>
				<author>L Montanaro</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2009</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Alloys Compd</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Mostafa</author>
				<author>H Hassan</author>
				<author>F Mohamed</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2009</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Surfaces and Interfaces</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Elouahli</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2018-09</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Saudi Chem. Soc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>I Mobasherpour</author>
				<author>E Salahi</author>
				<author>M Pazouki</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2011</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>DES</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Boujaady</author>
				<author>A Rhilassi</author>
				<author>M Bennani-Ziatni</author>
				<author>R Hamri</author>
				<author>A Taitai</author>
				<author>J Lacout</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2011</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Phys. Lett</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Souza</author>
				<author>M Matos</author>
				<author>B Galvão</author>
				<author>A Arapiraca</author>
				<author>S Da Silva</author>
				<author>I Pinheiro</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2019</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Biomed. Mater. Res</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Ohta</author>
				<author>H Monma</author>
				<author>S Takahashi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2001</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Arch. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Spinelli</author>
				<author>F Brudevold</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1971</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>PO4)</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N De Leeuw</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2004</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Desalin. Water Treat</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Mourabet</author>
				<author>A Rhilassi</author>
				<author>M Bennani-Ziatni</author>
				<author>R Hamri</author>
				<author>A Taitai</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Saudi Chem. Soc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Mourabet</author>
				<author>A Rhilassi</author>
				<author>H Boujaady</author>
				<author>M Bennani-Ziatni</author>
				<author>R Hamri</author>
				<author>A Taitai</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2015</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Bioresour. Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Fan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2019</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Eng. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Ravi</author>
				<author>Y Choi</author>
				<author>J Choe</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2020-01</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Moroccan J. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Mourid</author>
				<author>I Qor</author>
				<author>L Benaziz</author>
				<author>M Lakraimi</author>
				<author>E Khattabi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2018</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Calcif. Tissue Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J.-C Heughebaert</author>
				<author>G Montel</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1982</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Contributiona l'Étude de l'Évolution des Orthophosphates de Calcium Précipités en Orthophosphates Apatitiques</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Heughebaert</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Rev. Phys. Appliquée</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J.-C Heughebaert</author>
				<author>G Montel</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1977</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Process Saf. Environ. Prot</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Ho</author>
				<author>G Mckay</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1998-05</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Am. Chem. Soc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>I Langmuir</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1916</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Phys. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Freundlich</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1906</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Desalin. Water Treat</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Jarrah</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2010</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Arab. J. Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Sepehr</author>
				<author>T Al-Musawi</author>
				<author>E Ghahramani</author>
				<author>H Kazemian</author>
				<author>M Zarrabi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Mater. Sci. Mater. Med</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Kawata</author>
				<author>H Uchida</author>
				<author>K Itatani</author>
				<author>I Okada</author>
				<author>S Koda</author>
				<author>M Aizawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2004</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Ceram. Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B Nasiri-Tabrizi</author>
				<author>A Fahami</author>
				<author>R Ebrahimi-Kahrizsangi</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Powder Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>F Bakan</author>
				<author>O Laçin</author>
				<author>H Sarac</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Ceram. Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Varma</author>
				<author>S Babu</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2005</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochem. Eng. J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Vaghetti</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2008</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Infrared spectral interpretation: a systematic approach</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B Smith</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2018</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Environ. Manage</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Calvete</author>
				<author>E Lima</author>
				<author>N Cardoso</author>
				<author>J Vaghetti</author>
				<author>S Dias</author>
				<author>F Pavan</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2010</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Spectrochim. Acta</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Chapman</author>
				<author>L Thirlwell</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1964</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Arch. Oral Biol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B Fowler</author>
				<author>E Moreno</author>
				<author>W Brown</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1966</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Saudi Chem. Soc</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Boujaady</author>
				<author>M Mourabet</author>
				<author>A Rhilassi</author>
				<author>M Bennani-Ziatni</author>
				<author>R Hamri</author>
				<author>A Taitai</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2017</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Acta Biomaterialia</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Combes</author>
				<author>C Rey</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2010</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>infrared</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Nanoparticules</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2015</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Ceram. Int</title>
			<authors>
				<author>B Nasiri-Tabrizi</author>
				<author>A Fahami</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2013</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J. Water Resour. Prot</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Allam</author>
				<author>A Bouari</author>
				<author>B Belhorma</author>
				<author>L Bih</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2016</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Chem. Data Collect</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Dehmani</author>
				<author>O Khalki</author>
				<author>H Mezougane</author>
				<author>S Abouarnadasse</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Sci. Rep</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Egbosiuba</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Sci. Rep</title>
			<authors>
				<author>N Danesh</author>
				<author>M Ghorbani</author>
				<author>A Marjani</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2021</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
	<reference_dois>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0143-7208(95)00048-8</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0273-1223(99)00393-5</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2008.11.031</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S1010-6030(00)00377-4</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s11270-013-1818-4</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/BF00547128</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1128/AEM.64.3.1123-1129.1998</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/09593331808616600</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0032-9592(03)00152-3</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s11270-010-0663-y</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s11270-012-1277-3</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jenvman.2008.11.017</number>
		<number>DOI-10.4236/jwarp.2012.42011</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.carbpol.2012.06.078</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jenvman.2012.08.028</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2011.07.019</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.biortech.2005.05.001</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jenvman.2010.05.003</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s11270-010-0382-4</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2009.12.047</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/978-3-540-38522-6_7</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jenvman.2005.01.012</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.envint.2004.02.001</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.dyepig.2003.11.002</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.biortech.2006.05.011</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0960-8524(96)00113-7</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0273-1223(96)00700-7</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0960-8524(01)00028-1</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0032-9592(01)00234-5</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S1093-0191(01)00123-X</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S1093-0191(01)00123-X</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0043-1354(90)90063-C</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1002/col.20132</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0960-8524(02)00201-8</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0960-8524(00)00080-8</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.ecoleng.2011.10.004</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S1385-8947(03)00100-1</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0001-8686(00)00082-8</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.clay.2008.03.015</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.colsurfb.2011.02.009</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.watres.2012.01.009</number>
		<number>DOI-10.2166/wst.2010.388</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1002/ep.11680</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.seppur.2005.01.002</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2006.09.097</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0143-7208(01)00056-0</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/01496390701885331</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.colsurfa.2005.06.001</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2004.09.063</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/01496391003696921</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s11270-013-1582-5</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s11814-012-0096-y</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2005.10.032</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2010.08.036</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.chemosphere.2005.03.065</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.indcrop.2012.05.008</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jtice.2013.01.010</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1111/j.1747-6593.2011.00300.x</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.biortech.2008.04.014</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2008.09.009</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2012.05.075</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/19443994.2013.782083</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.arabjc.2013.06.005</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.biortech.2013.03.048</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s11356-012-0947-4</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/19443994.2012.749019</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2010.05.032</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2011.01.049</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0956-053X(00)00076-3</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0960-8524(03)00058-0</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0032-9592(98)00112-5</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1061/JSEDAI.0000430</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2008.06.046</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2006.09.029</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2006.07.072</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2010.07.047</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/je101204j</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2007.10.071</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/ja02242a004</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1002/ep.11673</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2007.01.145</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2004.05.029</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2007.03.038</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2011.03.029</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.procbio.2004.06.007</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0273-1223(97)00387-9</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0304-3894(02)00263-7</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.procbio.2003.11.035</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.biortech.2004.07.011</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0032-9592(02)00239-X</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2012.02.045</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.biortech.2012.08.128</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2010.03.041</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/01496390802222640</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2009.06.060</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.dyepig.2004.05.005</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0304-3894(02)00017-1</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2008.05.036</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2008.08.084</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2008.01.034</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2007.11.093</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2007.06.025</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2006.06.107</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2007.05.023</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2005.01.007</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/ef9001132</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.dyepig.2004.06.016</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1002/clen.200900158</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.carbpol.2011.06.058</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.bej.2005.08.004</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2010.11.046</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2010.07.017</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2010.09.043</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2011.02.021</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/01496395.2011.630335</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/02772248.2012.707656</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2008.09.028</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2010.09.019</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2007.07.005</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2010.07.010</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.dyepig.2006.01.027</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0008-6223(02)00367-6</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0143-7208(02)00160-2</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.colsurfa.2005.03.027</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.chemosphere.2004.04.004</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2003.08.071</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0043-1354(02)00375-5</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2004.03.019</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jenvman.2004.08.016</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.colsurfa.2005.08.044</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2006.06.094</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cis.2011.04.005</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2006.06.003</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2007.09.050</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/ie010667+</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.watres.2003.08.011</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2005.09.029</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2008.01.105</number>
		<number>DOI-10.5004/dwt.2009.967</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0045-6535(92)90316-J</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0045-6535(96)00385-2</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1081/SS-120003521</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.watres.2004.09.011</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2006.04.063</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/ie034218g</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2004.02.012</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S1369-703X(02)00177-8</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2008.08.029</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.fuel.2008.05.022</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s11270-012-1349-4</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1023/A:1008169111023</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0269-7491(92)90161-3</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0169-4332(02)00248-9</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0043-1354(01)00056-2</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2004.02.091</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.dyepig.2003.11.007</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0143-7208(01)00066-3</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2011.07.033</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.seppur.2003.12.018</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2005.09.036</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2011.05.013</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1023/A:1011652224816</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.desal.2010.05.062</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2009.01.014</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2005.11.048</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2005.01.012</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2005.01.035</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0043-1354(02)00540-7</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1081/SS-100106104</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1111/cote.12019</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1002/clen.200800167</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.cej.2006.01.018</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.biortech.2006.06.010</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1002/jctb.1192</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.biortech.2005.02.045</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jhazmat.2006.12.055</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0269-7491(03)00107-6</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/02757540600579607</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0141-0229(02)00110-2</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0960-8524(01)00172-9</number>
		<number>DOI-10.2166/wqrj.2000.006</number>
	</reference_dois>
</document>
