<document>
	<file>./pdf-files/Utilization of surface energetics approach to Understand protein interaction to ceramic hydroxyapatite.pdf</file>
	<title>Utilization of surface energetics approach to Understand protein interaction to ceramic hydroxyapatite</title>
	<date>2013</date>
	<doi_number>10.1002/jctb.4065</doi_number>
	<img_preview_path>./pdf-preview-images/Utilization of surface energetics approach to Understand protein interaction to ceramic hydroxyapatite.jpeg</img_preview_path>
	<authors>
		<author>Muhammad Aasim</author>
		<author>Noor Shad Bibi</author>
		<author>Rami Reddy Vennapusa</author>
		<author>Marcelo Fernandez‐Lahore</author>
	</authors>
	<abstract>AbstractBackgroundA surface thermodynamics approach can be utilized to understand protein interaction during adsorption chromatography. Ceramic hydroxyapatite has been widely used in the purification of biomolecules during downstream bio‐processing. Protein interaction with this adsorbent is a complicated process.ResultsIn this work, interaction between model proteins and an adsorbent (ceramic hydroxyapatite Type I) was studied via extended DLVO (Derjaguin, Landau, Verwey and Overbeek) theory. The surface energy parameters of proteins and adsorbent were determined from experimental contact angle and zeta potential values. In ceramic hydroxyapatite chromatography, protein adsorption takes place under mixed mode conditions i.e. cationic exchange and calcium chelation. The sample is loaded in low salt and eluted at increasing phosphate gradient. The XDLVO approach calculated the free energy of interaction as a function of distance, between the interacting surfaces under de‐binding conditions. The calculated interaction energy of the model proteins with CHT were correlated with the actual elution behavior. This revealed that all the proteins show minimum binding energies, i.e. |0.005| ± 0.002 kT under the observed conditions. These energy values are considered to be a cutoff between retaining and non‐retaining conditions. Higher energy values will explain binding and lower energies will explain elution (binding &amp;gt; |0.005| kT &amp;gt; elution).ConclusionKnowledge generated from these studies will assist understanding of adsorption of proteins to the process supports which could facilitate better bioprocess design and optimization. © 2013 Society of Chemical Industry</abstract>
	<methods>
		<method>
			<heading>Materials</heading>
			<text>Ceramic hydroxyapatite (CHT Type I, 40 µm particle size, 600-800 Â pore size) was purchased from Bio-Rad Laboratories (California, USA), Tricon (5 mm internal diameter and 100 mm length) columns were purchased from GE Healthcare (Munich, Germany). 1-bromonaphthalene and formamide were from Fluka (Buchs, Switzerland). Ultrapure water was used for contact angle determinations. All other chemicals were of analytical grade. The ultrafiltration system (Model 8050) and the regenerated cellulose membranes (10 kDa MWCO; 44.5 mm in diameter) were from Millipore (Billerica, Massachusetts, USA).

The Goniometer system (OCA 20) was obtained from Data Physics Instruments GmbH (Filerstadt, Germany). Zeta potential values were measured with a Zetasizer Nano ZS obtained from Malvern Instruments (Worcestershire, United Kingdom). The SurPASS electrokinetic analyzer EKA was from Anton Paar GmbH (Graz, Austria).</text>
		</method>
		<method>
			<heading>Thin layer wicking method</heading>
			<text>The CHT was characterized by contact angle measurements using the thin layer wicking technique, which is an alternative tool to the conventional sessile drop method. It utilizes the concept of capillary rise method. The CHT powder was packed in a capillary tube, the rise of the probe liquid is monitored as a function of time to determine the effective pore radius. The contact angle of probe liquid is evaluated using Washburn's equation: 22,23

where h is the liquid rise in the capillary, R eff the effective interstitial pore radius, γ L the surface tension of the liquid, θ the contact angle between the liquid and the solid, η the viscosity of the liquid and t is the time. To evaluate R eff , wicking experiments were made using low-energy apolar liquids, i.e. heptane, octane, decane and dodecane which spreads very faster and forms a zero contact angle. Once the R eff is determined, the contact angle of the probe liquids can be determined by running wicking methods separately for each liquid.</text>
		</method>
	</methods>
	<full_text>Calcium phosphate based stationary phase, hydroxyapatite [Ca 10 (PO 4 ) 6 (OH) 2 ] (CHT), has been widely utilized in the purification and separation of biological macromolecules such as proteins, enzymes, viruses and nucleic acids in today's demanding downstream processing. 1,2 It was initially introduced for protein purification in 1956 by Tiselius et al. 1,3 CHT is the inorganic component of bones and teeth and is widely utilized in coating artificial bones, bone fillings and drug carriers due to its excellent bio-affinity. 2 The adsorption of protein to CHT occurs in cationic and anionic modes, depending on the operating buffer conditions. 4 It has the capability to bind proteins, mainly with phosphoryl cation exchange with amino residues of protein called P-site interaction and calcium chelation with clusters of carboxyl residues, C-site interactions. 3,5,6 Amino groups interact nonspecifically with the negative charged groups on CHT by electrostatic interaction, when equilibrated with phosphate buffer.

4 ----H + 3 N -Protein Carboxyl groups of proteins are either repelled electrostatically from the negative charge of the CHT or bind specifically by complexation to calcium sites.

4 ----H + 3 N -Protein Basic proteins are eluted either by charge screening through phosphate or by specific displacement by Ca +2 and Mg +2 ions that complex with the phosphate of CHT and neutralize their charge. Acidic proteins are eluted from CHT by displacement of their carboxyl from HA-Ca +2 by ions which form stronger complexes with calcium than do carboxyl, e.g. fluoride and phosphate. 7 The interaction of the P-site is not explained by a simple cation exchange mechanism; similarly, the physicochemical basis for www.soci.org M Aasim et al.

C-site interaction is less clear. Moreover, it is well described in the literature that certain bio-molecules bearing negative surface charge are still retained by negative charged CHT. 8 A complex interaction mechanism has been observed for larger proteins due to heterogeneity of the surface charge. Such proteins exhibit mixed mode binding to CHT surface, regardless of their net charge. 9 The contribution of possible interactions can be adjusted via the composition of the mobile phase. 8 During CHT chromatography sample loading is performed at low concentration, i.e. 10-25 mmol L -1 , while eluted in increasing phosphate gradient. 4 Colloidal particle-solid substrate interaction has been widely investigated by the surface thermodynamics approach in various fields of science. It has also been used to explain biomass and bio-molecules interaction with chromatographic supports in downstream bioprocesses. 10 -14 In the above context, protein interaction with the hydrophobic support has already been studied applying the surface thermodynamics approach. 13,15 Insufficient information is available to study protein adsorption to CHT. Basic studies were performed to study protein adsorption isotherms on CHT to investigate the effect of texture of the ceramics and the effect of molecular weight on the retention of proteins. 16,17 But no detailed description of the underlying phenomenon is available. The physicochemical approach could be one possible answer to understand this interaction phenomenon at nano-scale. In this perspective, contact angle measurements and zeta potentials determinations can be used to study interfacial free energy and subsequently, protein adsorption. 18 The CHT surface contains positive (calcium) and negative (phosphate) sites. Since they are mainly operated at pH 6.8, the surface can be regarded as negative due to partial neutralization of the positive calcium loci by phosphate ions. 19 Proteins adsorbed to CHT may involve both short range and long range interaction forces. 20 XDLVO type calculations can quantitatively estimate the interaction energy of proteins to adsorbent. This theory has already been used to explain the protein (as nano-colloidal particle) interaction with the adsorbent bead. According to this theory the interaction of the particle with the solid support is the sum of Lifshitz Van der Waals (LW), acid base (AB), electrostatic (EL) energies. 11 -13,21 The surface property of the CHT is characterized by contact angle measurement using a thin layer wicking technique, utilizing the concept of capillary rise method. 22,23 The aim of this work was the fundamental understanding of protein adsorption behavior under de-binding conditions. The model system utilized to prove this concept was the interaction of proteins onto complex chromatographic support, i.e. ceramic hydroxyapatite, utilizing the surface thermodynamics approach. A plot was achieved to compare the free interaction energy minima and retention volume values. Interaction energy calculations were performed on the basis of experimental information provided by the contact angle, zeta potential, thin layer wicking and streaming potential determinations.

Ceramic hydroxyapatite (CHT Type I, 40 µm particle size, 600-800 Â pore size) was purchased from Bio-Rad Laboratories (California, USA), Tricon (5 mm internal diameter and 100 mm length) columns were purchased from GE Healthcare (Munich, Germany). 1-bromonaphthalene and formamide were from Fluka (Buchs, Switzerland). Ultrapure water was used for contact angle determinations. All other chemicals were of analytical grade. The ultrafiltration system (Model 8050) and the regenerated cellulose membranes (10 kDa MWCO; 44.5 mm in diameter) were from Millipore (Billerica, Massachusetts, USA).

The Goniometer system (OCA 20) was obtained from Data Physics Instruments GmbH (Filerstadt, Germany). Zeta potential values were measured with a Zetasizer Nano ZS obtained from Malvern Instruments (Worcestershire, United Kingdom). The SurPASS electrokinetic analyzer EKA was from Anton Paar GmbH (Graz, Austria).

Hen's Egg White Lysozyme (HEWL) and Bovine Serum Albumin (BSA) were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (Munich, Germany). Polygalacturonase from Aspergillus niger (Pectinex  3XL) and aminopeptidase from Aspergillus oryzae (Flavorzyme  ) were purchased from Novozymes (Lund, Sweden). Chymosin from Aspergillus niger var. Awamori (CHY-MAX  ), aspartic protease from Rhizomucor miehei (Hannilase  L 205), and beta-galactosidase from Kluyveromyces lactis (HA-Lactase 5200) were from CHR. HANSEN (Holdorf, Germany). Total human immunoglobulin G (hT-IgG /Octagam  ) was from Octapharma (Langenfeld, Germany). Lactoferrin was obtained from Biopole (Namur, Belgium). All protein solutions were extensively dialyzed against water and stored as a lyophilized powder until further use.

Homogenous protein layers were formed in the hydrated and dehydrated state. 13,24 -27 Briefly, 1.0 mL of protein solution (2 mg mL -1 prepared in 20 mmol L -1 phosphate buffer, pH 7.0) was deposited on a conventional microscopy glass slide, which was placed on a properly leveled surface in a clean bench, free of dust particles. The liquid was allowed to evaporate overnight at room temperature.

As an alternative to protein deposition on glass, proteins were adsorbed onto the plastic surface provided by a disposable Petri dish. Briefly, 10 mL of protein solution (2 mg mL -1 ) was contacted with the plastic surface for 24 h at 24 o C, in a closed and humidified environment. Excess liquid was decanted and the surface washed with ultrapure water. Finally, the surface was dried under vacuum at 24 • C. This method provided information on proteins in the dehydrated state. 13 To allow for the measurement of contact angles on hydrated protein layers, protein deposition onto hydrophilic ultrafiltration membranes (10 kDa, MWCO) was implemented. 13,24 -27 A 3% protein solution in 20 mmol L -1 phosphate buffer (pH 7.0) was concentrated in an ultrafiltration cell driven by nitrogen gas pressure (20 psi) until no further collection of permeate. After ultrafiltration, the protein-deposited membrane was removed and kept at room temperature for 20 min. The membrane was subsequently mounted on a flat glass or plastic surface utilizing a double sided adhesive tape.

Contact angle measurements were performed with a CCD camera Goniometer; the sessile drop technique was utilized. 28 A drop of a suitable diagnostic liquid (2-5 µL) was dispensed by a dosing device onto the sample surface. Probe liquids were water, formamide and 1-bromonephthalene; surface parameters wileyonlinelibrary.com/jctb c 2013 Society of Chemical Industry J Chem Technol Biotechnol 2013; 88: 1421-1428 of such liquids are available in the literature. 27,29 Surface energy calculations were performed according to the acid-base theory, on the basis of the measured contact angle values, by a commercial software package (SCA 20). All the measurements were performed six times, in a dust free environment, at 24 o C.

The CHT was characterized by contact angle measurements using the thin layer wicking technique, which is an alternative tool to the conventional sessile drop method. It utilizes the concept of capillary rise method. The CHT powder was packed in a capillary tube, the rise of the probe liquid is monitored as a function of time to determine the effective pore radius. The contact angle of probe liquid is evaluated using Washburn's equation: 22,23

where h is the liquid rise in the capillary, R eff the effective interstitial pore radius, γ L the surface tension of the liquid, θ the contact angle between the liquid and the solid, η the viscosity of the liquid and t is the time. To evaluate R eff , wicking experiments were made using low-energy apolar liquids, i.e. heptane, octane, decane and dodecane which spreads very faster and forms a zero contact angle. Once the R eff is determined, the contact angle of the probe liquids can be determined by running wicking methods separately for each liquid.

Zeta potential determinations were performed for the proteins under study. Determinations were performed in 20 mmol L -1 phosphate buffer (pH 7.0). Proteins were assayed in solution at a concentration of ≈2 mg mL -1 . The zeta potential values were calculated from electrophoretic mobility data according to Henry's equation:

where U e is the electrophoretic mobility, ε is the dielectric constant, ζ is the zeta potential, η is the viscosity of the dispersant, and f (κa) is the Henry function. 21

The surface charge of CHT is determined by steaming potential utilizing the electrokinetic analyzer EKA (Anton Paar GmbH, Graz, Austria), which is further converted to zeta potential by the following expression: 30

where µ is the viscosity, λ the electric conductivity, ε the dielectric constant, E the streaming potential, and P the pressure difference.

The EKA was filled with a 0.001 mol L -1 KCl-electrolyte solution to measure the zeta potential. The cylindrical cell was utilized to pack an appropriate amount of CHT. The sample amount should be a layer of 2-3 mm thickness and it should allow the passage of electrolyte solution in both directions. The measuring cell was connected to the analyzer, and rinsed with the KCl solution. The pH dependence of the zeta potential was determined in a 0.001 mol L -1 KCl-electrolyte solution to keep the ionic strength constant. The pH value was varied in the range 6.5 to 11 by adding a specific amount of 0.1 mol L -1 KOH solution. 31 Chromatographic experiments CHT slurry (in 200 mmol L -1 dibasic sodium phosphate pH 9.5) was packed in a tricon column (2 mL) as described in the literature. 32 Chromatographic experiments were performed utilizing an ÄKTA FPLC system (GE healthcare, Munich, Germany). Quality of the packing was evaluated by residence time distribution analysis employing 1% acetone as a tracer. 12,33 A 5 mmol L -1 sodium phosphate buffer (pH 6.8) [Buffer A] and 500 mmol L -1 sodium phosphate buffer (pH 6.8) [Buffer B] was utilized. After equilibration with 10 CV of Buffer A, a 200 µL pulse of protein sample (2 mg mL -1 in Buffer A) was injected into the column. Non-bound proteins were eluted with 5 CV of Buffer A and elution was exerted by executing a linear gradient from 0-100% of Buffer B (20 CV). The column was washed with 5 CV Buffer B, followed by sanitization with 5 CV of 1 mol L -1 sodium hydroxide. The column was reequilibrated with 5 CV of Buffer A. Flow rate was 1 mL min -1 (300 cm h -1 ).

Total interaction energy between a particle (protein) and a solid surface (CHT) can be expressed in terms of the extended DLVO theory as:

where U XDLVO is the total interaction energy in aqueous media, U LW is the Lifshitz Van der waals interaction energy, U EL is the electrostatic interaction energy and U AB is the acid base interaction energy between the matrix and the colloidal particle. 11 Surface energy can be calculated from the contact angle measurements using three probe liquids. 21 This contact angle data can be used for evaluating the free energy of interaction ( G LW and G AB ) between two defined surfaces utilizing the Lifshitz van der Waals-acid base equation. G represents the interaction energy per unit area between the adsorbent bead and the protein. Interactions between these two surfaces are evaluated at the closest distance of approximation (h o ≈ 0.167 nm). 34 G values can be utilized to calculate the corresponding energy-distance profile (U vs. H). 11 -13

Contact angle measurements and surface free energy calculations Contact angle determinations of proteins were performed with three probe liquids, i.e. water, formamide and 1bromonephthalene. The protein supported on glass and plastic served for the contact angle measurements in the dehydrated state. The proteins immobilized on ultrafiltration cellulose membrane presented a hydrated state. The surface tension parameters γ LW and γ AB , as well as the electron donating (γ -) and the electron accepting (γ + ) parameters of the probe liquids are available. 34 The contact angle of the adsorbent CHT is taken from the literature, shown in Table 1. 22 The contact angle values determined by the thin layer wicking method are usually considered to be overestimated in comparison with the sessile drop method. 35,36 The contact angle values are higher for the CHT chromatographic beads compared with the other hydrophobic beads available in the literature (Table 1). There could be several reasons for this difference but the most important could be the texture of the backbone chemistry. Agarose 11 and polymethyacrylate 15  contain some water molecules incorporated inside. The CHT bead is made of calcium phosphate and presents a rigid structure.

There are reports available which show that the contact angle determined by the thin layer wicking methods presents almost the same values as measured by sessile drop method. 37 The contact angles of proteins on the three different supports, i.e. glass, plastic and ultracellulose membrane have earlier been published with details. 13 Contact angle measurements with apolar and polar probe liquids has allowed the calculation of the LW, AB, electron donating or base (γ - sv ) and the electron-acceptor or acid (γ + sv ) free energy components by application of the modified Young's-Dupree equation. 13,26,38 1-bromonephthalene can be utilized to calculate the LW component of the protein or matrix:

On the other hand, water and formamide can be employed in combination to calculate the electron-donating and electronaccepting parameters of the sample surface from:

The contact angle values of the proteins are subjected to surface free energy calculations, according to the acid-base approach. 34 The same was also performed for the chromatographic material. The contact angle values of the CHT, obtained from the wicking experiments, are also utilized for the determination of surface tension parameter according to the procedure described in the literature. 37 Calculated parameters reflect the contribution of the various energy components, i.e. Lifhsitz-van der Waals, electronacceptor and electron-donor, to the total surface energy of a defined material. The surface energies of proteins and its relevant observations are described elsewhere. 13 Table 1 shows that the ceramic hydroxyapatite presents a very low surface energy, i.e. 28.6 mJ m -2 compared with other chromatographic materials, which showed a range of total surface energies from ∼40-60 mJ m -2 . 10 -12 It is a common observation that the high contact angle values result in lower surface energy values. 39,40 CHT's lower energy values are also attributed to high contact angle values. A comparison of the surface energies of CHT and some other chromatographic beads is also presented in Table 1. It is observed that for CHT the LW is the main contributing factor to the total surface energy. This reflects the apolar nature of this bead. Similarly, there is a prominent difference between the acid and base parameters of CHT compared with other materials. The low surface energy of CHT might give rise to a decreased interaction with proteins, which will be discussed in the following text.

The surface tension values of the proteins and CHT are used to calculate the free energy of interaction, G LW and G AB , at the shortest distance of approximation (1.67 Å) utilizing the following equations:

A list of these interaction energies is given in Table 2. As stated above the CHT has comparatively lower surface free energy, the observed interaction free energies between proteins and CHT are also low compared with the free energy of interaction between proteins and phenyl sepharose. 13 Table 2 shows the interaction free energies G LW and G AB for proteins with CHT. There are some interesting observations in the data presented here and they are in close agreement with our previous reports.

(a) The apolar interaction energy component ( G LW ) is smaller than the polar component ( G AB ) for all the investigated proteins. (b) There was a common trend observed within the data, i.e. G LW (plastic deposited protein) &gt; G LW (glass deposited protein) &gt; G LW (membrane deposited protein). Generally, the proteins immobilized in the dehydrated state presented higher LW energies than those in the hydrated state. (c) The opposite was observed for the polar energy component ( G AB ). High values were observed for proteins in the hydrated state compared with proteins deposited in the dehydrated state. The higher values for the hydrated state are due to the effect of water molecules bound to proteins. (d) All the proteins presented total interaction energies between 2 mJ m -2 and 27 mJ m -2 . (e) Globally, the G LW values were almost the same, G AB values were comparatively low and G Total interaction energies were also lower than the systems studied earlier.  been reported to be due to the poor adsorption of the protein on plastic support. 13

An understanding of protein interaction with the chromatographic supports can be gained from refined energy to distance profiles (U vs. H). These calculations require basic information from the experimental determination of contact angle and additional information gathered from zeta potential determinations. Zeta potential values for CHT were published elsewhere. 22 The zeta potential values for the set of model proteins under study are also available. 13 Some of the general properties of the model proteins are presented in Table 3. Utilizing the data provided earlier, i.e. G LW , G AB and zeta potential values, interaction energy (U) vs. distance (H) profiles were calculated according to the XDLVO approach. In these calculations all the parameters are considered at the elution conditions. The salt concentration at elution, the hydrodynamic radii and zeta potential of proteins at the de-binding conditions are summarized in Table 4. The zeta potential of CHT at corresponding elution salt concentration is also given in Table 4. It can be observed from this table that the proteins elute at different retention volumes depending on the ion strengths required for screening the surface charge. The surface charge of the chromatographic bead and the hydrodynamics size of the proteins are also affected by the ionic conditions in the operating buffer. As stated earlier, protein interaction with CHT may be a complex phenomenon. Within the data gathered in Table 4 it is seen that protein adsorption to this material is the overall effect of all the parameters mentioned. For instance, it is well understood that materials having the same surface charge will never be attracted, 11 but it is clearly observed here in the case of LAC, BSA and CHY, which are strongly retained by CHT. The opposite is observed for APR and PGase, which are not retained despite having opposite surface charges.

Figure 1(A) and 1(B) depict the secondary energy minimum of interaction between BSA and lactoferrin, respectively, and the adsorbent CHT, under the elution conditions during the chromatographic experiments. The interaction energies minimum for the model protein BSA (Fig. 1(A)) shifts to a deeper range from -0.004kT for the hydrated protein to -0.007kT for the plasticdeposited protein. Medium or equal energy minima were observed for glass-deposited protein, e.g. -0.006kT. The same trend was observed for lactoferrin (Fig. 1(B)), -0.004kT for hydrated proteins to -0.008kT for plastic and glass-deposited protein. Parallel calculations were performed for every protein. It was observed from the calculations that all the proteins showed more or less the same interaction energies, if compared on a single supporting surface. These observations are in accordance with what was expected, that all the proteins should more or less give the same interaction energy minimum at the unbinding environments. It is worth mentioning here that the basic parameters, i.e. contact angle and zeta potential, utilized for the calculations, are the average values considered after several (n = 6) experiments (raw data is not mentioned here).

The zeta potential of the CHT was determined using the streaming potential method. As the pH stability range of CHT is from 6.5-14, 31 this range was kept in mind during the streaming potential measurement.

Figure 2 depicts the zeta potential measurements, performed in duplicate, as a function of pH range. It is prominent from the figure that CHT presents a negative surface charge from -7.0 mV to -20 mV in the measured pH range. It is possible to determine the pI value of material under investigation, but it is avoided in this case, as the CHT cannot be operated in the extreme acidic titration range.     The zeta potential of both the CHT and the model proteins are considered at the ionic strength provided by the elution conditions for the respective proteins (Table 4). The zeta potential at the high ionic strength is calculated from the known correlations. 41

The model proteins utilized in this study were subjected to chromatography, under the conditions stated earlier. Ceramic hydroxyapatite was utilized as the chromatographic adsorbent. The proteins were loaded in a mobile phase containing 5 mmol L -1 NaPO 4, the elution behavior was observed by increasing the salt concentration in the mobile phase to 500 mmol L -1 NaPO 4 . A 20 CV gradient length was used to minimize the influence of mass transfer limitations. The elution profile of human immunoglobulin G during adsorption chromatography utilizing CHT is given in Fig. 3.

As most of the proteins bound to CHT have low ionic strength, at high salts the charges are screened out, and this could facilitate protein elution. On the basis of retention, proteins are classified into several groups, i.e. early, middle and late elution. Some of the larger proteins bind to the CHT column, irrespective of the negative surface charge. This might be as a consequence of the complex nature of the proteins. 32 A list of the retention volumes of all the proteins is given in Table 4.   the model proteins was observed. Experimental retention volumes on CHT, as a function of calculated energy minima, are depicted in Fig. 4, obtained under the conditions provided by the elution conditions. Calculations were performed for every protein, on the three different deposition surfaces (glass, plastic, cellulose).

In our previously reported studies, the correlation of the interaction energies with the retention volumes presented strongly retained proteins showing high interaction energy and loosely retained proteins presenting low interaction energies. 13,15 In this work the surface energetics approach is utilized to explain de-binding conditions. Both the strong and loosely retained proteins at the CHT surface give more or less the same interaction energy. In this piece of work the surface thermodynamics theory is presented from another perspective, i.e. the de-binding condition.

Within the data gathered in this work, three main groups were observed on the basis of retention volumes, but all the groups presented the same average interaction energy, i.e. &lt;|U|&gt; 0.005kT. Applying statistical analysis of three standard deviations (Sigma) from the mean, all the data points are included in the range above or below the average values. The interaction energies for all the proteins supported on the three surfaces i.e. glass (G), plastic (P) and membrane (M) are shown in the figure. The dark grey color above the average (black line) defines the maximum and the light grey line below the average line defines the lower limit of the interaction energies.

There is a negligibly small difference between the interaction energies of the protein eluting very late in the gradient and the proteins showing no retention. So the XDLVO calculations defined a limit that can be considered a cut-off between the binding and de-binding conditions. We can state that proteins having less interaction energy than this will not bind while proteins having more energy than this cut off will cause binding Elution &lt; 0.005kT &lt; Binding

The data presented in this work contains certain deviations. These deviations are due to impurities present in the protein material or due to lack of optimized chromatographic conditions.

According to the results presented in this work, the tool proposed enables an understanding of the chromatographic behavior of proteins, as presented for the hydrophobic supports. 13 An extension of the same method has previously been utilized to predict colloidal particle deposition onto solid surfaces. 5,7,10,18,29,30,32,33 The approach proposed here is simple and can be performed with an ordinary computer, utilizing commercial software. This methodology can lead to better process prediction and adsorbent development with moderate experimental efforts.

A physicochemical approach was presented to study protein interaction with the solid support ceramic hydroxyapatite. All calculations were performed using experimental contact angle and surface charge values according to XDLVO theory. A linear trend was observed between the calculations based on theory and chromatographic behavior of the same proteins, confirming that all the proteins have the same interaction energies at the de-binding conditions. So the proposed method is promising as a predictor of protein separation during adsorption chromatography.

beads are soft and semi-rigid beads that J Chem Technol Biotechnol 2013; 88: 1421-1428 c 2013 Society of Chemical Industry wileyonlinelibrary.com/jctb

10974660, 2013, 8, Downloaded from https://scijournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/jctb.4065 by Riga Technical University, Wiley Online Library on [02/04/2026]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License</full_text>
	<references>
		<reference>
			<title>Arch Biochem Biophys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Tiselius</author>
				<author>S Hjertén</author>
				<author>Levin</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1956</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Mater Sci Mater Med</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Ohta</author>
				<author>H Monma</author>
				<author>J Tanaka</author>
				<author>Eda</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2002</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Chromatogr A</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Shepard</author>
				<author>C Brickman-Stone</author>
				<author>J Schrimsher</author>
				<author>G Koch</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Anal Biochem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Schröder</author>
				<author>L Poole</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2003</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Immunol Methods</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Gagnon</author>
				<author>C Cheung</author>
				<author>P Yazaki</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2009</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Biotechnol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>T Nordström</author>
				<author>A Senkas</author>
				<author>S Eriksson</author>
				<author>Nordstr Lindqvist</author>
				<author>C</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Methods in Enzymology</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Gorbunoff</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1990</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Chromatogr A</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Schubert</author>
				<author>R Freitag</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2009</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Bioseparation</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Giovannini</author>
				<author>R Freitag</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biotechnol Bioprocess Eng</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Vennapusa</author>
				<author>M Aasim</author>
				<author>R Cabrera</author>
				<author>M Fernandez-Lahore</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2009</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Chromatogr A</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Vennapusa</author>
				<author>S Hunegnaw</author>
				<author>R Cabrera</author>
				<author>M Fernandez-Lahore</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2008</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biochem Eng J</title>
			<authors>
				<author>R Vennapusa</author>
				<author>C Tari</author>
				<author>R Cabrera</author>
				<author>M Fernandez-Lahore</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2009</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Int Rev Chem Eng</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Aasim</author>
				<author>G Poondi</author>
				<author>R Vennapusa</author>
				<author>M Fernandez-Lahore</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2010</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Encyclopedia of Industrial Biotechnology</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Fernández Lahore</author>
				<author>M Aguilar</author>
				<author>O Vennapusa</author>
				<author>R Aasim</author>
				<author>M</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2010</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Sep Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Aasim</author>
				<author>N Bibi</author>
				<author>R Vennapusa</author>
				<author>Fernández Lahore</author>
				<author>M</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2012</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Kandori</author>
				<author>M Saito</author>
				<author>T Takebe</author>
				<author>A Yasukawa</author>
				<author>T Ishikawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1995</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Phys Chem Chem Phys</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Kandori</author>
				<author>A Fudo</author>
				<author>T Ishikawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Biomaterials</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Ferraz</author>
				<author>F Monteiro</author>
				<author>A Serro</author>
				<author>B Saramago</author>
				<author>I Gibson</author>
				<author>J Santos</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2001</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Methods in Enzymology</title>
			<authors>
				<author>M Gorbunoff</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1990</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Infect Immun</title>
			<authors>
				<author>E Reynolds</author>
				<author>A Wong</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1983</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Interfacial forces, in Aqueous Media</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Van Oss</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2006</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Cryst Growth</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Y Liu</author>
				<author>W Wu</author>
				<author>G Sethuraman</author>
				<author>G Nancollas</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids Surfaces B: Biointerfaces</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Jacobs</author>
				<author>F Lafolie</author>
				<author>J Herry</author>
				<author>M Debroux</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2007</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Protein Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Van Oss</author>
				<author>R Good</author>
				<author>M Chaudhury</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1986</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Protein Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Van Oss</author>
				<author>L Moore</author>
				<author>R Good</author>
				<author>M Chaudhury</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1985</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Protein Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Van Oss</author>
				<author>C Good</author>
				<author>R</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1988</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Macromol Sci Part A Pure Appl Chem</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Van Oss</author>
				<author>C Good</author>
				<author>R</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1989</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Adv Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Sharma</author>
				<author>R Hanumantha</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2002</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Dispersion Sci Technol</title>
			<authors>
				<author>Van Oss</author>
				<author>C Giese</author>
				<author>R</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2004</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Colloids Surf Physicochem Eng Aspects</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Igarashi</author>
				<author>K Nishizawa</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2007</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>JColloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Bismarck</author>
				<author>M Kumru</author>
				<author>J Springer</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Chromatogr A</title>
			<authors>
				<author>S Schubert</author>
				<author>R Freitag</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2009</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Chromatogr B</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Bak</author>
				<author>Ort Thomas</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2007</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>FEMS Microbiol Rev</title>
			<authors>
				<author>H Van Der Mei</author>
				<author>R Bos</author>
				<author>H Busscher</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1999</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Interfaces, Surfactants and Colloids in Engineering</title>
			<authors>
				<author>K Grundke</author>
				<author>T Bogumil</author>
				<author>T Gietzelt</author>
				<author>H Jacobasch</author>
				<author>D Kwok</author>
				<author>A Neumann</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1996</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Marmur</author>
				<author>R Cohen</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Langmuir</title>
			<authors>
				<author>P Costanzo</author>
				<author>W Wu</author>
				<author>Giese Jr</author>
				<author>R</author>
				<author>Van Oss</author>
				<author>C</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1995</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>C Volpe</author>
				<author>S Siboni</author>
			</authors>
			<date>1997</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Macromolecules</title>
			<authors>
				<author>J Tsibouklis</author>
				<author>P Graham</author>
				<author>P Eaton</author>
				<author>J Smith</author>
				<author>T Nevell</author>
				<author>John Ewen</author>
				<author>R</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2000</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>Langmuir</title>
			<authors>
				<author>I Woodward</author>
				<author>W Schofield</author>
				<author>V Roucoules</author>
				<author>J Badyal</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2003</date>
		</reference>
		<reference>
			<title>J Colloid Interface Sci</title>
			<authors>
				<author>A Huang</author>
				<author>J Berg</author>
			</authors>
			<date>2006</date>
		</reference>
	</references>
	<reference_dois>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/0003-9861(56)90183-7</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1023/A:1015721321912</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0021-9673(00)00626-9</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0003-2697(02)00567-5</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jim.2008.11.021</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0168-1656(99)00038-3</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.chroma.2009.02.074</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1023/A:1011174905511</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/s12257-008-0172-7</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.chroma.2007.11.078</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.bej.2008.08.004</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1002/9780470054581.eib638</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1006/jcis.1995.1373</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1039/a909396f</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0142-9612(01)00059-X</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1128/iai.39.3.1285-1290.1983</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0022-0248(96)01133-5</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.colsurfb.2007.04.008</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/BF01025572</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/BF01025302</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/BF01025248</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1080/00222338908052041</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/S0001-8686(02)00004-0</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1081/DIS-200027316</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.colsurfa.2007.04.004</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1006/jcis.1999.6345</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.chroma.2009.02.074</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jchromb.2006.07.003</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1111/j.1574-6976.1999.tb00396.x</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1007/BFb0114445</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1006/jcis.1997.4816</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/la00005a064</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1006/jcis.1997.5124</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/ma0008185</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1021/la020427e</number>
		<number>DOI-10.1016/j.jcis.2005.08.068</number>
	</reference_dois>
</document>
